Captions proofread by @xiaolai, www.lixiaolai.com
When we finished last time,
we were looking at
John Stuart Mill's
attempt to reply to the critics
of Bentham's Utilitarianism.
In his book Utilitarianism Mill
tries to show that critics
to the contrary it is possible
within the utilitarian framework
to distinguish between
higher and lower pleasures.
It is possible to make qualitative
distinctions of worth and we tested
that idea with the Simpsons
and the Shakespeare excerpts.
And the results of our experiment
seem to call into question
Mill's distinction because a great
many of you reported that you prefer
the Simpsons but that you
still consider Shakespeare to be
the higher or the
worthier pleasure.
That's the dilemma with which
our experiment confronts Mill.
What about Mill's attempt to account
for the especially weighty character
of individual rights and justice
in chapter five of Utilitarianism.
He wants to say that individual rights
are worthy of special respect.
In fact, he goes so far as
to say that justice is
the most sacred part and the
most incomparably binding part
of morality.
But the same challenge could be
put to this part of Mill's defense.
Why is justice the chief part and
the most binding part of our morality?
Well, he says because
in the long run,
if we do justice and
if we respect rights,
society as a whole will be
better off in the long run.
Well, what about that?
What if we have a case where
making an exception and
violating individual rights
actually will make people better off
in the long run?
Is it all right then
to use people?
And there is a further objection
that could be raised
against Mill's case for
justice and rights.
Suppose the utilitarian
calculus in the long run
works out as he says it will such
that respecting people's rights
is a way of making everybody
better off in the long run.
Is that the right reason?
Is that the only reason
to respect people?
If the doctor goes in and
yanks the organs from
the healthy patient who
came in for a checkup
to save five lives,
there would be adverse
effects in the long run.
Eventually, people would
learn about this and
would stop going
in for checkups.
Is it the right reason?
Is the only reason that you as a
doctor won't yank the organs
out of the healthy patient
that you think, well,
if I use him in this way, in the
long run more lives would be lost?
Or is there another reason
having to do with intrinsic respect
for the person as
an individual?
And if that reason matters
and it's not so clear
that even Mill's utilitarianism
can take account of it,
fully to examine these two
worries or objections,
to Mill's defense we
need to push further.
And we need to ask in the case
of higher or worthier pleasures
are there theories of the good
life that can provide
independent moral standards
for the worth of pleasure?
If so, what do they look like?
That's one question.
In the case of justice and rights,
if we suspect that Mill
is implicitly leaning on
notions of human dignity
or respect for person that are
not strictly speaking utilitarian,
we need to look to see whether
there are some stronger theories
of rights that can explain the
intuition which even Mill shares,
the intuition that the reason
for respecting individuals
and not using them goes beyond
even utility in the long run.
Today, we turn to one of those
strong theories of rights.
Strong theories of right say
individuals matter not just as
instruments to be used for
a larger social purpose
or for the sake of
maximizing utility,
individuals are separate beings
with separate lives worthy of respect.
And so it's a mistake,
according to strong theories
or rights, it's a mistake
to think about justice
or law by just adding up
preferences and values.
The strong rights theory
we turn to today is
libertarianism.
Libertarianism takes
individual rights seriously.
It's called libertarianism
because it says
the fundamental individual
right is the right to liberty
precisely because we are
separate individual beings.
We're not available to
any use that the society
might desire or devise
precisely because we are
individual separate
human beings.
We have a fundamental
right to liberty,
and that means a right
to choose freely,
to live our lives
as we please
provided we respect other
people's rights to do the same.
That's the fundamental idea.
Robert Nozick, one of the
libertarian philosophers
we read for this course,
puts it this way:
Individuals have rights.
So strong and far reaching
are these rights that they
raise the question of what,
if anything, the state may do.
So what does libertarianism
say about the role of government
or of the state?
Well, there are three things
that most modern states do
that on the libertarian
theory of rights are
illegitimate or unjust.
One of them is
paternalist legislation.
That's passing laws that
protect people from themselves,
seatbelt laws, for example,
or motorcycle helmet laws.
The libertarian says it
may be a good thing
if people wear seatbelts
but that should be up to
them and the state,
the government, has no
business coercing them,
us, to wear seatbelts
by law.
It's coercion, so no paternalist
legislation, number one.
Number two, no
morals legislation.
Many laws try to promote
the virtue of citizens
or try to give expression to the
moral values of the society as a whole.
Libertarian say that's also a
violation of the right to liberty.
Take the example of, well,
a classic example
of legislation authored in the
name of promoting morality
traditionally have been laws that
prevent sexual intimacy
between gays and lesbians.
The libertarian says nobody
else is harmed,
nobody else's rights
are violated,
so the state should get out
of the business entirely of
trying to promote virtue or
to enact morals legislation.
And the third kind of law or
policy that is ruled out
on the libertarian philosophy
is any taxation or other policy
that serves the purpose of
redistributing income or wealth
from the rich to the poor.
Redistribution is a 每
if you think about it,
says the libertarian is
a kind of coercion.
What it amounts to is theft by
the state or by the majority,
if we're talking about a democracy,
from people who happen to
do very well and
earn a lot of money.
Now, Nozick and other libertarians
allow that there can be
a minimal state that taxes people for
the sake of what everybody needs,
the national defense,
police force,
judicial system to enforce
contracts and property rights,
but that's it.
Now, I want to get your reactions
to this third feature
of the libertarian view.
I want to see who among you agree
with that idea and who disagree and why.
But just to make it concrete
and to see what's at stake,
consider the distribution of
wealth in the United States.
United States is among the most
inegalitarian society as far as
the distribution of wealth of
all the advanced democracies.
Now, is this just or unjust?
Well, what does the
libertarian say?
Libertarian says you can't know
just from the facts I've just given you.
You can't know whether that
distribution is just or unjust.
You can't know just by looking at
a pattern or a distribution or
result whether it's
just or unjust.
You have to know
how it came to be.
You can't just look at the
end stage or the result.
You have to look
at two principles.
The first he calls justice in
acquisition or in initial holdings.
And what that means simply is
did people get the things they used
to make their money fairly?
So we need to know was there
justice in the initial holdings?
Did they steal the land or
the factory or the goods
that enabled them to
make all that money?
If not, if they were entitled
to whatever it was
that enabled them to
gather the wealth,
the first principle is matched.
The second principle is did
the distribution arise from
the operation of free consent,
people buying and trading
on the market?
As you can see, the libertarian
idea of justice corresponds to
a free market conception of justice
provided people got what they used
fairly, didn't steal it, and
provided the distribution results
from the free choice of individual's
buying and selling things,
the distribution is just.
And if not, it's unjust.
So let's, in order to fix
ideas for this discussion,
take an actual example.
Who's the wealthiest person
in the United States 每
wealthiest person in the world?
Bill Gates.
It is. That's right.
Here he is.
You'd be happy, too.
Now, what's his net worth?
Anybody have any idea?
That's a big number.
During the Clinton years, remember
there was a controversy donors?
Big campaign contributors were
invited to stay overnight
in the Lincoln bedroom
at the White House?
I think if you've contributed
twenty five thousand dollars or above,
someone figured out at the median
contribution that got you invited
to stay a night in the
Lincoln bedroom,
Bill Gates could afford to stay in
the Lincoln bedroom every night
for the next sixty six
thousand years.
Somebody else figured out, how much
does he get paid on an hourly basis?
And so they figured out,
since he began Microsoft,
I suppose he worked, what 14
hours per day, reasonable guess,
and you calculate this net wealth,
it turns out that his rate of pay
is over 150 dollars,
not per hour, not per minute
150 dollars, more than
150 dollars per second
which means that if on
his way to the office,
Gates noticed a hundred
dollar bill on the street,
it wouldn't be worth his
time to stop and pick it up.
Now, most of you will say someone
that wealthy surely we can tax them
to meet the pressing needs of people
who lack in education or lack enough
to eat or lack decent housing.
They need it more than he does.
And if you were a utilitarian,
what would you do?
What tax policy would you have?
You'd redistribute in a flash,
wouldn't you?
Because you would know being a
good utilitarian that taking some,
a small amount, he'd scarcely
going to notice it,
but it will make a huge improvement
in the lives and in the welfare
of those at the bottom.
But remember, the libertarian theory
says we can't just add up an
aggregate preferences and
satisfactions that way.
We have to respect persons and if he
earned that money fairly without
violating anybody else's rights in
accordance with the two principles
of justice in acquisition and
in justice in transfer,
then it would be wrong, it would be
a form of coercion to take it away
Michael Jordan is not as
wealthy as Bill Gates but he did
pretty well for himself.
You wanna see Michael Jordan.
There he is.
His income alone in one year was
31 million dollars and then
he made another 47 million dollars
in endorsements for a Nike
and other companies.
So his income was, in
one year, $78 million.
To require him to pay, let's say,
a third of his earnings to
the government to support good causes
like food and health care and
housing and education for the poor,
that's coercion, that's unjust.
That violates his rights.
And that's why redistribution
is wrong.
Now, how many agree with that argument,
agree with the libertarian argument
that redistribution for the sake of
trying to help the poor is wrong?
And how many disagree
with that argument?
All right, let's begin with
those who disagree.
What's wrong with the libertarian
case against redistribution?
Yes.
I think these people like
Michael Jordan have received
we're talking about working within
a society and they receive
a larger gift from the society and
they have a larger obligation
in return to give that through
redistribution, you know,
you can say that Michael Jordan
may work just as hard as some who works,
you know, doing laundry 12 hours,
14 hours a day, but he's receiving more.
I don't think it's fair to say that,
you know, it's all on him,
on his, you know, inherent,
you know, hard work.
All right, let's hear from defenders
of libertarianism.
Why would it be wrong in principle
to tax the rich to help the poor?
Go ahead.
My name is Joe and I
collect skateboards.
I've since bought a
hundred skateboards.
I live in a society of
a hundred people.
I'm the only one with skateboards.
Suddenly, everyone decides
they want a skateboard.
They come to my
house, they take my
they take 99 of
my skateboards.
I think that is unjust.
Now, I think in certain circumstances
it becomes necessary
to overlook that unjustness,
perhaps condone that injustice
as in the case of the cabin boy
being killed for food.
If people are on the verge of dying,
perhaps it is necessary to
overlook that injustice,
but I think it's important
to keep in mind that we're still
committing injustice
by taking people's
belongings or assets.
Are you saying that taxing
Michael Jordan, say,
at a 33 percent tax rate for good
causes to feed the hungry is theft?
I think it's unjust.
Yes, I do believe it's theft but perhaps
it is necessary to condone that theft.
But it's theft.
Yes.
Why is it theft, Joe?
Because --
Why is it like your
collection of skateboards?
It's theft because, or at least,
in my opinion and by
the libertarian opinion he earned that
money fairly and it belongs to him.
So to take it from him
is by definition theft.
All right, let's hear
if there is＃
Who wants to reply to Joe?
Yes, go ahead.
I don't think this is necessarily
a case in which you have 99 skateboards
and the government＃
or you have a hundred skateboards and
the government is taking 99 of them.
It's like you have more skateboards
than there are days in a year.
You have more skateboards that
you're going to be able to use
in your entire lifetime and the
government is taking part of those.
And I think that if you are operating
in a society in which
the government's not 每
in which the government doesn't
redistribute wealth, then that
allows for people to amass
so much wealth that people who
haven't started from this very
the equal footing in our hypothetical
situation, that doesn't exist
in our real society get undercut
for the rest of their lives.
So you're worried that if there isn't
some degree of redistribution
of some or left at the bottom,
there will be no genuine
equality of opportunity.
All right, the idea that
taxation is theft,
Nozick takes that point
one step further.
He agrees that it's theft.
He's more demanding than Joe.
Joe says it is theft, maybe in an
extreme case it's justified,
maybe a parent is justified in stealing
a loaf of bread to feed his
or her hungry family.
So Joe I would say, what
would you call yourself,
a compassionate
quasi-libertarian?
Nozick says, if you
think about it,
taxation amounts to the
taking of earnings.
In other words, it means taking
the fruits of my labor.
But if the state has the right to take
my earning or the fruits of my labor,
isn't that morally the same as
according to the state the right
to claim a portion of my labor?
So taxation actually is morally
equivalent to forced labor
because forced labor involves the
taking of my leisure, my time,
my efforts, just as taxation takes
the earnings that I make with my labor.
And so, for Nozick and
for the libertarians,
taxation for redistribution is theft,
as Joe says, but not only theft is
morally equivalent to laying claim to
certain hours of a person's
life and labor, so it's morally
equivalent to forced labor.
If the state has a right to
claim the fruits of my labor,
that implies that it really has
an entitlement to my labor itself.
And what is forced labor?
Forced labor, Nozick points
out, is what, is slavery,
because if I don't have the right,
the sole right to my own labor,
then that's really to say that
the government or the
political community is
a part owner in me.
And what does it mean for the
state to be a part owner in me?
If you think about it,
it means that I'm a slave,
that I don't own myself.
So what this line of reasoning brings
us to is the fundamental principle
that underlies the libertarian
case for rights.
What is that principle?
It's the idea that I own myself.
It's the idea of self possession
if you want to take right seriously.
If you don't want to just regard
people as collections of preferences,
the fundamental moral idea to which
you will be lead is the idea
that we are the owners or the
propietors of our own person,
and that's why
utilitarianism goes wrong.
And that's why it's wrong to yank the
organs from that healthy patient.
You're acting as if that patient belongs
to you or to the community.
But we belong to ourselves.
And that's the same reason that
it's wrong to make laws
to protect us from ourselves or
to tell us how to live,
to tell us what virtues we
should be governed by,
and that's also why it's wrong to tax
the rich to help the poor
even for good causes,
even to help those
who are displaced by
the Hurricane Katrina.
Ask them to give charity.
But if you tax them, it's
like forcing them to labor.
Could you tell Michael Jordan he has
to skip the next week's games
and go down to help the people
displaced by Hurricane Katrina?
Morally, it's the same.
So the stakes are very high.
So far we've heard some objections
to the libertarian argument.
But if you want to reject it,
you have to break in to
this chain of reasoning which
goes, taking my earnings
is like taking my labor,
but taking my labor
is making me a slave.
And if you disagree with
that, you must believe in
the principle of
self possession.
Those who disagree,
gather your objections
and we'll begin with
them next time.
Anyone like to take
up that point? Yes.
I feel like when you live in a
society, you'd give up that right.
I mean, technically, if I want to
personally go out and kill someone
because they offend me,
that is self possession.
Because I live in a society,
I cannot do that.
Victoria, are you questioning the
fundamental premise of self possession?
Yes. I think that you don't
really have self possession
if you choose to live in a society
because you cannot just discount
the people around you.
We were talking last time
about libertarianism.
I want to go back to the arguments
for and against
the redistribution of income.
But before we do that, just
one word about the minimal state,
Milton Friedman, the
libertarian economist,
he points out that many
of the functions that
we take for granted as properly
belonging to government don't.
They are paternalist.
One example he gives
is social security.
He says it's a good idea for people
to save for their retirement
during their earning years
but it's wrong.
It's a violation of people's liberty
for the government to force everyone
whether they want to or not to
put aside some earnings today
for the sake of their retirement.
If people want to take the chance
or if people want to live big today
and live a poor retirement,
that should be their choice.
They should be free to make those
judgments and take those risks.
So even social security would still
be at odds with the minimal state
that Milton Friedman argued for.
It sometimes thought that collective
goods like police protection
and fire protection will inevitably
create the problem of free riders
unless they're publicly provided.
But there are ways to
prevent free riders.
There are ways to restrict even
seemingly collective goods
like fire protection.
I read an article a while back
about a private fire company,
the Salem Fire Corporation,
in Arkansas.
You can sign up with the
Salem Fire Corporation,
pay a yearly subscription fee,
and if your house catches on fire,
they will come and
put out the fire.
But they won't put
out everybody's fire.
They will only put it out
if it's a fire in the home
of a subscriber or if it starts
to spread and to threaten
the home of a subscriber.
The newspaper article just told
the story of a home owner
who had subscribed to this
company in the past but failed
to renew his subscription.
His house caught on fire.
The Salem Fire Corporation
showed up with its trucks
and watched the house burn,
just making sure that
it didn't spread.
The fire chief was asked, well,
he wasn't exactly the fire chief.
I guess he was the CEO.
He was asked how can you stand
by with fire equipment and allow
a person's home
to burn?
He replied, once we verified there
was no danger to a member's property,
we had no choice but to back
off according to our rules.
If we responded to all fires, he said,
there would be no incentive
to subscribe.
The homeowner in this case tried
to renew his subscription
at the scene of the fire.
But the head of the company refused.
You can't wreck your car, he said,
and then buy insurance for it later.
So even public goods that
we take for granted
that's being within the
proper province of government
can many of them in
principle be isolated,
made exclusive to those who pay.
That's all to do with the
question of collective goods
and the libertarians injunction
against paternalism.
But let's go back now to the
arguments about redistribution.
Now, underlying the libertarian's
case for the minimal state
is a worry about coercion,
but what's wrong with coercion?
The libertarian
offers this answer:
To coerce someone, to use some person
for the sake of the general welfare
is wrong because it calls into question
the fundamental fact that we own ourselves
the fundamental moral fact of
self possession or self ownership.
The libertarian's argument against
redistribution begins with
this fundamental idea that
we own ourselves.
Nozick says that if the society
as a whole can go to Bill Gates
or go to Michael Jordan and
tax away a portion of their wealth,
what the society is really asserting
is a collective property right
in Bill Gates or
in Michael Jordan.
But that violates the fundamental
principle that we belong to ourselves.
Now, we've already heard a number of
objections to the libertarian argument.
What I would like to do today is
to give the libertarians among us
a chance to answer the objections
that have been raised and some have been
some have already identified themselves
and have agreed to come and make
the case for libertarianism
to reply to the objections
that have been raised.
So raise your hand if you are
among the libertarians
who's prepared to stand up for the
theory and respond to the objections.
You are?
Alex Harris.
Alex Harris, who's been
a star on the web blog.
All right, Alex, come here.
Stand up.
Come.
We'll create a libertarian
corner over here.
And who else?
Other libertarians who will join.
What's your name?
John.
John?
Sheffield.
John Sheffield.
Who else wants to join?
Other brave libertarians who
are prepared to take on
Yes, what's your name?
Julia Rotto.
Julia, come join us over there.
Now, while the 每
while team libertarian
Julie, John, Alex.
While team libertarian is
gathering over there,
let me just summarize the main
objections that I've heard
in class and on the website.
Objection number one每
and here I'll come down to-
I wanna talk to team
libertarian over here.
So objection number one is that
the poor need the money more.
That's an obvious objection,
a lot more than -- thanks 每
than do Bill Gates
and Michael Jordan.
Objection number two, it's not
really slavery to tax because
at least in a democratic society
it's not a slave holder.
It's congress.
It's a democratic〞
you're smiling,
Alex, already.
You're confident you can
reply to all of these?
So taxation by consent of the
governed is not coercive.
Third, some people have said don't
the successful like Gates
owe a debt to society for their success
that they repay by paying taxes.
Who wants to respond
to the first one,
the poor need the
money more?
All right, and you're?
John.
John. All right, John,
what's the, here I'll hold it.
All right.
The poor need the money more.
That's quite obvious.
I could use the money.
You know, I certainly wouldn't
mind if Bill Gates give
me a million dollars.
I mean, I'd take a thousand.
But at some point you
have to understand that
the benefits of redistribution of
wealth don't justify the initial
violation of the property right.
If you look at the argument
the poor need the money more,
at no point in that argument
do you contradict the fact that
we've extrapolated from,
agreed upon principles
that people own themselves.
We've extrapolated that people have
property rights and so whether or not
it would be a good thing
or a nice thing or even
a necessary thing for the
survival of some people,
we don't see that that justifies
the violation of the right
that we've logically
extrapolated.
Good. Okay.
And so that also, I mean,
there still exist this institution
of like individual philanthropy.
Milton Friedman makes
this argument-
All right, so Bill Gates can
give to charity if he wants to.
Right.
But it would still be
wrong to coerce him.
Exactly.
To meet the needs of the poor.
Are the two of you
happy with that reply?
Anything to add?
All right, go ahead. Julie?
Julia, yes.
I think I can also add, it's okay.
I guess I could add that there's a
difference between needing something
and deserving something.
I mean, in an ideal society
everyone's needs would be met
but here we're arguing what do
we deserve as a society and, yeah.
And the poor don't deserve
don't deserve the benefits
that would flow from taxing
Michael Jordan to help them.
Based on what we've covered
here I don't think you deserve
something like that.
All right, let me push you
a little bit on that, Julia.
The victims of Hurricane Katrina
are in desperate need of help.
Would you say that they don't
deserve help that would come
from the federal government
through taxation?
Okay, that's a difficult question.
I think this is a case where they need
help, not deserve it, but I think,
again, if you had a certain level of
requirements to meet sustenance,
you're gonna need help,
like, if you don't have food
or a place to live,
that's a case of need.
So need is one thing
and deserve is another.
Exactly.
All right.
Who would like to reply?
Yes.
Going back to the first point
that you made about the
property rights of individual.
The property rights are established
and enforced by the government,
which is a democratic government,
and we have representatives
to enforce those rights.
If you live in a society that
operates under those rules,
then it should be up to the
government to decide how
those resources[inaudible]taxation
are distributed because it is
through the consent
of the government.
If you disagree with it,
you don't have to live
in that society
where that operates.
All right, good, so,
and tell me your name.
Raul.
Raul is pointing out, actually,
Raul is invoking point number two.
If the taxation is by the
consent of the governed,
it's not coerced.
It's legitimate.
Bill Gates and Michael Jordan
are citizens of the United States.
They get to vote for congress.
They get to vote their
policy convictions just
like everybody else.
Who would like to take
that one on? John?
Basically, what the libertarians
are objecting to in this case is
the middle 80 percent deciding
what the top ten percent
are doing for the
bottom ten percent.
Wait, wait, wait, John.
Majority.
Don't you believe in democracy?
Well, right, but at some point --
Don't you believe in,
I mean, you say 80 percent,
10 percent majority.
Majority rule is what?
The majority.
Exactly, but --
In a democracy.
Aren't you for democracy?
Yes, I'm for democracy, but
Hang on, hang on, hang on.
Democracy and mob rule
aren't the same thing.
Mob rule?
Mob rule, exactly.
In an open society you have
a recourse to address that
through your representatives.
And if the majority of the consent
of those who are governed
doesn't agree with you,
then you know,
you're choosing to live in a
society and you have to operate
under what the majority
the society concludes.
All right, Alex,
on democracy.
What about that?
The fact that I have one, you
know, five hundred thousandth
of the vote for one representative
in congress is not the same thing
as my having the ability to
decide for myself how
to use my property rights.
I'm a drop in the bucket
and, you know, well --
You might lose the vote.
Exactly.
And they might take --
And I will.
I mean,
I don't have the decision
right now of whether or not
to pay taxes.
If I don't, I get locked in jail or they
tell me to get out of the country.
But, Alex, Alex, let me make
a small case for democracy.
And see what you would say.
Why can't you, we live in a
democratic society with
freedom of speech.
Why can't you take to the Hustings,
persuade your fellow citizens
that taxation is unjust
and try to get a majority?
I don't think that people
should be, should have to
convince 280 million others
simply in order to exercise
their own rights, in order to not
have their self ownership violated.
I think people should be able
to do that without having
to convince 280 million people.
Does that mean you are
against democracy as a whole?
I -- no.
I just believe in a very
limited form of democracy
whereby we have a constitution
that severely limits the scope
of what decisions can
be made democratically.
All right, so you're saying
that democracy is fine
except where fundamental
rights are involved.
Yes.
And I think you could win.
If you're going on the Hustings,
let me add one element
to the argument
you might make.
You can say put aside the
economic debates, taxation.
Suppose the individual right
to religious liberty were
at stake, then, Alex, you
could say, on the Hustings.
Surely, you would all agree that
we shouldn't put the right to
individual liberty up to a vote.
Yeah, that's exactly right,
and that's why we have a
constitutional amendments.
and why do we make it so hard
to amend our constitution.
So you would say that the
right to private property,
the right of Michael Jordan to
keep all the money he makes
at least to protect it from
redistribution is the same
kind of right with the same
kind of weight as the right
to freedom of speech,
the right to religious liberty,
rights that should trump
what the majority wants.
Absolutely.
The reason why we have a right
to free speech is because
we have a right to own ourselves,
to exercise our voice
in any way that we choose.
All right, good.
All right, so there we〞
All right, who would like to
respond to that argument
about democracy being-
Okay, up there. Stand up.
I think comparing religion
economics it's not the same thing.
The reason why Bill Gates is able
to make so much money is because
we live in an economically and
socially stable society.
And if the government didn't provide
for the poor as ten percent
as you say through taxation,
then we would need more money
for police to prevent crime
and so, either way,
there would be more taxes
taken away to provide
what you guys call the necessary
things that the government provides.
What's your name?
Anna.
Anna, let me ask you this.
Why is the fundamental right
to religious liberty different
from the right Alex asserts
as a fundamental right
to private property and to
keep what I earn?
What's the difference
between the two?
Because you wouldn't have-
You wouldn't be able to make money,
you wouldn't be able to own property
if there wasn't that socially,
like, if society wasn't stable,
and that's completely
different from religion.
That's like something personal,
something that you can practice
on your own in your own home
or like me practicing my religion
is not going to affect
the next person.
But if I'm poor and
I'm desperate,
like I might commit a crime to feed
my family and that can affect others.
Okay, good, thank you.
Would it be wrong for someone
to steal a loaf of bread
to feed his starving family?
Is that wrong?
I believe that it is.
This is --
Let's take a quick poll
of the three of you.
You say, yes, it is wrong.
Yes.
John?
It violates property rights.
It's wrong.
Even to save a starving family?
I mean there are definitely
other ways around that
and by justifying, no,
hang on, hang on,
before you laugh at me.
Before justifying the
act of stealing,
you have to look at violating the right
that we've already agreed exists,
the right of self possession and
the possession of, I mean,
your own things.
We agree on property rights.
All right, we
agree at stealing.
Yeah, we agree at stealing.
So property rights
is not the issue.
All right, but --
So why is it wrong to steal
even to feed your starving family?
Sort of the original argument
that I made in the very first
question you asked.
The benefits of an action don't
justify, don't make the action just.
Do what, what would
you say, Julia?
Is it all right to steal a
loaf of bread to feed a
starving family or to steal a drug
that your child needs to survive?
I think, I'm okay with
that, honestly.
Even from the
libertarian standpoint,
I think that, okay, saying
that you can just take money
arbitrarily from people who
have a lot to go to this pool
of people who need it,
but you have an individual
who's acting on their own behalf
to kind of save themselves and then
I think you said they, for
any idea like self possession,
they are also in charge of protecting
themselves and keeping themselves
alive so, therefore, even for
a libertarian standpoint,
that might be okay.
All right, that's good,
that's good.
All right, what about
number three up here?
Isn't it the case that
the successful,
the wealthy, owe a debt.
They didn't do that
all by themselves.
They had to cooperate with other
people that they owe a debt
to society and that that's
expressed in taxation.
You wanna take that on, Julia?
Okay, this one, I believe
that there is not a debt to society
in the sense that how did
these people become wealthy?
They did something that
society valued highly.
I think that society has already
been giving, been providing for them
if anything, I think it's＃
everything is cancelled out.
They provided a service to society
and society responded by somehow
they got their wealth,
so I think that --
So be concrete.
In the case of Michael Jordan, some＃
I mean, to illustrate your point.
There were people who helped him
make the money, the teammates,
the coach, people who
taught him how to play.
But they've, you're saying, but they've
all been paid for their services.
Exactly, and society derived a lot
of benefit and pleasure from watching
Michael Jordan play.
I think that that's how
he paid his debt to society.
All right, good.
Who would, anyone likes
to take up that point? Yes.
I think that there's a problem
here with that we're assuming
that a person has self possession
when they live in a society.
I feel like when you live in a
society, you give up that right.
I mean, technically, if I want to
personally go out and kill someone
because they offend me,
that is self possession.
Because I live in a society
I cannot do that.
I think it's kind of equivalent to
say because I have more money,
I have resources that
can save people's lives,
is it not okay for the government
to take that from me?
Self possession only to a certain
extent because I'm living in a society
where I have to take account
of the people around me.
So are you question,
what's your name?
Victoria.
Victoria, are you questioning the
fundamental premise of self possession?
Yes.
I think that you don't really
have self possession
if you choose to live in a society
because you cannot just discount
the people around you.
All right, I want to quickly get
the response of the libertarian
team to the last point.
The last point builds on, well,
maybe it builds on Victoria's
suggestion that we don't own ourselves
because it says that Bill Gates
is wealthy, that Michael Jordan
makes a huge income,
isn't wholly their own doing.
It's the product of a lot of luck
and so we can't claim that they
morally deserve all
the money they make.
Who wants to reply to that?
Alex?
You certainly could make
the case that it is not＃
their wealth is not appropriate
to the goodness in their hearts,
but that's not really the
morally relevant issue.
The point is that they have
received what they have through
the free exchange of people
who have given them their holdings,
usually in exchange for
providing some other service
Good enough.
I want to try to sum up what
we've learned from this discussion,
but, first, let's thank John, Alex,
and Julia for a really wonderful job.
Toward the end of the discussion
just now Victoria challenged
the premise of this line of
reasoning that's libertarian logic.
Maybe, she suggested, we don't
own ourselves after all.
If you reject the libertarian
case against redistribution,
there would seem to be an incentive
to break in to the libertarian line
of reasoning at the earliest,
at the most modest level,
which is why a lot of people
disputed that taxation
is morally equivalent
to forced labor.
But what about the big claim,
the premise, the big idea
underlying the
libertarian argument?
Is it true that we own ourselves
or can we do without that idea
and still avoid what libertarians
want to avoid creating a society
in an account of justice where
some people can be just used
for the sake of other people's welfare
or even for the sake of the general good?
Libertarians combat the utilitarian
idea of using people as means
for the collective happiness by
saying the way to put a stop
to that utilitarian logic of
using persons is to resort to
the intuitively powerful idea
that we are the proprietors
of our own person.
That's Alex and Julia and
John and Robert Nozick.
What are the consequences
for a theory of justice
and in account of rights
of calling into question
the idea of self possession?
Does it mean that we're back to
utilitarianism and using people
and aggregating preferences and
pushing the fat man off the bridge?
Nozick doesn't himself fully develop
the idea of self possession.
He borrows it from an
earlier philosopher, John Locke.
John Locke accounted for the rise
of private property from the state
of nature by a chain of reasoning
very similar to the one that Nozick
and the libertarians use.
John Locke said private property arises
because when we mix our labor with things,
unowned things, we come to aquire
a property right in those things.
And the reason?
The reason is that we
own our own labor,
and the reason for that?
We are the proprietors, the
owners of our own person.
And so in order to examine the
moral force of the libertarian claim
that we own ourselves,
we need to turn to
the English political philosopher,
John Locke, and examine his account
of private property and self ownership
and that's what we'll do next time.