Captions proofread by @xiaolai, www.lixiaolai.com
JUSTICE
with Michael Sandel
Arguing Affirmative Action
Last time,
we were discussing the distinction,
that Rawls draws between
two different types of claims.
Claims of moral desert
on the one hand,
and of entitlement to legitimate
expectations on the other.
Rawls argued that
it's a mistake to think that
distributive justice is a
matter of moral desert.
A matter of rewarding people
according to their virtue.
Today we're going to
explore that question
of moral desert and its
relation to distributive justice.
Not in connection
with incoming wealth,
but in its connection
with opportunities.
With hiring decisions and
admission standards.
And so we turn to the case,
of affirmative action.
You read about the case
of Cheryl Hopwood.
She applied for admission to the
University of Texas Law School.
Cheryl Hopwood had worked her
way through high school,
she didn't come from
an affluent family,
she put herself through
community college,
and California State
University at Sacramento.
She achieved a 3.8 grade
point average there,
later moved to Texas,
became a resident,
took the law school
admissions test,
did pretty well on that,
and she applied to the
University of Texas Law School.
She was turned down.
She was turned down at a time
when the University of Texas,
was using an affirmative
action admissions policy.
A policy that took into account,
race and ethnic background.
The University of Texas said,
"40 percent of the population of Texas
is made up of African Americans
and Mexican Americans.
It's important that we, as a law school,
have a diverse student body.
And so we are going to
take into account,
not only grades and test scores,
but also the demographic makeup of our class
including, its race and ethnic profile."
The result, and this is what
Hopwood complained about,
the result of that policy,
is that some applicants to the
University of Texas Law School,
with a lower academic index,
which includes grades and test scores,
than hers, were admitted.
And she was turned down.
She said, she argued, "I'm just being
turned down because I'm white.
If I weren't, if I were a
member of a minority group,
with my grades and test scores
I would had been admitted."
And the statistics, the admissions
statistics that came out in the trial,
confirmed that African American and
Mexican American applicants that year,
who had, her grades and test scores,
were admitted.
It went to Federal Court.
Now, put aside the law,
let's consider it from the
standpoint of justice and morality.
Is it fair, or it unfair?
Does Cheryl Hopwood have a case?
A legitimate complaint?
Were her rights violated,
by the admissions policy of the law school?
How many say,
how many would rule for the law school,
and say that it was just to consider race and
ethnicity as a factor in admissions?
How many would rule
for Cheryl Hopwood
and say "her rights were violated?"
So here we have a pretty even split.
Alright, now I want to hear from a
defender of Cheryl Hopwood. Yes?
You're basing something
that's an arbitrary factor,
you know, Cheryl couldn't control
the fact that she was white,
or not in a minority.
And therefore, you know, it's not as if it
was like a test score that she worked hard
to try and show that she could,
you know, put that out there,
you know, that she had no
control over her race.
Good. And what're your name?
- Bree.
Okay. Bree, stay right there.
Now let's find someone
who has an answer for Bree.
Yes? - There are discrepancies
in the educational system.
And the majority of the time,
I know this in New York City,
the schools that minorities go to,
are not as well-funded,
are not as well-supplied,
as white schools.
And so there is going
to be a discrepancy,
naturally, between minorities
and between whites.
If they go to better schools.
And they will not do as well on exams
because they haven't had as much help.
Because of the worst
school systems.
Let me just interrupt you to,
tell me your name?
Aneesha.
- Aneesha. Aneesha, you're pointing out
that minority kids may have
gone in some cases
to schools that didn't give them the same
educational opportunity as kids from
affluent families.
- Yes.
And so the test
scores they got,
may actually not represent
their true potential.
Because they didn't receive
the same kind of help
that they might have received had they
gone to a school with better funding.
Good, alright. Aneesha
has raised the point
that colleges still should choose
for the greatest academic scholarly promise
but in reading the test
scores and grades,
they should take into account
the different meaning
those tests and grades have,
in the light of educational
disadvantage in the background.
So that's one argument in defense
of affirmative action, Aneesha's argument.
Correcting for the effects
of unequal preparation.
Educational disadvantage.
Now, there are other arguments.
Suppose, just to identify whether
there is a competing principle here.
Suppose there are two candidates,
who did equally well on
the tests and grades.
Both of whom went
to first rate schools.
Two candidates,
among those candidates,
would it be unfair for the college
or university, for Harvard, to say,
"we still want diversity along racial
and ethnic dimensions,
even where we are not
correcting for the effects
on test scores of
educational disadvantage."
What about in that case, Bree?
If it's that's one thing that puts,
you know someone over the edge,
then it's, I guess that would be,
you know, justifiable.
If everything else about
the individual first, though,
everything to consider about that
person's you know, talents,
and where they come from, and who they are
without these arbitrary factors, is the same.
Without these 'arbitrary factors',
you call them.
But before you were suggesting, Bree,
that race and ethnicity are arbitrary factors
outside the control of the applicants.
- True, I would agree with that.
And your general principle is that admissions
shouldn't reward arbitrary factors,
over which people have no control.
- Right.
Alright. Who else, who else
would like to, thank you both.
Who else would like to get
into this, what do you say?
Well, first of all, I'm for
affirmative action temporarily,
but, for two reasons.
First of all, you have to
look at the university's purpose.
It is to educate their students.
And I feel that different races,
people coming from different races have
different backgrounds and they
contribute differently to the education.
And second of all, when you say
that they have equal backgrounds,
that's not true when you look
at the broader picture,
and you look at slavery
and this is kind of a reparation.
I think affirmative action is a temporary
solution to alleviate history,
and the wrongs done to
African Americans in particular.
And what's your name?
David.
- David. You say that affirmative action
is justified at least for now as a way
of compensating for past injustice.
The legacy of slavery and segregation.
- Right.
Who wants to take
on that argument?
We need now a critic
of affirmative action.
Yes, go ahead.
I think that what happened in the past
has no bearing on what happens today.
I think that discriminating based
on race should always be wrong.
Whether you're discriminating
against one group or another.
Just because our ancestors
did something,
doesn't mean that that should have any
effect on what happens with us today.
Alright, good. I'm sorry, your name is?
- Kate.
Kate. Alright, who has
an answer for Kate?
Yes.
- I just wanted to comment
and say that,
- Tell us your name.
My name is Mansur. Because of slavery,
because of past injustices today,
we have a higher proportion of African
Americans who are in poverty,
who face less opportunities
than white people.
So because of slavery 200 years ago,
and because of Jim Crow,
and because of segregation,
today we have injustice based on race.
Kate?
- I think that there are differences,
obviously, but the way to fix those
differences is not by some artificial fixing
of the result.
You need to fix the problem.
So we need to address
differences in education,
and differences in upbringing
with programs like Head Start,
and giving more funding
to lower income schools
rather than just trying
to fix the result,
so it makes it look like it's
equal when it's really it isn't.
Yes.
Well, with regard to affirmative
action based on race,
I just want to say that white people
have had their own affirmative action
in this country for
more than 400 years.
It's called 'nepotism' and 'quid pro quo'.
So there's nothing wrong with correcting
the injustice and discrimination
that's been done to black
people for 400 years.
Good. Tell us your name.
- Hannah.
Hannah. Alright who has
an answer for Hannah?
And just to add
to Hannah's point,
because we need now
someone to respond,
Hannah, you could have
also mentioned legacy admissions.
Exactly.
I was going to say,
if you disagree
with affirmative action,
you should disagree with
legacy admission because
it's obvious from looking around here
that there are more white legacies
than black legacies in the
history of Harvard University.
And explain what legacy admissions are.
Well, legacy admissions is giving
an advantage to someone
who has an arbitrary privilege of their
parent having attended the university
to which they're applying.
Alright, so a reply for Hannah.
Yes, in the balcony, go ahead.
First of all, if affirmative action
is making up for past injustice,
how do you explain minorities that were
not historically discriminated against
in the United States who
get these advantages?
In addition, you could argue
that affirmative action perpetuates
divisions between the races rather
than achieve the ultimate goal
of race being an irrelevant
factor in our society.
And what, tell us your name.
Danielle.
- Hannah.
I disagree with that because
I think that by promoting diversity
in an institution like this,
you further educate all of the students,
especially the white students
who grew up in predominately
white areas.
It's certainly a form of education to be
exposed to people from different backgrounds.
And you put white students at an inherent
disadvantage when you surround them
only with their own kind.
Why should race necessarily
be equated with diversity?
There are so many other forms,
why should we assume
that race makes people different?
Again, that's perpetuating the idea of
racial division within our universities
and our society.
- Hannah?
With regard to
African American people
being given a special advantage,
it's obvious that they bring
something special to the table,
because they have a
unique perspective
just as someone from a different religion or
socio-economic background would, as well.
As you say, there are many
different types of diversity.
There's no reason that racial diversity
should be eliminated from that criteria.
Yes, go ahead.
Racial discrimination
is illegal in this country,
and I believe that it was African
American leaders themselves,
when Martin Luther King said he wanted to
be judged not on the color of skin,
but by the content of his character,
his merit, his achievements.
And I just think that,
to decide solely based on someone's race
is just inherently unfair.
I mean, if you want to correct based
on disadvantaged backgrounds,
that's fine, but there are also
disadvantaged white people as well.
It shouldn't matter if you're white or black.
- Tell us your name.
Ted. - Ted, - Yes.
- Think of Hopwood.
It's unfair to count race or, I assume
you would also say, ethnicity or religion?
Yes. - Do you think she has
a right to be considered
according to her grades
and test scores alone?
No. There is more
to it than that.
Universities need
to promote diversity.
So you agree with the goal
of promoting diversity?
There's ways to promote diversity besides
discriminating against people solely
based on a factor they cannot control.
Alright, so what makes it wrong,
is that she can't
control her race.
She can't control the
fact that she's white.
That's the heart of
the unfairness to her.
Bree made a similar point.
That basing admissions on factors
that people can't control,
is fundamentally unfair.
What do you say?
There's a lot of things
you can't control,
and if you don't
for it based on merit,
like just based on
your test scores,
a lot of what you can achieve has
to do with family background,
that you were raised in.
If both of your parents
were scholarly,
then you have more of
chance of actually
of being more scholarly yourself
and getting those grades.
And you can't control what kind
of family you were born into.
Alright good, that's a great
rejoinder, what's your name?
Da.
- Da.
Ted, are you against advantages that come
from the family you were born into?
What about legacy admissions?
I do believe that in terms
of a legacy admission
you shouldn't have
a special preference,
I mean there is a legacy admission you
could argue is another part,
versus you could day it's
important to have a small percentage
of people that have a several generation
family attendance at a place like Harvard.
However that should not be
an advantage factor like race,
it should just be another part
promoting diversity.
Should it count at all?
I think that,
- Alumni status, should it count at all, Ted?
Yes. It should count.
Alright, I want to step back for a
moment from these arguments.
Thank you all for
these contributions.
We're going to come
back to you.
If you've listened carefully
I think you will have noticed
three different arguments
emerge from this discussion.
In defense of considering
race and ethnicity
as a factor in admissions.
One argument has to do
with correcting for the effects,
for the effects of
educational disadvantage.
That was Aneesha's argument.
This is what we might call
the corrective argument.
Correcting for differences
in educational background,
the kind of school
people went to.
The opportunities they
had and so on.
That's one argument.
What's worth noticing though,
is that argument is consistent
in principle with the idea
that only academic promise and scholarly
potential should count in admissions.
We just need to go beyond
test scores and grades alone,
to get a true estimate
of academic promise
and scholarly ability.
That's the first argument.
Then we heard a second
argument that said
affirmative action is justified
even where there may not be
the need to correct for
educational disadvantage
in a particular applicant's case.
It's justified as a way of
compensating for past wrongs,
for historic injustices.
So that's a compensatory argument.
Compensating for past wrongs.
Then we heard, a third,
a different argument,
for affirmative action,
from Hannah and others,
that argued in the name of diversity.
Now, the diversity argument is different
from the compensatory argument,
because it makes a certain
appeal to the social purpose
or the social mission
of the college or university.
There are really two aspects
to the diversity argument.
One says it's important to have a
diverse student body for the sake of
the educational
experience for everyone.
Hannah made that point.
And the other talks
about the wider society.
This was the argument made by
the University of Texas in the Hopwood case.
We need to train lawyers
and judges and leaders,
public officials who will
contribute to the strength,
the civic strength of the state of
Texas, and the country as a whole.
So there are two different aspects
to the diversity argument.
But both are arguments in the name
of the social purpose,
or the social mission or
the common good,
served by the institution.
Well, what about the force
of these arguments?
We've also heard objections
to these arguments.
The most powerful objection to the
compensatory argument is,
is it fair to ask Cheryl
Hopwood today,
to make the sacrifice,
to pay the compensation
for an injustice that was admittedly
committed and egregious,
in the past,
but in which she was not implicated.
Is that fair?
So that's an important objection
to the compensatory argument.
And in order to meet that objection,
we would have to investigate
whether there is such a thing
as group rights or
collective responsibility
that reaches over time.
So having identified that issue,
let's set it aside to
turn to the diversity argument.
The diversity argument doesn't
have to worry about that question.
About collective responsibility
for past wrongs.
Because it says, for reasons
Hannah and others pointed out,
that the common good is served,
is advanced if there is a racially
and ethnically diverse student body.
Everyone benefits.
This indeed was the
argument that Harvard made
when it filed a friend of the court brief
to the Supreme Court in the 1978 case,
the affirmative action case,
the Bakke case.
In the Harvard brief,
the Harvard rationale,
was cited by Justice Powell,
who was the swing vote in the case
upholding affirmative action,
he cited that as providing
the rationale that he thought
was constitutionally acceptable.
Harvard's argument
in its brief, was this:
"We care about diversity.
Scholarly excellence alone, has never been
the criterion of admission, the sole
criterion of admission to Harvard College.
Fifteen years ago diversity meant
students from California and New York,
and Massachusetts.
City dwellers, and farm boys.
Violinists, painters and football players.
Biologists, historians and classicists.
The only difference now,
Harvard argued, is that we're adding racial
and ethnic status to this long list
of diversity considerations.
When reviewing the large number of
candidates able to do well in our classes,"
Harvard wrote, "Race may count as a plus,
just as coming from Iowa may count
or being a good middle
linebacker or pianist.
A farm boy from Idaho can bring
something to Harvard College
that a Bostonian cannot offer.
Similarly, a black student can usually bring
something a white student cannot offer.
The quality of the educational
experience of all students
depends in part on these differences
in the background and outlook
that students bring with them."
That was Harvard's argument.
Now what about the diversity argument?
Is it persuasive?
If it's to be persuasive, it has to
meet one very powerful objection.
That we've heard voiced here.
By Ted,
by Bree.
Unless you're a utilitarian, you believe
that individual rights can't be violated.
And so the question is,
is there an individual right
that is violated?
Is Cheryl Hopwood's right violated?
If she is used, so to speak,
denied admission,
for the sake of the common good
and the social mission
that the University of Texas
Law School has defined for itself,
does she have a right?
Don't we deserve to be considered
according to our excellences,
our achievements,
our accomplishments,
our hard work?
Isn't that the right at stake?
Now we've already heard
an answer to that argument.
No, she doesn't
have the right.
Nobody deserves to be admitted.
Notice how this gets us back to the
issue of desert versus entitlement.
They're arguing there is no
individual right that Hopwood has.
She doesn't deserve to be admitted according
to any particular set of criteria that
she believes to be important.
Including criteria that have only to
do with her efforts and achievements.
Why not?
I think implicit,
in this argument,
is something like Rawls' rejection of moral
desert as the basis of distributive justice.
Yes, once Harvard
defines its mission
and designs its admission
policy in the light of its mission,
people are entitled,
who fit those criteria,
they are entitled to be admitted.
But according to this argument,
no one deserves that
Harvard college define its mission
and design its admission
criteria in the first place,
in a way that prizes the qualities
they happen to have in abundance.
Whether those qualities
are test scores or grades
or the ability to play the piano,
or to be a good middle linebacker,
or to come from Iowa,
or to come from a certain minority group.
So you see how this
debate about affirmative action,
especially the diversity argument,
takes us back to the
question of rights,
which in turn takes us back to
the question of whether moral desert
is or is not the basis
for distributive justice.
Think about that over the weekend and
we'll continue this discussion next time.
Suppose we're distributing flutes.
Who should get the best ones?
What's Aristotle's answer?
Anyone?
His answer is, the best flutes
should go to the best flute players,
because that's what flutes are for.
When we ended last time,
we were considering arguments for
and against affirmative action.
Counting race as a factor in admissions.
And, in the course of the discussion,
three arguments emerged,
three arguments for affirmative action.
One of them was the idea that race
and ethnic background should count
as a way of correcting for the true
meaning of test scores and grades.
Getting a more accurate
measure of the academic potential
those scores,
those numbers represent.
Second, was what we called
"the compensatory argument".
The idea of righting past wrongs,
past injustice.
And the third was the diversity argument.
And when Cheryl Hopwood
in the 1990s challenged
the University of Texas Law School's
affirmative action program,
in the federal courts,
the University of Texas
made another version of
the diversity argument.
Saying that the broader social purpose, the
social mission of the University of Texas
Law School, is to produce leaders,
in the legal community,
in the political community,
among judges, lawyers, legislators,
and therefore it's important
that we produce leaders,
who reflect the background,
and the experience,
and the ethnic and the racial
composition of the state of Texas.
It's important for serving
our wider social mission.
That was the University of
Texas Law School's argument.
And then we considered an objection
to the diversity argument which after
all is an argument in the name of
the social mission,
the common good.
We saw that Rawls does
not simply believe
that arguments of the common good
or the general welfare should prevail
if individual rights must be violated in
the course of promoting the common good.
You remember that was the question,
the challenge,
to the diversity rationale
that we were considering
when we finished last time.
And we began to discuss the question
"Well, what right might be at stake"?
Maybe the right to be considered
according to factors within one's control.
Maybe this is the argument that
Cheryl Hopwood implicitly was making.
She can't help the
fact that she is white.
Why should her chance
at getting into law school
depend on a factor she can't control?
And then Hannah who is
advancing an argument last time
said Harvard has the right
to define its mission
any way it wants to,
it's a private institution.
And it's only once
Harvard defines its mission
that we can identify
the qualities that count.
So no rights are being violated.
Now, what about
that argument?
What I would like to do is to
hear objections to that reply.
And then, see whether
others have an answer.
Yes?
And tell us your name.
Da.
- Da, right you spoke up last time.
How do you answer that argument?
Well, I think there was
two things in there.
One of them was that a private institution
could define its mission however it wants.
But that doesn't make however it defines it,
right, like I could define my personal
mission as I want to collect all
the money in the world.
But does that make it
even a good mission?
So you can't like, you can't say that just
because a college is a private institution it
can just define it as whatever it wants,
you still have to thing about, what
are the way it's defining it, it's right.
And the case of affirmative action
a lot of people have said that
since there's a lot
of other factors involved,
why not race?
Like if we already know that,
- Let's I want to stick with your first
point, Da.
- Okay.
Here's Da's objection.
Can a college or university define
its social purpose any way it wants to
and define admissions
criteria accordingly?
What about the
University of Texas Law School
not today, but in the 1950s?
Then, there was
another Supreme Court case,
against the admissions policy of the
University of Texas Law School
because it was segregated.
It only admitted whites.
And when the case went to
court back in the '50s,
the University of Texas Law School
also invoked its mission.
"Our mission as a law school,
is to educate lawyers
for the Texas bar, the Texas law firms.
And no Texas law firm hires
African Americans.
So to fulfill our mission,
we only admit whites."
Or consider Harvard,
in the 1930s
when it had anti-Jewish quotas.
President Lowell, the president
of Harvard in the 1930s said,
that he had nothing
personally against Jews,
but he invoked the mission,
the social purpose of Harvard he said,
"which is not only
to train intellectuals,
part of the mission at Harvard," he said,
"is to train stockbrokers for Wall Street,
presidents and senators and there are
very few Jews who go into those professions."
Now, here's the challenge.
Is there a principle distinction
between the invocation of
the social purpose
of the college or university today,
in the diversity rationale
and the invocation of the
social purpose or mission
of the university by
Texas in the 1950s
or Harvard in the 1930s?
Is there a difference in principle?
What's the reply?
Hannah?
- Well, I think that the principle that's
different here, is, basically the distinction
between inclusion versus exclusion.
I think that it's morally
wrong of the university to
say "We're going to exclude you on
the basis of your religion or your race."
That's denial on the
basis of arbitrary factors.
What Harvard is trying to do
today with its diversity initiatives,
is to include groups that
were excluded in the past.
Good, let's see if, stay there, let's see
if someone would like to reply.
Go ahead. - Actually this is
kind of in support of Hannah,
rather than a reply but,
- That's alright.
I was going to say
another principle difference
can be based on malice being
the motivation for the historical
segregation act, so it's saying that we're
not going to let blacks or Jews in because
they're worse as
people or as a group.
Good, so the element of
malice isn't present.
And what's your name?
- Stevie.
Stevie says that in the historic segregation
as racist, anti-Semitic quotas
or prohibitions.
There was built into them,
a certain kind of malice,
a certain kind of judgment
that African Americans or Jews were
somehow less worthy than everybody else.
Whereas present day
affirmative action programs
don't involve or imply
any such judgment.
What it amounts to saying is,
so long as the policy,
just uses people in a way as
valuable to the social purpose
of the institution, it's okay
provided it doesn't judge them,
maliciously, as Stevie might add,
as intrinsically less worthy.
I'd like to raise a question.
Doesn't that
concede that all of us
when we compete for positions or
for seats in colleges and universities
in a way are being used, not judged,
but used, in a way that has
nothing to do with moral desert.
Remember we got into this
whole discussion of affirmative action
when we were
trying to figure out
whether distributive justice should
be tied to moral desert or not.
And we were launched
on that question
by Rawls and his denial,
his rejection of the idea
that distributive justice
whether its positions or places
in the class or income and wealth
is a matter of moral desert.
Suppose that were the moral basis
of Harvard's admissions policy,
what letters would they have to write
to people they rejected or
accepted for that matter?
Wouldn't they have
to write something like this:
"Dear unsuccessful applicant,
we regret to inform you
that your application for admission
has been rejected.
It's not your fault that
when you came along
society happened not to need
the qualities you had to offer.
Those admitted instead of
you are not themselves
deserving of a place nor worthy of a praise
for the factors that led their admission.
We are in any case only using them and you
as instruments of a wider social purpose.
Better luck next time."
What was the letter
you actually got
when you were admitted?
Perhaps it should have read
something like this:
"Dear successful applicant,
we are pleased to inform you that your
application for admission has been accepted.
It turns out,
lucky for you,
that you have the traits that
society needs at the moment,
so we propose to
exploit your assets
for society's advantage.
You are to be congratulated.
Not in the sense that you deserve
credit for having the qualities
that led to your admission,
but only in a sense that
the winner of a lottery
is to be congratulated.
And if you choose
to accept our offer,
you will ultimately be entitled
to the benefits that attach
to being used in this way.
We look forward to
seeing you in the fall."
Now, there is something a little odd,
morally odd,
if it's true that those
letters do reflect
the theory,
the philosophy
underlying the policy.
So here's the question they pose.
And it's a question that takes us back
to a big issue in political philosophy.
Is it possible,
and is it desirable,
to detach questions
of distributive justice
from questions of moral desert
and questions of virtue?
In many ways,
this is an issue that separates
modern political philosophy from
ancient political thought.
What's at stake in the question of whether
we can put desert, moral desert aside?
It seemed when we
were reading Rawls,
that the incentive,
the reason he had,
for detaching distributive
justice from moral desert
was an egalitarian one.
That if we set desert to one side,
there's greater scope for the
exercise of egalitarian considerations.
The veil of ignorance.
The two principles,
the difference principle,
helping the least well off,
redistribution and all that.
But what's interesting,
is if you look,
at a range of thinkers
we've been considering,
there does seem to be a reason they
want to detach justice from desert
that goes well beyond
any concern for equality.
Libertarian rights oriented theorists,
the kind we've been studying, as well
as egalitarian rights oriented theorists,
including Rawls, and for that
matter, also including Kant,
all agree, despite their disagreements
over distributive justice,
and the welfare state
and all of that,
they all agree that justice is not
a matter of rewarding or honoring
virtue or moral desert.
Now why do they all think that?
It can't just be
for egalitarian reasons
not all of them are egalitarians.
This gets us to the big philosophical
question we have to try to sort out.
Somehow they think tying
justice to moral merit or virtue
is going to lead away from freedom,
from respect for
persons as free beings.
Well, in order to see what they
consider to be at stake,
and in order to assess
their shared assumption,
we need to turn to a thinker,
to a philosopher,
who disagrees with them.
Who explicitly ties justice
to honor, honoring virtue,
and merit and moral desert.
And that thinker
is Aristotle.
Now, in many ways
Aristotle's idea of justice
is intuitively very powerful.
In some ways it's strange.
I want to bring out both its power,
its plausibility and its strangeness,
so that we can see what's at
stake in this whole debate about
justice and whether it's
tied to desert and virtue.
So, what is Aristotle's answer
to the question about justice?
For Aristotle, justice is a matter of
giving people what they deserve,
giving people their due.
It's a matter of figuring out
the proper fit
between persons,
with their virtues,
and their appropriate social roles.
Well, what does this picture
of justice look like,
and how does it differ from the
conception that seems to be shared among
libertarian and egalitarian
rights oriented theorists alike?
Justice means giving each person
his or her due, giving
people what they deserve.
But what is a person's due?
What are the relevant
grounds of merit or desert?
Aristotle says that depends on
the sort of things being distributed.
"Justice involves two factors:
Things and the persons
to whom the things are assigned.
In general we say," Aristotle writes,
"That persons who are equal
should have equal things
assigned to them."
But here there arises a hard question.
Equals in what respects?
Aristotle says that depends on the
sort of thing we're distributing.
Suppose we're distributing flutes.
What is the relevant merit or
basis of desert for flutes?
Who should get the best ones?
What's Aristotle's answer?
Anyone?
The best flute players, right.
Those who are best in
the relevant sense,
the best flute players.
Is it just to discriminate
in allocating flutes? Yes.
All justice involves discrimination,
Aristotle says.
What matters is that the
discrimination be according to the relevant
excellence,
according to the virtue
appropriate to having flutes.
He says it would be unjust to
discriminate on some other basis.
In giving out the flutes,
to, say, wealth.
Just giving the best flutes to the
people who can pay the highest price,
or nobility of birth,
just giving flutes to aristocrats,
or physical beauty, giving the
best flutes to the most handsome,
or chance, having a lottery.
Aristotle says birth and
beauty may be greater
goods than the ability to play the flute,
and those who possess them may surpass
the flute player more in these qualities
than he surpasses them
in his flute playing.
But the fact remains that he is the person
who ought to get the best flute.
It's a strange idea this comparison,
by the way,
that could you say,
"Am I more handsome
than she is a good lacrosse player?"
That's a strange kind of comparison.
But putting that aside,
Aristotle says, we're not looking for
the best overall whatever that might mean.
We're looking for the best musician.
Now, why this is important to see.
Why, should the best flutes
go to the best flute players?
Well, why do you think?
Anybody?
What?
They'll produce the best music.
Well, and everybody will enjoy it more.
That's not Aristotle's answer.
Aristotle is not a utilitarian.
He's not just saying, that way there'll be
better music and everyone will enjoy it,
everyone will be better off.
His answer is the best flutes
should go to the best flute players
because that's what flutes are for.
To be played well.
The purpose of flute playing,
the purpose,
is to produce excellent music.
And those who can
best perfect that purpose,
ought properly to have the best ones.
Now, it may also be true,
as a welcome side effect.
That everyone will enjoy
listening to that music.
So that answer is true enough
as far as it goes,
but it's important to
see that Aristotle's
reason is not a utilitarian reason.
It's a reason that looks,
here's where you might think
it's a little bit strange,
it looks to the purpose, the point,
the goal, of flute playing.
Another way of describing this,
looking to the goal to determine
the just allocation,
the Greek for goal or end,
was 'telos'.
So Aristotle says, you have to
consider the point, the end, the goal,
the telos of the thing in
this case of flute playing.
And that's how you
define a just allocation.
A just discrimination.
So this idea of
reasoning from the goal,
from the telos, is called
"teleological reasoning".
Teleological moral reasoning.
And that's Aristotle's way.
Reasoning from the goal,
from the end.
Now, this may seem,
as I said a strange idea,
that we're supposed to
reason from the purpose,
but it is, does have a certain
intuitive plausibility.
Consider the allocation, let's say, at
Harvard, of the best tennis courts
or squash courts.
How should they be allocated?
Who should have priority in playing
on the best courts?
Well, you might say,
"Those who can best afford them."
Set up a fee system,
charge money for them.
Aristotle would say "No".
You might say,
"Well, Harvard big shots, the most
influential people at Harvard,
who would they be"?
The senior faculty should have priority
in playing on the best tennis courts.
No, Aristotle would reject that.
Some scientist may be a greater scientist
than some Varsity tennis player
is a tennis player, but still
the tennis player is the one
who should have priority
for playing in the best tennis court.
There is a certain
intuitive plausibility to this idea.
Now, one of the things
that makes it strange
is that in Aristotle's world,
in the ancient world,
it wasn't only social practices
that were governed,
in Aristotle's view,
by teleological reasoning
and teleological explanation.
All of nature
was understood to be a meaningful order
and what it meant to understand nature,
to grasp nature,
to find our place in nature,
was to inquire into and read out
the purposes or the telos,
of nature.
And with the advent of modern science, it's
been difficult to think of the world that way
and so it makes it harder perhaps to think
of justice in a teleological way,
but there is a certain naturalness
to thinking about even the natural world,
as teleologically ordered
as a purpose of whole.
In fact, children have to be
educated out of this way
of looking at the world.
I realized this when my
kids were very young
and I was reading them a book,
Winnie the Poo.
And Winnie the Poo gives
you a great idea of how
there is a certain, natural, childlike
way of looking at the world
in a teleological way.
You may remember a story
of Winnie-the-Poo walking
in the forest one day,
"He came to a place in the forest,
and from the top of the tree
there came a loud buzzing-noise.
Winnie-the-Poo sat at the foot of a tree,
put his head between his paws,
and began to think."
Here's what he said to himself,
" 'That buzzing-noise means something.
You don't get a buzzing-noise like
that just buzzing and buzzing
without its meaning something.
If there's a buzzing-noise,
somebody's making a buzzing-noise.
And the only reason for making
a buzzing-noise that I know of,
is because you're a bee.'
Then he thought for
another long time and said,
'And the only reason for
being a bee that I know of,
is making honey.'
And then he got up,
and he said, 'And the only
reason for making honey,
is so I can eat it.'
So he began to climb the tree."
This is an example
of teleological reasoning.
It isn't so implausible after all.
Now, we grew up,
and we're talked out of this way
of thinking about the world.
But here's the question,
even if teleological explanations don't
fit with modern science,
even if we've outgrown them
in understanding nature,
isn't there
something still intuitively,
and morally plausible,
even powerful,
about Aristotle's idea that
the only way to think about justice
is to reason from the purpose,
the goal, the telos,
of the social practice?
And isn't that precisely what we were
doing when we were disagreeing about
affirmative action?
You can almost recast
that disagreement
as one about what the proper
appropriate purpose, or end
of a university
education consists in.
Reasoning from the purpose
or from the telos.
Or from the end.
Aristotle says that's indispensable
to thinking about justice.
Is he right?
Think about that question
as you turn to Aristotle's politics.
Don't miss the chance to interact online
with other viewers of Justice.
Join in the conversation,
take a pop quiz.
Watch lectures you've missed,
and learn a lot more.
Visit justiceharvard.org,
it's the right thing to do.