Captions proofread by @xiaolai, www.lixiaolai.com
Funding for this program
is provided by:
Additional funding provided by:
Last time,
we argued about
the case of
The Queen v. Dudley & Stephens,
the lifeboat case,
the case of cannibalism at sea.
And with the arguments
about the lifeboat in mind,
the arguments for and against
what Dudley and Stephens did in mind,
let's turn back to the philosophy,
the utilitarian philosophy of Jeremy Bentham.
Bentham was born in England in 1748.
At the age of 12, he went to Oxford.
At 15, he went to law school.
He was admitted to the Bar at age 19
but he never practiced law.
Instead, he devoted his life to
jurisprudence and moral philosophy.
Last time, we began to consider
Bentham's version of utilitarianism.
The main idea is simply stated
and it's this:
The highest principle of morality,
whether personal or political morality,
is to maximize the general welfare,
or the collective happiness,
or the overall balance
of pleasure over pain;
in a phrase, maximize utility.
Bentham arrives at this principle
by the following line of reasoning:
We're all governed
by pain and pleasure,
they are our sovereign masters,
and so any moral system
has to take account of them.
How best to take account?
By maximizing.
And this leads to the principle of the
greatest good for the greatest number.
What exactly should we maximize?
Bentham tells us happiness,
or more precisely, utility -
maximizing utility as a principle
not only for individuals
but also for communities
and for legislators.
"What, after all, is a community?"
Bentham asks.
It's the sum of the individuals
who comprise it.
And that's why in deciding
the best policy,
in deciding what the law should be,
in deciding what's just,
citizens and legislators
should ask themselves the question
if we add up all of the benefits
of this policy
and subtract all of the costs,
the right thing to do
is the one that maximizes the balance
of happiness over suffering.
That's what it means
to maximize utility.
Now, today, I want to see
whether you agree or disagree with it,
and it often goes,
this utilitarian logic,
under the name of
cost-benefit analysis,
which is used by companies
and by governments all the time.
And what it involves
is placing a value,
usually a dollar value,
to stand for utility on the costs
and the benefits
of various proposals.
Recently, in the Czech Republic,
there was a proposal
to increase the excise tax on smoking.
Philip Morris, the tobacco company,
does huge business
in the Czech Republic.
They commissioned a study,
a cost-benefit analysis
of smoking in the Czech Republic,
and what their cost-benefit
analysis found was the government
gains by having Czech citizens smoke.
Now, how do they gain?
It's true that there are
negative effects to the public finance
of the Czech government
because there are increased health care
costs for people who develop
smoking-related diseases.
On the other hand,
there were positive effects
and those were added up
on the other side of the ledger.
The positive effects included,
for the most part,
various tax revenues that the
government derives from the sale
of cigarette products,
but it also included
health care savings to the
government when people die early,
pension savings -- you don't have to
pay pensions for as long -
and also, savings in
housing costs for the elderly.
And when all of the costs
and benefits were added up,
the Philip Morris study found
that there is a net public finance gain
in the Czech Republic
of $147,000,000,
and given the savings in housing,
in health care, and pension costs,
the government enjoys savings
of over $1,200 for each person
who dies prematurely due to smoking.
Cost-benefit analysis.
Now, those among you
who are defenders of utilitarianism
may think that this is an unfair test.
Philip Morris was pilloried
in the press
and they issued an apology
for this heartless calculation.
You may say that what's missing here
is something that the utilitarian
can easily incorporate,
namely the value to the person
and to the families of those who die
from lung cancer.
What about the value of life?
Some cost-benefit analyses incorporate
a measure for the value of life.
One of the most famous
of these involved the Ford Pinto case.
Did any of you read about that?
This was back in the 1970s.
Do you remember
what the Ford Pinto was,
a kind of car?
Anybody?
It was a small car,
subcompact car, very popular,
but it had one problem,
which is the fuel tank
was at the back of the car
and in rear collisions,
the fuel tank exploded
and some people were killed
and some severely injured.
Victims of these injuries
took Ford to court to sue.
And in the court case,
it turned out that Ford
had long since known about the
vulnerable fuel tank
and had done a cost-benefit analysis
to determine whether it would be
worth it to put in
a special shield that would
protect the fuel tank
and prevent it from exploding.
They did a cost-benefit analysis.
The cost per part
to increase the safety of the Pinto,
they calculated at $11.00 per part.
And here's -- this was the cost-benefit
analysis that emerged in the trial.
Eleven dollars per part
at 12.5 million cars and trucks
came to a total cost of
$137 million to improve the safety.
But then they calculated the benefits
of spending all this money
on a safer car
and they counted 180 deaths
and they assigned a dollar value,
$200,000 per death,
180 injuries, $67,000,
and then the costs to repair,
the replacement cost
for 2,000 vehicles,
it would be destroyed without
the safety device $700 per vehicle.
So the benefits turned out to be
only $49.5 million
and so they didn't
install the device.
Needless to say,
when this memo of the
Ford Motor Company's cost-benefit
analysis came out in the trial,
it appalled the jurors,
who awarded a huge settlement.
Is this a counterexample to the
utilitarian idea of calculating?
Because Ford included a measure
of the value of life.
Now, who here wants to defend
cost-benefit analysis
from this apparent counterexample?
Who has a defense?
Or do you think this
completely destroys the whole
utilitarian calculus?
Yes?
Well, I think that once again,
they've made the same mistake
the previous case did,
that they assigned a dollar value
to human life,
and once again,
they failed to take account
things like suffering
and emotional losses by the families.
I mean, families lost earnings
but they also lost a loved one
and that is more valued
than $200,000.
Right and -- wait, wait, wait,
that's good. What's your name?
Julie Roteau .
So if $200,000, Julie,
is too low a figure
because it doesn't include the
loss of a loved one
and the loss of those years of life,
what would be -
what do you think
would be a more accurate number?
I don't believe I could give a number.
I think that this sort of analysis
shouldn't be applied to issues
of human life.
I think it can't be used monetarily.
So they didn't just put
too low a number, Julie says.
They were wrong to try
to put any number at all.
All right, let's hear someone who -
You have to adjust for inflation.
All right, fair enough.
So what would the number be now?
This was 35 years ago.
Two million dollars.
Two million dollars?
You would put two million?
And what's your name?
Voytek
Voytek says we have to
allow for inflation.
We should be more generous.
Then would you be satisfied
that this is the right way of
thinking about the question?
I guess, unfortunately, it is for -
there needs to be a number
put somewhere, like, I'm not sure
what that number would be,
but I do agree that
there could possibly
be a number put on the human life.
All right, so Voytek says,
and here, he disagrees with Julie.
Julie says we can't put a number
on human life
for the purpose of a
cost-benefit analysis.
Voytek says we have to because
we have to make decisions somehow.
What do other people
think about this?
Is there anyone prepared
to defend cost-benefit analysis
here as accurate as desirable?
Yes? Go ahead.
I think that if Ford
and other car companies
didn't use cost-benefit analysis,
they'd eventually go out of business
because they wouldn't be able to be
profitable and millions of people
wouldn't be able to use their cars
to get to jobs,
to put food on the table,
to feed their children.
So I think that if cost-benefit
analysis isn't employed,
the greater good is sacrificed,
in this case.
All right, let me add.
What's your name?
Raul.
Raul, there was recently a study done
about cell phone use by a driver
when people are driving a car,
and there was a debate
whether that should be banned.
Yeah.
And the figure was that
some 2,000 people die as a result
of accidents each year
using cell phones.
And yet, the cost-benefit analysis
which was done by the
Center for Risk Analysis
at Harvard found that
if you look at the benefits
of the cell phone use
and you put some value on the life,
it comes out about the same
because of the enormous
economic benefit of enabling people
to take advantage of their time,
not waste time, be able to make deals
and talk to friends and so on
while they're driving.
Doesn't that suggest that
it's a mistake to try to put
monetary figures on
questions of human life?
Well, I think that if the
great majority of people try to
derive maximum utility
out of a service,
like using cell phones and the
convenience that cell phones provide,
that sacrifice is necessary
for satisfaction to occur.
You're an outright utilitarian.
Yes. Okay.
All right then, one last question, Raul.
- Okay.
And I put this to Voytek,
what dollar figure should
be put on human life to decide
whether to ban the use of cell phones?
Well, I don't want to
arbitrarily calculate a figure,
I mean, right now.
I think that -
You want to take it under advisement?
Yeah, I'll take it under advisement.
But what, roughly speaking, would it be?
You got 2,300 deaths. - Okay.
You got to assign a dollar value
to know whether you want
to prevent those deaths by banning
the use of cell phones in cars. - Okay.
So what would your hunch be?
How much? A million?
Two million?
Two million was Voytek's figure. - Yeah.
Is that about right?
- Maybe a million.
A million?
- Yeah.
You know, that's good.
Thank you. -Okay.
So, these are some of the controversies
that arise these days
from cost-benefit analysis,
especially those that involve placing a
dollar value on everything
to be added up.
Well, now I want to turn
to your objections,
to your objections not necessarily to
cost-benefit analysis specifically,
because that's just one version of the
utilitarian logic in practice today,
but to the theory as a whole,
to the idea that the right thing to do,
the just basis for policy and law
is to maximize utility.
How many disagree with the
utilitarian approach to law
and to the common good?
How many agree with it?
So more agree than disagree.
So let's hear from the critics.
Yes?
My main issue with it is
that I feel like you can't say
that just because someone's
in the minority, what they want
and need is less valuable than
someone who is in the majority.
So I guess I have an issue with
the idea that the greatest good
for the greatest number is okay
because there are still -
what about people who
are in the lesser number?
Like, it's not fair to them.
They didn't have any say
in where they wanted to be.
All right.
That's an interesting objection.
You're worried about
the effect on the minority.
Yes.
What's your name, by the way?
Anna.
Who has an answer to Anna's worry
about the effect on the minority?
What do you say to Anna?
Um, she said that
the minority is valued less.
I don't think that's the case
because individually,
the minority's value is just the same
as the individual of the majority.
It's just that the numbers
outweigh the minority.
And I mean, at a certain point,
you have to make a decision
and I'm sorry for the minority
but sometimes,
it's for the general,
for the greater good.
For the greater good.
Anna, what do you say?
What's your name?
Yang-Da.
What do you say to Yang-Da?
Yang-Da says you just have to
add up people's preferences
and those in the minority do have
their preferences weighed.
Can you give an example
of the kind of thing
you're worried about when you say
you're worried about utilitarianism
violating the concern
or respect due the minority?
And give an example.
Okay. So, well, with any of the cases
that we've talked about,
like for the shipwreck one,
I think the boy who was eaten
still had as much of a right to live
as the other people
and just because he was
the minority in that case,
the one who maybe had less of a
chance to keep living,
that doesn't mean
that the others automatically
have a right to eat him
just because it would give a
greater amount
of people a chance to live.
So there may be certain rights
that the minority members have,
that the individual has that shouldn't
be traded off for the sake of utility?
Yes.
Yes, Anna? You know,
this would be a test for you.
Back in Ancient Rome,
they threw Christians to the lions
in the Colosseum for sport.
If you think how the
utilitarian calculus would go,
yes, the Christian thrown to the lions
suffers enormous excruciating pain.
But look at the collective ecstasy
of the Romans!
Yang-Da.
Well, in that time,
I don't -- if -- in modern day of time,
to value the -- to give a number
to the happiness
given to the people watching,
I don't think any, like,
policymaker would say the pain
of one person, of the suffering
of one person is much, much -- is,
I mean, in comparison
to the happiness gained, it's -
No, but you have to admit that
if there were enough Romans
delirious enough with happiness,
it would outweigh even the
most excruciating pain of a handful
of Christians thrown to the lion.
So we really have here two
different objections to utilitarianism.
One has to do with whether
utilitarianism adequately respects
individual rights or minority rights,
and the other has to do with
the whole idea of aggregating utility
or preferences or values.
Is it possible to aggregate all values
to translate them into dollar terms?
There was, in the 1930s,
a psychologist who tried
to address this second question.
He tried to prove
what utilitarianism assumes,
that it is possible
to translate all goods, all values,
all human concerns
into a single uniform measure,
and he did this by conducting a survey
of young recipients of relief,
this was in the 1930s,
and he asked them,
he gave them a list of unpleasant
experiences and he asked them,
"How much would you have to be paid
to undergo the following experiences?"
and he kept track.
For example,
how much would you have to be paid
to have one upper front
tooth pulled out?
Or how much would you have to be
paid to have one little toe cut off?
Or to eat a live earthworm
six inches long?
Or to live the rest of your life
on a farm in Kansas?
Or to choke a stray cat to death
with your bare hands?
Now, what do you suppose was the most
expensive item on that list? - Kansas!
Kansas?
You're right, it was Kansas.
For Kansas, people said
they'd have to pay them -
they have to be paid $300,000.
What do you think was the
next most expensive?
Not the cat.
Not the tooth.
Not the toe.
The worm!
People said you'd have to pay them
$100,000 to eat the worm.
What do you think was
the least expensive item?
Not the cat.
The tooth.
During the Depression,
people were willing to have their
tooth pulled for only $4,500.
What?
Now, here's what Thorndike
concluded from his study.
Any want or a satisfaction which exists
exists in some amount
and is therefore measurable.
The life of a dog or a cat
or a chicken consists of appetites,
cravings, desires,
and their gratifications.
So does the life of human beings,
though the appetites
and desires are more complicated.
But what about Thorndike's study?
Does it support
Bentham's idea that all goods,
all values can be captured according
to a single uniform measure of value?
Or does the preposterous character
of those different items on the list
suggest the opposite conclusion
that maybe,
whether we're talking about
life or Kansas or the worm,
maybe the things we value
and cherish can't be captured
according to a single uniform
measure of value?
And if they can't,
what are the consequences
for the utilitarian theory
of morality?
That's a question we'll
continue with next time.
All right, now, let's take the
other part of the poll,
which is the highest
experience or pleasure.
How many say Shakespeare?
How many say Fear Factor?
No, you can't be serious.
Really?
Last time, we began to consider
some objections to
Jeremy Bentham's
version of utilitarianism.
People raised two objections
in the discussion we had.
The first was the objection,
the claim that utilitarianism,
by concerning itself with the greatest
good for the greatest number,
fails adequately to
respect individual rights.
Today, we have debates
about torture and terrorism.
Suppose a suspected terrorist was
apprehended on September 10th
and you had reason to believe that
the suspect had crucial information
about an impending terrorist attack
that would kill over 3,000 people
and you couldn't extract
the information.
Would it be just to torture the suspect
to get the information
or do you say no,
there is a categorical moral duty
of respect for individual rights?
In a way, we're back to the
questions we started with
about Charlie Carson
organ transplant.
So that's the first issue.
And you remember,
we considered some examples
of cost-benefit analysis,
but a lot of people were unhappy
with cost-benefit analysis
when it came to placing
a dollar value on human life.
And so that led us
to the second objection.
It questioned whether it's possible
to translate all values into
a single uniform measure of value.
It asks, in other words,
whether all values are commensurable.
Let me give you one other
example of an experience.
This actually is a true story.
It comes from personal experience
that raises a question
at least about whether all values
can be translated without loss
into utilitarian terms.
Some years ago,
when I was a graduate student,
I was at Oxford in England and
they had men's and women's colleges.
They weren't yet mixed
and the women's colleges
had rules against overnight
male guests.
By the 1970s, these rules were
rarely enforced and easily violated,
or so I was told.
By the late 1970s,
when I was there,
pressure grew to relax these rules
and it became the subject of debate
among the faculty
at St. Anne's College,
which was one of these
all-women's colleges.
The older women on the faculty
were traditionalists.
They were opposed to change
unconventional moral grounds.
But times have changed
and they were embarrassed
to give the true grounds for their
objection and so they translated
their arguments into
utilitarian terms.
"If men stay overnight",
they argued,
"the costs to the college
will increase."
"How?" you might wonder.
"Well, they'll want
to take baths
and that'll use up hot water,"
they said.
Furthermore, they argued,
"We'll have to replace
the mattresses more often."
The reformers met these arguments
by adopting the following compromise.
Each woman could have a maximum of
three overnight male guests each week.
They didn't say whether it had to be
the same one or three different
provided, and this was
the compromise,
provided the guest paid 50 pence
to defray the cost to the college.
The next day, the national headline
in the national newspaper read,
"St. Anne's Girls, 50 Pence A Night."
Another illustration of the
difficulty of translating all values,
in this case, a certain idea of virtue,
into utilitarian terms.
So, that's all to illustrate the
second objection to utilitarianism,
at least the part of that objection,
that questions whether utilitarianism
is right to assume that we can assume
the uniformity of value,
the commensurability of all values
and translate all moral considerations
into dollars or money.
But there is a second aspect
to this worry about
aggregating values and preferences.
Why should we weigh all preferences
that people have without assessing
whether they're good preferences
or bad preferences?
Shouldn't we distinguish between
higher pleasures and lower pleasures?
Now, part of the appeal of not
making any qualitative distinctions
about the worth
of people's preferences,
part of the appeal is that it is
nonjudgmental and egalitarian.
The Benthamite utilitarian says
everybody's preferences count
and they count regardless
of what people want,
regardless of what makes
different people happy.
For Bentham, all that matters,
you'll remember,
are the intensity
and the duration of a pleasure or pain.
The so-called
"higher pleasures or nobler virtues"
are simply those,
according to Bentham,
that produce stronger,
longer pleasure.
Yet a famous phrase
to express this idea,
the quantity of pleasure being equal,
pushpin is as good as poetry.
What was pushpin?
It was some kind of a child's game,
like tiddlywinks.
"Pushpin is as good as poetry",
Bentham says.
And lying behind this idea, I think,
is the claim, the intuition,
that it's a presumption to judge
whose pleasures
are intrinsically higher
or worthier or better.
And there is something attractive
in this refusal to judge.
After all, some people like Mozart,
others Madonna.
Some people like ballet,
others bowling.
Who's to say,
a Benthamite might argue,
who is to say which of these pleasures,
whose pleasures are higher,
worthier, nobler than others?
But is that right, this refusal
to make qualitative distinctions?
Can we altogether dispense
with the idea that
certain things we take pleasure in
are better or worthier than others?
Think back to the case of the
Romans in the Colosseum.
One thing that troubled people about
that practice is that it seemed
to violate the rights
of the Christian.
Another way of objection
to what's going on there
is that the pleasure that the Romans
take in this bloody spectacle,
should that pleasure, which is abased,
kind of corrupt, degrading pleasure,
should that even be valorized
or weighed in deciding
what the general welfare is?
So here are the objections
to Bentham's utilitarianism
and now, we turn to someone who
tried to respond to those objections,
a latter-day utilitarian,
John Stuart Mill.
So what we need to examine now
is whether John Stuart Mill
had a convincing reply
to these objections to utilitarianism.
John Stuart Mill was born in 1806.
His father, James Mill,
was a disciple of Bentham's,
and James Mill set about
giving his son, John Stuart Mill,
a model education.
He was a child prot¨¦g¨¦,
John Stuart Mill.
He knew Greek at the age of three,
Latin at eight,
and age 10, he wrote
"A History of Roman Law."
At age 20, he had a nervous breakdown.
This left him in a depression
for five years, but at age 25,
what helped lift him out
of this depression
is that he met Harriet Taylor.
She and Mill got married,
they lived happily ever after,
and it was under her influence
that John Stuart Mill
tried to humanize utilitarianism.
What Mill tried to do
was to see whether the
utilitarian calculus could be
enlarged and modified to
accommodate humanitarian concerns,
like the concern to
respect individual rights,
and also to address the distinction
between higher
and lower pleasures.
In 1859, Mill wrote
a famous book on liberty,
the main point of which
was the importance
of defending individual rights
and minority rights,
and in 1861,
toward the end of his life,
he wrote the book we read as part
of this course, "Utilitarianism."
He makes it clear that utility
is the only standard of morality,
in his view, so he's not challenging
Bentham's premise.
He's affirming it.
He says very explicitly,
"The sole evidence it is possible
to produce that anything is desirable
is that people actually do desire it."
So he stays with the idea that
our de facto actual empirical desires
are the only basis for moral judgment.
But then, page eight,
also in chapter two,
he argues that it is possible
for a utilitarian to distinguish
higher from lower pleasures.
Now, for those of you
who have read Mill already,
how, according to him, is it
possible to draw that distinction?
How can a utilitarian distinguish
qualitatively higher pleasures
from lesser ones, base ones,
unworthy ones? Yes?
If you've tried both of them
and you prefer the higher one,
naturally, always.
That's great.
That's right.
What's your name?
- John.
So as John points out,
Mill says here's the test.
Since we can't step
outside actual desires,
actual preferences that would
violate utilitarian premises,
the only test of whether a pleasure
is higher or lower
is whether someone who has
experienced both would prefer it.
And here, in chapter two,
we see the passage where
Mill makes the point that
John just described.
"Of two pleasures,
if there be one to which
all or almost all who have experience
of both give a decided preference,
irrespective of any feeling
of moral obligation to prefer it --
in other words, no outside,
no independent standard -- then,
that is the more desirable pleasure."
What do people think
about that argument?
Does it succeed?
How many think that it
does succeed of arguing
within utilitarian terms
for a distinction between
higher and lower pleasures?
How many think it doesn't succeed?
I want to hear your reasons.
But before we give the reasons
let's do an experiment of Mill's claim.
In order to do this experiment,
we're going to look at
three short excerpts
of popular entertainment.
The first one is a Hamlet soliloquy.
It'll be followed by
two other experiences.
See what you think.
What a piece of work is a man,
how noble in reason,
how infinite in faculties,
in form and moving
how express and admirable,
in action how like an angel,
in apprehension how like a god!
The beauty of the world,
the paragon of animals -
and yet, to me,
what is this quintessence of dust?
Man delights not me.
Imagine a world where your greatest
fears become reality.
Ahh! They're biting me!
Each show, six contestants
from around the country
battle each other in
three extreme stunts.
Ow!
These stunts are designed
to challenge the contestants
both physically and mentally.
Six contestants,
three stunts, one winner.
Yes! Whooo!
Fear Factor.
Hi-diddily-ho,
pedal-to-the-metal-o-philes.
Flanders, since when
do you like anything cool?
Well, I don't care
for the speed but I can't get enough
of that safety gear.
Helmets, roll bars, caution flags...
I like the fresh air...
and looking at the poor people
in the infield.
Dang, Cletus, why'd you have to
park by my parents?
Now, Honey,
they's my parents too.
I don't even have to ask
which one you liked most.
The Simpsons,
how many liked The Simpsons most?
How many Shakespeare?
What about Fear Factor?
How many preferred Fear Factor?
Really?
People overwhelmingly like The Simpsons
better than Shakespeare.
All right, now,
let's take the other part of the poll,
which is the highest experience
or pleasure.
How many say Shakespeare?
How many say Fear Factor?
No, you can't be serious.
Really? What?
All right, go ahead.
You can say it.
I found that one the most entertaining.
I know, but which do you think
was the worthiest,
the noblest experience?
I know you found it
the most entertaining.
If something is good
just because it is pleasurable,
what does it matter
whether you have sort of an
abstract idea of whether it is
good by someone else's sense or not?
All right, so you come down
in the straight Benthamite side.
Who is to judge
and why should we judge,
apart from just registering
and aggregating de facto preference?
All right, that's fair enough.
And what's your name?
Nate, okay, fair enough.
All right, so how many think
The Simpsons is actually,
apart from liking it,
is actually the higher experience?
Higher than Shakespeare?
All right, let's see the vote
for Shakespeare again.
How many think Shakespeare is higher?
All right.
So why is it -- ideally,
I'd like to hear from someone,
is there someone who thinks
Shakespeare is highest but who
preferred watching The Simpsons?
Yes?
Like, I guess just sitting
and watching The Simpsons,
it's entertaining because they make
jokes and they make us laugh.
But like, someone has to tell us that
Shakespeare was this great writer.
We had to be taught how to read him,
how to understand him.
We had to be taught how to kind of
take in Rembrandt,
how to analyze a painting.
But let me -- what's your name?
Anisha.
Anisha, when you say someone
told you that Shakespeare is better --
Right.
Are you accepting it on blind faith?
You voted that Shakespeare is higher
only because the culture
tells you that
or teachers tell you that or do you
actually agree with that yourself?
Well, in the sense that Shakespeare no,
but earlier you made
an example of Rembrandt.
I feel like I would enjoy
reading a comic book
more than I would enjoy
kind of analyzing Rembrandt
because someone told me
it was great, you know. - Right.
So some of this seems to be,
you're suggesting,
a kind of a cultural convention
and pressure.
We're told what books,
what works of art are great. - Right.
Who else?
Yes?
Although I enjoyed watching
The Simpsons more
in this particular moment,
in justice, if I were to spend
the rest of my life considering
the three different video clips shown,
I would not want to spend
that remainder of my life
considering the latter two clips.
I think I would derive more pleasure
from being able to branch out in my
own mind sort of considering more
deep pleasures, more deep thoughts.
And tell me your name.
Joe.
Joe, so if you had to spend
the rest of your life on a farm
in Kansas with only Shakespeare
or the collected episodes
of The Simpsons,
you would prefer Shakespeare?
What do you conclude from that about
John Stuart Mill's test that the test
of a higher pleasure is whether people
who have experienced both prefer it?
Can I cite another example briefly?
Yeah.
In Neurobiology last year,
we were told of a rat
who was tested a particular center
in the brain where the rat was able
to stimulate his brain and caused
itself intense pleasure repeatedly.
The rat did not eat
or drink until it died.
So the rat was clearly
experiencing intense pleasure.
Now, if you ask me right now
if I would rather experience
intense pleasure or have a
full lifetime of higher pleasure,
I would consider
intense pleasure to be low pleasure.
I would right now enjoy
intense pleasure but
-- yes, I would.
I certainly would.
But over a lifetime,
I think I would think almost
a complete majority here
would agree that they would rather
a complete majority here would agree
that they would rather
be a human with higher pleasure
than be that rat with intense pleasure
for a momentary period of time.
Now, in answer to your question,
I think this proves that -
or I won't say "proves."
I think the conclusion is that
Mill's theory that when a majority
of people are asked
what they would rather do,
they will answer that they would
rather engage in a higher pleasure.
So you think that this support Mill's
you think Mill is onto something here?
I do.
All right, Is there anyone who
disagrees with Joe and who thinks
that our experiment
disproves Mill's test,
shows that that's not an adequate way,
that you can't distinguish
higher pleasures
within the utilitarian framework?
Yes?
If whatever is good is truly just
whatever people prefer,
it's truly relative
and there's no objective definition,
then there will be some society
where people prefer Simpsons more.
Anyone can appreciate The Simpsons
but I think it does take education
to appreciate Shakespeare as much.
All right, you're saying
it takes education
to appreciate higher true things.
Mill's point is that the
higher pleasures do require
cultivation and appreciation
and education.
He doesn't dispute that.
But once having been cultivated
and educated, people will see,
not only see the difference
between higher and lower pleasures,
but will actually prefer
the higher to the lower.
You find this famous passage
from John Stuart Mill.
"It is better to be a human being
dissatisfied than a pig satisfied;
better to be Socrates
dissatisfied than a fool satisfied.
And if the fool, or the pig,
are of a different opinion,
it is because they only know
their side of the question."
So here, you have an attempt
to distinguish
higher from lower pleasures.
So going to an art museum
or being a couch potato
and swilling beer,
watching television at home.
Sometimes, Mill agrees,
we might succumb to the temptation
to do the latter,
to be couch potatoes.
But even when we do that
out of indolence and sloth,
we know that the pleasure we get
gazing at Rembrandts in the museum
is actually higher
because we've experienced both,
and it is a higher pleasure
gazing at Rembrandts
because it engages our
higher human faculties.
What about Mill's attempt to reply to
the objection about individual rights?
In a way, he uses the same kind
of argument,
and this comes out in chapter five.
He says, "I dispute the pretensions
of any theory which sets up
an imaginary standard
of justice not grounded on utility."
But still, he considers justice
grounded on utility to be what he calls
"the chief part and incomparably,
the most sacred
and binding part of all morality."
So justice is higher,
individual rights are privileged,
but not for reasons that depart
from utilitarian assumptions.
Justice is a name,
for certain moral requirements,
which, regarded collectively,
stand higher in the scale
of social utility and are,
therefore, of more paramount
obligation than any others.
So justice, it is sacred.
It's prior.
It's privileged.
It isn't something that can easily
be traded off against lesser things.
But the reason is ultimately,
Mill claims, a utilitarian reason
once you consider
the long-run interests of humankind,
of all of us as progressive beings.
If we do justice
and if we respect rights,
society as a whole will be
better off in the long run.
Well, is that convincing or is Mill
actually, without admitting it,
stepping outside utilitarian
considerations in arguing for
qualitatively higher pleasures
and for sacred
or especially important
individual rights?
We haven't fully answered that question
because to answer that question,
in the case of rights and justice,
will require that
we explore other ways,
non-utilitarian ways
of accounting for the basis
of rights and then asking
whether they succeed.
As for Jeremy Bentham,
who launched utilitarianism
as a doctrine in moral
and legal philosophy,
Bentham died in 1832
at the age of 85.
But if you go to London,
you can visit him today literally.
He provided in his will
that his body be preserved,
embalmed, and displayed
in the University of London,
where he still presides
in a glass case with a wax head,
dressed in his actual clothing.
You see, before he died,
Bentham addressed himself
to a question consistent
with his philosophy.
Of what use could a dead man
be to the living?
One use, he said,
would be to make one's corpse
available to the study of anatomy.
In the case of great philosophers,
however, better yet to preserve
one's physical presence in order to
inspire future generations of thinkers.
You want to see
what Bentham looks like stuffed?
Here is what he looks like.
There he is.
Now, if you look closely,
you will notice that the embalming
of his actual head
was not a success,
so they substituted a waxed head
and at the bottom, for verisimilitude,
you can actually see
his actual head on a plate.
You see it?
Right there.
So, what's the moral of the story?
The moral of the story -
and by the way,
they bring him out
during meetings of the board
at University College London
and the minutes record him
as present but not voting.
Here is a philosopher in life
and in death
who adhered to the principles
of his philosophy.
We'll continue with rights next time.
Don't miss the chance to interact
online with other viewers of Justice.
Join the conversation,
take a pop quiz,
watch lectures you've missed,
and learn a lot more.
It's at justiceharvard.org.
It's the right thing to do.