Captions proofread by @xiaolai, www.lixiaolai.com
We ended last time talking about
the narrative conception of the self.
We were testing the narrative
conception of the self
and the idea of obligations
of solidarity or membership
that did not flow
from consent,
that claimed us for reasons unrelated
to a contract or an agreement
or a choice we
may have made.
And we were debating
among ourselves
whether there are any
obligations of this kind
or whether all apparent obligations
of solidarity and membership
can be translated into
consent or reciprocity
or universal duty that we
owe persons qua persons.
And then there were those who defended
the idea of loyalty and of patriotism.
So the idea of loyalty and of
solidarity and of membership
gathered a certain kind of
intuitive moral force
in our discussion.
And then, as
we concluded,
we considered what seems to be a pretty
powerful counter example to that idea.
Namely, the film of those southern
segregationists in the 1950s.
And they talked all
about their traditions,
their history, the way in which
their identities were bound up
with their life history.
Do you remember that?
And what flowed from that history,
from that narrative sense of identity
for those southern
segregationists?
They said we have to
defend our way of life.
Is this a fatal or a decisive
objection to the idea
of the narrative
conception of the self?
That's the question
we were left with.
What I would like to do today
is to advance an argument
and see what you make of it.
And let me tell you
what that argument is.
I would like to defend
the narrative conception
of the person
as against the voluntarist
conception.
I would like to defend
the idea that there are obligations
of solidarity or membership.
Then, I want to suggest
that there being
such obligations
lends force to the idea,
when we turn to justice,
that arguments about
justice can't be detached,
cannot be detached after all,
from questions of the good.
But I wanted to distinguish
two different ways
in which justice might
be tied to the good
and argue for one of them.
Now, the voluntarist conception
of the person of Kant and Rawls
we saw was powerful
and liberating.
A further appeal is its
universal aspiration.
The idea of treating
persons as persons
without prejudice,
without discrimination,
and I think that's what led
some among us to argue that,
okay, maybe there are obligations of
membership but they are always subordinate.
They must always
be subordinate
to the duties that we have to human
beings as such, the universal duties.
But is that right?
If our encompassing loyalty
should always take precedence
over more particular ones,
then the distinction between
friends and strangers
should ideally be overcome.
A special concern for the welfare of
friends would be a kind of prejudice,
a measure of our distance
from universal human concern
But if you look
closely at that idea,
what kind of a moral universe,
what kind of moral imagination,
would that lead you to?
The enlightenment flows
from Montesquieu
gives perhaps the most
powerful, and I think,
the ultimately, the
most honest account
of where this relentless
universalizing tendency
leads the moral imagination.
Here's how Montesquieu put it.
He said, "A truly virtuous
man would come to the aid
of the most distant stranger as
quickly as to his own friend."
And then he adds,
listen to this,
"If men were perfectly virtuous,
they wouldn't have friends."
But it's difficult to
imagine a world
in which persons were so virtuous
that they had no friends,
only a universal disposition
to friendliness.
The problem isn't simply
that such a world
would be difficult to bring
about, that it's unrealistic.
The deeper problem
is that such a world
would be difficult to recognize
as a human world.
The love of humanity
is a noble sentiment
but most of the time we live
our lives by smaller solidarities.
This may reflect certain limits to
the bounds of moral sympathy,
but more important,
it reflects the fact
that we learn to love
humanity, not in general,
but through its
particular expressions.
So these are some
considerations.
They're not knock-down arguments,
but moral philosophy can't offer
knock-down arguments,
but considerations, of the
kinds that we've been
discussing and arguing
about all along.
Well, suppose that's right.
One way of assessing whether
this picture of the person
and of obligation
is right, is to see
what are its consequences
for justice.
And here is where is
confronts a serious problem,
and here we go back to our
southern segregationists.
They felt the weight
of history.
Do we admire their character,
these segregationists,
who wanted to preserve
their way of life?
Are we committed
to saying,
if we accept the idea of
solidarity and membership,
are we committed
to saying
that justice is tied to good in
the sense that justice means
whatever a particular community
or tradition says it means,
including those southern
segregationists.
Here it's important to
distinguish two different ways
in which justice can
be tied to the good.
One is a relativist way.
That's the way
that says,
to think about rights,
to think about justice,
look to the values that
happened to prevail
in any given community
at any given time.
Don't judge them by
some outside standard,
but instead conceive justice as a matter of
being faithful to the shared understandings
of a particular tradition.
But there's a problem with this
way of tying justice to the good.
The problem is that it makes
justice wholly conventional.
A product of circumstance,
and this deprives justice
of its critical character.
But there is a second
way in which
justice can be tied with or
bound up with the good.
On a second non-relativist way of linking
justice with conceptions of the good,
principles of justice depend for their
justification not on the values
that happened to prevail at any
given moment in a certain place,
but instead on the moral worth or the
intrinsic good of the ends rights serve.
On this non-relativist view the
case for recognizing a right
depends on showing that it
honors or advances some
important human good.
The second way of tying
justice to the good
is not strictly speaking,
communitarian,
if by communitarian
you mean,
just giving over to a particular
community the definition of justice.
Now, what I would
like to suggest
that of these two different ways
of linking justice to the good,
the first is insufficient.
Because the first leaves justice
the creature of convention.
It doesn't give us enough
moral resources to respond to
those southern segregationists
who invoke their way
of life, their traditions,
their way of doing things.
But if justice is bound up with
the good in a non-relativist way,
there is a big challenge,
a big question to answer.
How can we reason
about the good?
What about the fact that people hold
different conceptions of the good?
Different ideas about the purposes
of key social institutions.
Different ideas about what
social goods and human goods
are worthy of honor
and recognition.
We live in a pluralist society,
people disagree about the good.
That's one of the incentives to
try to find principles of justice
and rights that don't depend
on any particular ends
or purposes or goods.
So is there a way to
reason about the good?
Before addressing
that question,
I want to address a
slightly easier question.
Is it necessary, is it unavoidable,
when arguing about justice
to argue about the good?
And my answer to that question
is yes, it's unavoidable.
It's necessary.
So for the remainder of today,
I want to take up...
I want to try to
advance that claim,
that reasoning about the good,
about purposes, and ends,
is an unavoidable feature
of arguing about justice,
it's necessary.
Let me see if I can
establish that.
And for that I'd like for us to begin
a discussion of same sex marriage.
Now, same sex marriage
draws on, implicateds,
deeply contested and
controversial ideas,
morally and religiously.
And so there's a
powerful incentive
to embrace a conception
of justice or of rights
that doesn't require the society
as a whole to pass judgment,
one way or another,
on those hotly contested moral
and religious questions.
About the moral permissibility
of homosexuality.
About the proper ends of
marriage as a social institution.
So, clearly, if there's an incentive
to resolve this question,
to define people's rights in a way that
doesn't require the society as a whole
to sort out those moral
and religious disputes
that would be very attractive.
So what I would like
to do now is to see,
using the same sex
marriage case,
whether it's possible
to detach one's use
about the moral permissibility
of homosexuality and about
the purpose, the
end of marriage,
detach those questions
from the question of
whether the state should recognize
same sex marriage or not.
So let's begin.
I would like to begin by hearing
the arguments of those
who believe that there should
be no same sex marriage
but that the state should only recognize
marriage between a man and a woman.
Do I have volunteers?
I had two.
There were two
people I asked,
people who had voiced their views
already on the justice blog.
Mark Loff and Ryan McCaffrey
where are you?
Okay, Mark.
And where is Ryan?
Alright, let's
go first to Mark.
I have sort of a theological
understanding of
the purpose of sex and
the purpose of marriage.
And I think that for people like myself,
who are a a Christian and also a Catholic,
the purpose of sex is, one,
for its procreative uses,
and two, for a unifying purpose
between a man and a woman
within the institution of marriage.
You have a certain conception of
the purpose or the telos... - Yeah.
...of human sexuality, which is
bound up with procreation.
Right.
As well as union.
- Yeah.
And the essence of marriage, the purpose
of marriage as a social institution
is to give expression
to that telos
and to honor that purpose, namely,
the procreative purpose of marriage.
Is that a fair summary of your view?
- Yeah.
Where is Ryan?
Go ahead.
Do you agree more or less
with Mark's reasons?
Yes, I agree.
I think that the ideal of
marriage involves procreation.
And it's fine that, homosexuals would
go off and cohabitate with each other
but the government doesn't have
a responsibility to encourage that.
All right, so the government
should not encourage
homosexual behavior by conferring
the recognition of marriage.
Yeah, it would be wrong to outlaw it
but encouraging it is not necessary.
Who has a reply?
Yes.
Hannah?
I just like to ask a
question to Mark.
Let's say you got
married to a woman,
you did not have sex with
her before marriage,
and then when you became
married it became evident that
you're an infertile couple.
Do you think that it should illegal
for you to engage in sex
if children will not result
from that act?
Yeah, I think that it is moral and that's
why I gave the two-fold purpose.
So like a woman, say...
I think older couples
can get married,
someone... a woman
who's beyond...
she has already had menopause
and who can't have a child,
because I think that
sex has these...
It has purposes
beyond procreation.
I hate to be uncouth but have you
ever engaged in masturbation?
You don't have
to answer that.
Right, make your...
I'd like to respond to that.
Wait. We've done pretty
well over a whole semester
and we're doing pretty
well now dealing with
questions that most people think can't even
be discussed to any university settting
and, Hannah, you've got,
you have a powerful point.
Make that point as a general
argument rather than,
Rather than as an
interrogative.
Okay.
- But make the point.
What's the principle
that you're appealing?
What's the argument
you have in mind?
Alrightt. Well, biblically...
- Put it in the third person.
Yeah, okay.
- Rather than...
...Rather than in a second person.
Make the argument.
Okay. Biblically, masturbation
or onanism, is not permissible
because it's spilling your
seed on the earth
when it's not going to result
in the birth of a child.
But what I'm saying is,
you're saying that sex,
there's something wrong with sex
if it doesn't produce children
or reinforce the marriage bond.
- Right.
But then how can you say that
there's something wrong,
that masturbation is permissible,
if masturbation, obviously,
is not going to
create a child?
I think marriage is society's way
to create a separate institution
where they say this is
what we hold as a virtue.
Yes, every day we fall short
and people fall short
in so many different other ways,
but I think that if you
personally fall short,
and some morals fear,
as we all do,
that doesn't take the right
of you to argue.
All right, I want
you, to stay there.
I want to bring in some other
voices and we'll continue.
Stay there if you would.
Go ahead.
I think that the response
to the masturbation-
Wait, tell us your name.
- My name's Steve.
Steve, go ahead.
The response to the
masturbation issue is,
it's not something
that's permissible.
I don't think anyone will argue that
homosexual sex is impermissible.
It's just that society has no place
in letting you marry yourself
if masturbation is
something that you do.
Well, all right, Hannah.
Alright, Steve has drawn...
Alright, that's a good argument.
Steve has drawn our attention to the
fact that there are two issues here.
One of them is the moral
permissibility of various practices.
The other is the fit between
certain practices,
whatever their moral
permissibility,
with the honor
or recognition
that the state should accord
in allowing marriage.
So Steve has a pretty good
counter argument.
What do you say to Steve?
Well, I think that it's clear
that human sexuality
is something that is inherent
in, I believe, most people
and it's not something
you can avoid.
And masturbation, I mean,
yeah, you can't marry yourself
but I don't think that takes
away from the fact that
homosexuals are people too.
And I can't understand why they
wouldn't be able to marry each other.
If you want to
marry yourself,
I mean, I don't know if
you can legally do that.
That's fine but I don't think-
- Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait!
Now, here we're deciding,
here we're deliberating
as if legislators, what
the law should be.
So you said, Steve, that's fine.
Does that mean as a
legislator you would vote
for a law of marriage that
would be so broad
that it would let people
marry themselves?
Well, I mean, that's really
beyond the pale of
anything that would
really happen but
I don't think that-
- But in principle.
Yeah, in principle?
- Yes.
Yeah, sure, I mean if Steve
wants to marry himself
I'm not going
to stop him.
And you would confer state
recognition on that solo marriage?
Sure.
And while we're at it,
what about consensual
polygamous marriages?
I actually think that if
the male and the female,
or that if the wives and the man,
of the husbands and the wife
are consenting, it should
be permissible.
Who else? I know there are
a lot of people who...
Yes, okay, down here.
Stand up and tell
us your name.
Victoria.
- Victoria.
So we're talking about the theological
reasoning here for marriage
but I think the problem is that we're talking
about it within the Catholic viewpoint.
Whereas, the theological,
and the point to marriage
for another religion or
someone who's an atheist
could be completely different.
And the government doesn't
have a right to impose
the theological reasoning for Catholicism
on everyone in the state.
Which is what my problem is with
not allowing same sex marriage.
Because, I mean, you're beliefs
are your beliefs, and that's fine,
but civil union is not marriage
within the Catholic Church.
And the state has a right to
recognize a civil union between
whoever it wants, but
does not have a right
to impose the beliefs of a certain
minority or majority of whoever it is
based on religion
within our state.
Alright, Victoria, good.
A question.
Do you think the state should
recognize same sex marriage
or just same sex civil unions as
something short of marriage?
Well, I think that the state doesn't
have a right to recognize it
as marriage within a church,
because that is not their place.
But whereas civil union, I see civil union
as essentially the same thing except
not under a religion and that state
has a right to recognize a civil union.
Alright, so, Victoria's argument is
that the state should not try to
decide the question of what
the telos of marriage is.
That's only something that
religious communities can decide.
Who else?
My point is I don't see
why you feel like
the state should recognize
marriages at all.
I'm like one of the 70
people who voted
that the state should not
recognize any marriages
because I believe it is a union
between male and a female
or two males or
two females.
But there's no reason to ask the state to
give permission to me to unite myself.
And some might say that, if the
state recognizes these marriages,
it will help children, it will
have a binding effect.
But in reality, I don't think it
actually has a binding effect.
Alright, tell us your name.
- Cezanne.
So, Victoria and
Cezanne's comments
differ from earlier parts
of the conversation.
They say
the state shouldn't
be in the business
of honoring or recognizing
or affirming
any particular telos, or
purpose of marriage,
or of human sexuality.
And Cezanne is among
those who says,
therefore, maybe the state
should get out of the business
of recognizing
marriage at all.
Here's the question.
Unless, you adopt
Cezanne's position,
no state recognition of
any kind of marriage,
is it possible to choose between...
...to decide the question
of same sex marriage
without taking a stand on the
moral and religious controversy
over the proper telos
of marriage.
Thank you very much to all of
you who have participated.
We'll pick this up next time.
You did a great job.
When we first came together
some 13 weeks ago
I tried to warn you that once
the familiar turns strange
once we begin to reflect
on our circumstance,
it's never quite the same again.
I hope you have by now experienced
at least a little of this unease
because this is the tension that
animates critical reflection
and political improvement
and maybe even the
moral life as well.
We have two remaining
questions to answer.
First, is it necessary,
is it unavoidable
to take up questions of the good
life in thinking about justice? Yes.
And is it possible to
reason about justice?
Yes, I think so.
Let me try to develop those
answers to those two questions.
Now, as a way of addressing those
questions, we began last time
to discuss the question
of same sex marriage.
And we heard from those who
argued against same sex marriage
on the grounds that the
purpose, or telos, or marriage
is at least in part,
procreation,
the bearing and
raising of children.
And then there were those who
defended same sex marriage
and they contested that account of
the purpose, or telos, of marriage
arguing we don't require as a
condition of heterosexual marriage
that couples be able or
willing to procreate.
We allow infertile
couples to marry.
This was Hannah's point in
the exchange with Mark.
Then there was
another position
expressed at the end our
discussion by Victoria,
who argued we shouldn't
try to decide this question.
We shouldn't, at least at the level
of the state, at the level of law,
try to come to any agreement on
those questions about the good
because we live in a pluralist society
where people had different
moral and religious convictions.
And so we should
try to make law
in the framework
of rights, neutral
with respect to these competing
moral and religious views.
Now, it's interesting that
others, some others,
who favor the idea
of neutrality
argued, not in favor of restricting
marriage to a man and a woman,
nor in favor of permitting
same sex marriage,
they argued in the
name of neutrality,
for a third possibility.
Which is that government
get out of the business
of recognizing any
kind of marriage.
That was the third possibility.
Now, Andrea Mayrose had an interesting
contribution to this debate.
She had a rejoinder to people
who argue for neutrality.
Where is Andrea?
Alright, Andrea, would
you be willing...
Share with us the view.
If we can get you a microphone.
Share with us your view.
Why do you think
that it's a mistake
for the state to
try to be neutral
moral and even religious questions
like same sex marriage?
I don't know that it is possible
because people's lives are
completely embedded in
how they view the world.
And maybe I just agree
with Aristotle that
the role of the government is
helping people live in a sort of...
Having a collective understanding
what is wrong and what is right.
Is it possible, and one could ask
the same question of abortion,
that we've been asking
of same sex marriage.
Do you think it's possible
to decide whether
abortion should be
permitted or prohibited
without taking a stand
or making a judgment
about the moral permissibility
of abortion?
No, I don't think it is and I think
that's why it's such a controversy
because people are so
deeply committed to,
their fundamental beliefs about
whether a fetus is a life or if it isn't.
If I believe that, a fetus is a
living being and has rights
and has fundamentally
the right to live,
then it's very hard
for me to say,
"But I can put that aside and
let you do what you want,"
because that's
like me saying,
"well, despite my beliefs, I'm going to
let you commit what to me is murder."
So, I mean, that's just one...
Alright, and the analogy in the
same sex marriage case is,
you said, you're a defender
of same sex marriage. - Yes.
But you only came
to that view
once you were persuaded
on the underlying
moral question.
Right, well, I think
particularly, in the US
so many people's beliefs are
driven by their religious beliefs
and like Mark the other day,
I'm a Christian, I'm Catholic,
and I had to decide for myself
on a lot of thought,
a lot of prayer, a lot of
conversations with other people
that I disagreed with
the Catholic standpoint
that homosexuality
itself isn't a sin.
And once I came to that, sort of conclusion,
in my personal relationship with god,
I mean, that's sounds hokey, right?
That's like, oh, religious!
But a lot of people are religious
and that's where they draw
theif beliefs and
their views from.
That's when I could say, yeah,
I'm down with the state saying,
"Go same sex marriage!"
because I'm okay with that
and I think that's morally okay.
Good, thank you.
Now, who would
like to reply?
If you can, perhaps, hang
on there for a moment.
Who would like to reply
to Andrea's idea
that in order to decide the
question of same sex marriage,
it's necessary to sort out
the question about the
moral status of
homosexuality
and figuring out the purpose, the
telos, the proper end, of marriage?
Who disagrees with
Andrea on that point?
Yes.
Well, I think you absolutely can
separate your moral opinion
and what you think
the law should be.
For example, I
think abortion is
unequivocally morally wrong.
But I do not believe that illegalizing
abortion makes it go away.
I don't believe illegalizing
abortion stops it.
And, therefore, I am pro choice and I do
believe the woman should have the choice
as it gives it more
safety just as,
maybe, morally, I don't want
to get married to a man,
but I'm not going try to,
impede someone else's freedom to do
what they wish to do in terms of the law.
Andrea?
Whether the law makes
something legal or illegal,
it's implicitly approving or
disapproving something.
So if you say, by making abortion
legal, we're saying it's okay.
As a society, collectively, we're saying
it's okay with us in our society
to abort a fetus.
If we make it illegal, then we're
saying collectively as a society
it's not okay, and that's why
societies have different beliefs.
Tell us your name before you...
- My name is Daniel.
Daniel, what do you say?
Are we saying collectively
that it's okay?
Or are we saying that
collectively we don't
want women who are going to
have an aboration anyway
to go to clinics in
the side alleys
and have unsafe conditions?
Alright, bring it to the
same sex marriage case.
Why don't you have to decide that
which position you're in favor of
same sex marriage, Daniel,
being legally permitted?
I think it absolutely should
be legally permitted
because it's not something
telling me that I need to have...
I need to marry a man.
I absolutely don't, I don't see,
if two men are consenting adults
and want to get married, I don't
see how I could even object to that.
Alright, there's no harm.
There's no harm done.
There's no harm
done either way,
even if it is morally wrong
according to me.
Alright, let me turn to the way
the Massachusetts court,
who made this landmark ruling
in the same sex marriage case,
grappled with the very issue
that Andrea and Dan had been
discussing here.
Thanks to both of you very much.
What did the court say?
This was in the Goodridge
case which
required the state
of Massachusetts
to extend marriage
to same sex couples.
The court started out, well,
the court was conflicted.
If you read that opinion carefully,
the court was conflicted
as between the two positions
we've just been hearing,
defended by Andrea
and by Dan.
The court begins, and this is
Chief Justice Margaret Marshall's opinion,
it begins with an attempt
at liberal neutrality.
Many people hold deep-seated
religious, moral and ethical convictions
that marriage should be limited to the
union of one man and one woman,
and that homosexual
conduct is immoral.
Many hold equally strong religous,
moral, and ehtical convictions
that same sex souples are
entitled to be married,
that homosexual persons should
be treated no differently
than their heterosexual neighbors.
This is the court.
Neither view answers
the question before us.
What is at stake is "respect for individual
autonomy and equality under law."
At stake is an individual freely
choosing the person with whom
to share an exclusive
commitment.
In other words, the issue is not
the moral worth of the choice
but the right of the
individual to make it.
So this is the liberal neutral
strand in the court opinion,
voluntarist strand, the one
that emphasizes autonomy,
choice, consent.
But the court seemed to realize
that the liberal case,
the neutral case, for recognizing
same sex marriage doesn't succeed,
doesn't get you all the
way to that position,
because if it were only a matter of
respect for individual autonomy,
if government were truly
neutral on the moral worth
of voluntary intimate
relationships,
then it should adopt
a different policy.
Which is to remove government
and the state all together
from according recognition
to certain associations,
certain kinds of unions,
rather than others.
If government really
must be neutral,
then the consistent
position is what we here
have been describing
as the third position,
the one defended in the
article by Michael Kinsley,
who argues for the
abolition of marriage,
at least as a state function.
Perhaps a better term for this is
the disestablishment of religion.
This is Kinsley's proposal.
He points out that the reason for the
opposition to same sex marriage
is that it would go beyond
neutral toleration
and give same sex marriage a
government stamp of approval.
That's at the heart
of the dispute.
In Aristotle's terms,
at issue here
is the proper distribution
of offices and honors,
a matter of social recognition.
Same sex marriage
can't be justified
on the basis of liberal neutrality or
non-discrimination or autonomy rights alone
because the question at
stake in the public debate
is whether same sex
unions have moral worth,
whether they're worthy
of honor and recognition,
and whether they fit the purpose
of the social institution of marriage.
So Kinsley says, you
want to be neutral?
Then, let churches and other religous
institutions offer marriage ceremonies.
Let department stores and casinos
get into the act if they want to.
This is Kinsley.
Let couples celebrate their
union in any way they choose
and consider themselves
married whenever they want.
And if three people
want to get married,
or if one person wants to
marry himself or herself,
and someone else wants to
conduct a ceremony for them
and declare them
married, let them.
If you and your government aren't
implicated, what do you care?
This is Kinsley.
But this is not the position that
the Supreme Judicial Court
of Massachusetts wanted.
They didn't call for the abolition or for
the disestablishment of marriage.
The court did not question
government's role in conferring
social recognition on some intimate
associations rather than others.
To the contrary,
the court waxes eloquent
about marriage
as, "one of our community's most
rewarding and cherished institutions."
And then it goes on to expand
the definition of marriage
to include partners
of the same sex.
And in doing so
it acknowledges
that marriage is more
than a matter
of tolerating choices
that individuals make.
It's also a matter of social
recognition and honor.
As Justice Marshall wrote.
In a real sense there are three
partners to every civil marriage:
two willing spouses and
an approving state.
Marriage is at once a deeply
personal cimmitment,
but also a highly public
celebration of the ideals of
mutuality, companionship,
intimacy, fidelity, and family.
This is the court.
Now, this is reaching well
beyond liberal neutrality.
This is celebrating and affirming
marriage as an honorific,
as a form of public recognition.
And, therefore, the court found
that it couldn't avoid the debate
about the telos of marriage.
Justice Marshall's opinion considers
and rejects the notion
that the primary purpose of
marriage is procreation.
She points out that
there is no requirement
that applicants for marriage license,
who are heterosexuals,
attest to their ability or their
intention to conceive children.
Fertility is not a condition
of marriage.
People who cannot stir from
their deathbed, they marry.
So she advances all
kinds of arguments,
along the lines that
we began last time,
about the proper and the essential
nature, the telos of marriage, is.
And she concludes, not
procreation but the exclusive
and permanent commitment
of the partners to one another
is the essential point and
purpose of marriage.
Now, nothing I've said
about this court opinion
is an argument for or against
same sex marriage.
But it is an argument
against the claim
that you can favor or oppose
same sex marriage
while remaining neutral on the underlying
moral and religious questions.
So all of this is to suggest
that at least in some of the
hotly contested debates
about justice and rights that
we have in our society,
the attempt to be neutral,
the attempt to say,
it's just a matter of consent
and choice and autonomy,
we take no stand.
That doesn't succeed.
Even the court, which wants to be neutral
on these moral and religious disputes,
finds that it can't.
What then about our
second question?
If reasoning about the
good is unavoidable
in debates about
justice and rights,
is it possible?
If reasoning about
the good means
that you must have a single
principle or rule or maxim
or criterion for the good life,
that you simply plug in
every time you have
a disagreement about morality,
then the answer is, no.
But having a single principle
or rule is not the only way,
not the best way of reasoning
either about the good
life or about justice.
Think back, think back to the arguments
that we've been having here
about justice and about rights and
sometimes about the good life.
How have those arguments
proceeded?
They've proceeded very
much in the way
that Aristotle suggests
moving back and forth
between our judgments
about particulars,
particular cases, events,
stories, questions,
back and forth between our
judgments about particular cases
and more general principles
that make sense
of our reasons for the positions
we take on the particular cases.
This dialectical way of doing
moral reasoning goes back
to the ancients, to
Plato and Aristotle,
but it doesn't stop with them,
because there is a version of Socratic
or dialectical moral reasoning
that is defended with great clarity
and force by John Rawls
in giving an account of his method
of justifying a theory of justice.
You remember it's not only the veil
of ignorance and the principles
that Rawls argues for.
It's also a method
of moral reasoning,
reasoning about justice that
he calls reflective equilibrium.
What is the method of
reflective equilibrium?
It's moving back and forth between our
considered judgments about particular cases
and the general principles
we would articulate
to make sense of
those judgments.
And not just stopping there,
because we might be wrong
in our initial intuitions.
Not stopping there but then sometimes
revising our particular judgments
in the light of the principles
once we work them out.
So sometimes we revise the principles,
sometimes we revise our judgments
and intuitions in the
particular cases.
The general point is this,
and here I quote Rawls.
A conception of justice can't be
deduced from self evicdent premises.
Its justification is a matter of the mustual
support of many considerations,
of everything fitting together
into one coherent view.
And later in the theory
of justice, he writes,
moral philosophy is Socratic.
We may want to change our
present considered judgments
once their regulative principles
are brought to light.
Well, if Rawls
accepts that idea
and advances that notion
of reflective equilibrium,
the question we're
left with is,
he applies that to
questions of justice,
not to questions of morality
and the good life.
And that's why he remains
committed to the priority
of the right over the good.
He thinks the method
of reflective equilibrium
can generate shared judgments
about justice in the right
but he doesn't think they can
generate shared judgments
about the good life,
about what he calls
comprehensive moral and
religious question.
And the reason he thinks
that is that he says that
in modern societies there is a fact or
reasonable pluralism about the good.
Even conscientious people
who reason well,
will find that they
disagree about questions
of the good life, about
morality and religion.
And Rawls is likely
right about that.
He's not talking about the fact of
disagreement in pluralist societies.
He's also suggesting that
there may be persisting
disagreements about the good life and
about moral and religious questions.
But if that's true, then
is he warranted in
his further claim
that the same can't be
said about justice?
Isn't it also true, not only that
we, as a matter of fact, disagree
about justice in
pluralist societies,
but that at least some of those disagreements
are reasonable disagreements?
In the same way,
some people favor a libertarian
theory of justice,
others are more egalitarian theory
of justice and they argue.
And there is pluralism in our society
as between free market laissez faire,
libertarian theories of justice
and more egalitarian ones.
Is there any difference
in principle
between the kind of moral reasoning and
the kind of disagreements that arise
when we debate about justice
and the meaning
of free speech
and the nature of
religious liberty?
Look at the debates
we have over
appointees to the
Supreme Court.
These are all disagreements
about justice and rights.
Is there any difference between
the fact of reasonable pluralism
in the case of justice and rights and
in the case of morality and religion?
In principle I don't
think that there is.
In both cases what we
do when we disagree is
we engage with our interlocutor, as we've
been doing here for an entire semester.
We consider the arguments that are
provoked by particular cases.
We try to develop the reasons that lead
us to go one way rather than another.
And then we listen to the
reasons of other people.
And sometimes we're persuaded
to revise our view.
Other times we're challenged at least
to shore up and strengthen our view.
But this is how moral
argument proceeds,
with justice, and so it
seems to me, also
with questions of
the good life.
Now, there remains
a further worry
and it's a liberal worry,
what about if we are going to think of our
disagreements about morality and religion
as bound up with our
disagreements about justice,
how are we ever going to
find our way to a society
that accords respect to fellow
citizens with whom we disagree?
It depends I think on which conception
of respect one accepts.
On the liberal conception, to
respect our fellow citizens'
moral and religious convictions,
is, so to speak, to ignore them,
for political purposes.
To rise above or to abstract
from or to set aside
those moral and
religious convictions.
To leave them undisturbed,
to carry on our political debate
without reference to them.
But that isn't the only way,
or perhaps even the
most plausible way
of understanding the
mutual respect
on which democratic
life depends.
There is a different conception of
respect according to which we respect
our fellow citizens' moral
and religious convictions,
not by ignoring, but
by engaging them.
By attending to them.
Sometimes by challenging
and contesting them.
Sometimes by listening and
learning from them.
Now, there's no guarantee
that a politics
of moral and religious attention
and engagement
will lead in any given
case to agreement.
There is no guarantee it will
lead even to appreciation
for the moral and religious
convictions of others.
It's always possible,
after all,
that learning more about a
religious or a moral doctrine
will lead us to like it less.
But the respect of deliberation
and engagement
seems to me a more adequate, more
suitable ideal for a pluralist society.
And to the extent that our moral
and religious disagreements reflect
some ultimate plurality
of human goods.
A politics of moral engagement will
better enable us, so it seems to me,
to appreciate the distinctive goods
our different lives expressed.
When we first came together
some 13 weeks ago,
I spoke of the exhilaration
of political philosophy
and also of its dangers.
About how philosophy works
and has always worked
by estranging us from the familiar
by unsettling our settled assumptions.
And I tried to warn you that once
the familiar turns strange,
once we begin to reflect
on our circumstance,
it's never quite the same again.
I hope you have by now experienced
at least a little of this unease
because this is the tension that animates
critical reflection and political improvement
and maybe even the
moral life as well.
And so our argument comes
to an end, in a sense,
but in another
sense goes on.
Why, we asked at the outset,
why did these arguments keep
going even if they raise questions
that are impossible ever,
finally, to resolve?
The reason is that we live some answer
to these questions all the time.
In our public life, and
in our personal lives,
philosophy is inescapable even
if it sometimes seems impossible.
We began with the
thought of Kant,
that skepticism is a resting
place for human reason.
Where it can reflect upon
its dogmatic wanderings,
but it is no dwelling place
for permanent settlement.
To allow ourselves simply to
acquiescence in skepticism
or in complacence, Kant
wrote, can never suffice
to overcome the
restlessness of reason.
The aim of this course
has been to awaken
the restlessness of reason
and to see where it might lead.
And if we had done
at least that,
and if the restlessness
continues to afflict you
in the days and
years to come,
then we together have
achieved no small thing.
Thank you.