Captions proofread by @xiaolai, www.lixiaolai.com
THE GOOD CITIZEN
We turn to Aristotle
after examining theories,
modern theories, of justice
that try to detach
considerations of
justice and rights
from questions of
moral desert and virtue.
Aristotle disagrees
with Kant and Rawls.
Aristotle argues that justice is a matter
of giving people what they deserve.
And the central idea of
Aristotle's theory of justice
is that in reasoning
about justice and rights
we have,
unavoidably,
to reason about the purpose,
or the end, or the telos,
of social practices in institutions.
Yes, justice requires giving equal things
to equal persons,
but the question immediately arises,
in any debate about justice,
equal in what respect?
And Aristotle says we need to fill in
the answer to that question
by looking to the
characteristic end,
or the essential nature,
or the purpose,
of the thing we're distributing.
And so we discussed
Aristotle's example of flutes;
who should get the best flutes.
And Aristotle's answer was
the best flute-players.
The best flute-player
should get the best flute
because that's the way
of honoring
the excellence
of flute playing.
It's a way of rewarding the virtue
of the great flute-player.
What's interesting though,
and this is what we are
going to explore today,
is that it's not quite so easy
to dispense with teleological reasoning
when we're thinking
about social institutions
and political practices.
In general it's hard
to do without teleology
when we're thinking about
ethics, justice, and moral argument.
At least that is Aristotle's claim.
And I would like to bring out
the force in Aristotle's claim
by considering two examples.
One is an example that Aristotle
spends quite a bit of time discussing;
the case of politics.
How should political offices
and honors,
how should political rule
be distributed?
The second example is a
contemporary debate about golf
and whether the
Professional Golfers Association
should be required
to allow Casey Martin,
a golfer with a disability,
to ride in a golf cart.
Both cases
bring out
a further feature
of Aristotle's teleological way
of thinking about justice.
And that is that when we attend
to the telos, or the purpose,
sometimes we disagree and argue
about what the purpose
of a social practice
really consists in.
And when we have
those disagreements
part of what's at stake
in those disagreements
is not just who will get what,
not just a distributive question,
but also an honorific question.
What qualities,
what excellences,
of persons
will be honored?
Debates about
purpose and telos
are often, simultaneously,
debates about honor.
Now, let's see
how that works
in the case of Aristotle's
account of politics.
When we discuss
distributive justice these days
we're mainly concerned with the distribution
of income and wealth and opportunity.
Aristotle took
distributive justice
to be mainly not
about income and wealth
but about offices and honors.
Who should have
the right to rule?
Who should be a citizen?
How should political authority
be distributed?
Those were his questions.
How did he go about
answering those questions?
Well, in line with his
teleological account of justice,
Aristotle argues that to know how
political authority should be distributed
we have, first, to inquire
into the purpose, the point,
the telos,
of politics.
So, what is politics about?
And, how does this help us
decide who should rule?
Well, for Aristotle the answer
to that question is,
politics is about
forming character,
forming good character.
It's about cultivating
the virtue of citizens.
It's about the good life.
The end of the State,
the end of the political community,
he tells us in
Book Three of the Politics,
is not mere life,
it's not economic exchange only,
it's not security only,
it's realizing the good life.
That's what politics is for
according to Aristotle.
Now, you might worry about this.
You might say, "Well, maybe this shows us
why those modern theorists of justice,
and of politics,
are right".
Because remember,
for Kant and for Rawls,
the point of politics is not to shape
the moral character of citizens.
It's not to make us good.
It's to respect our freedom
to choose our goods,
our values,
our ends,
consistent with
a similar liberty for others.
Aristotle disagrees.
"Any polis which is truly so called,
and is not merely one in name,
must devote itself to the end
of encouraging goodness.
Otherwise political association
sinks into a mere alliance.
Law becomes a mere covenant,
a guarantor of man's rights
against one another,
instead of being -
as it should be -
a way of life such as will make
the members of a polis good and just."
That's Aristotle's view.
"A polis is not an association
for residents on a common site,
or for the sake of
preventing mutual injustice
and easing exchange."
Aristotle writes.
"The end and purpose
of a polis is the good life,
and the institutions of social life
are means to that end."
Now, if that's the purpose of politics,
of the polis,
then, Aristotle says,
we can derive from that
the principles of
distributive justice;
the principles that tell us
who should have the greatest say,
who should have the greatest measure
of political authority.
And what's his answer
to that question?
Well, those who contribute the most
to an association of this character,
namely an association
that aims at the good,
should have a greater share in political rule
and in the honors of the polis.
And the reasoning is,
they are in a position
to contribute most
to what political community
is essentially about.
Well, so you can see
the link that he draws
between the principle of distribution
for citizenship and political authority
and the purpose of politics.
"But why,"
you'll quickly ask,
"Why does he claim
that political life,
participation in politics,
is somehow essential
to living a good life?"
"Why isn't it possible
for people to live
perfectly good lives,
decent lives,
moral lives,
without participating in politics?"
Well, he gives two answers
to that question.
He gives a partial answer,
a preliminary answer,
in Book One of the Politics
where he tells us
that only by living in a polis,
and participating in politics,
do we fully realize our nature
as human beings.
Human beings are,
by nature,
meant to live in a polis.
Why?
It's only in political life
that we can actually exercise
our distinctly human capacity
for language,
which Aristotle understands is this capacity
to deliberate about right and wrong,
the just and the unjust.
And so, Aristotle writes
in Book One of the Politics,
that the polis,
the political community,
exists by nature
and is prior to the individual.
Not prior in time,
but prior in its purpose.
Human beings
are not self-sufficient,
living by themselves,
outside a political community.
"Man who is isolated, who is unable to share
in the benefits of political association,
or who has no need to share,
because he's already self-sufficient,
such a person must be
either a beast or a god."
So we only fully
realize our nature,
we only fully unfold
our human capacities,
when we exercise our
faculty of language,
which means when we deliberate
with our fellow citizens
about good and evil,
right and wrong,
just and the unjust.
"But why can we only exercise our capacity
for language in political community?"
you might ask.
Aristotle gives a second part,
a fuller part,
of his answer in the
Nichomachean Ethics;
an excerpt of which
we have among the readings.
And there he explains
that political deliberation,
living the life of a citizen,
ruling and being ruled in turn,
sharing in rule,
all of this is necessary to virtue.
Aristotle defines happiness
not as maximizing the balance
of pleasure over pain
but as an activity,
an activity of the soul
in accordance with virtue.
And he says that every student
of politics must study the soul
because shaping the soul
is one of the objects of legislation
in a good city.
But why is it necessary
to live in a good city
in order to live
a virtuous life?
Why can't we just learn
good moral principles at home
or in a philosophy class
or from a book,
live according to those principles,
those rules,
those precepts,
and leave it at that?
Aristotle says virtue
isn't acquired that way.
Virtue
is only something
we can acquire by practicing,
by exercising the virtues.
It's the kind of thing
we can only learn by doing.
It doesn't come
from book learning.
In this respect,
it's like flute playing;
you couldn't learn how to play
a musical instrument well
just by reading a book about it.
You have to practice,
and you have to listen
to other accomplished flute-players.
There are other practices
and skills of this type.
Cooking;
there are cookbooks
but no great chef ever learns how to cook
by reading a cookbook only.
It's the kind of thing
you only learn by doing.
Joke-telling is probably
another example of this kind.
No great comedian learns to be a comedian
just by reading a book
on the principles of comedy.
It wouldn't work.
Now, why not?
What do joke-telling
and cooking
and playing a musical instrument
have in common
such that we can't learn them
just by grasping a precept or a rule
that we might learn
from a book or a lecture?
What they have in common is
that they are all concerned with
getting the hang of it.
But also what is it we get the hang of
when we learn how to cook,
or play a musical instrument,
or tell jokes well?
Discerning particulars,
particular features of a situation.
And no rule,
no precept,
could tell the comedian or the cook
or the great musician
how to get in the habit of,
the practice of,
discerning the particular features
of a situation.
Aristotle says virtue
is that way too.
Now, how does this
connect to politics?
The only way we can acquire the virtues
that constitute the good life
is to exercise the virtues,
to have certain habits inculcated in us,
and then to engage in the practice
of deliberating with citizens
about the nature of the good.
That's what politics
is ultimately about.
The acquisition of civic virtue,
of this capacity
to deliberate among equals,
that's something we couldn't get
living a life alone outside of politics.
And so, that's why,
in order to realize our nature,
we have to engage in politics.
And that's why those
who are greatest in civic virtue,
like Pericles,
are the ones
who properly have the greatest measure
of offices and honors.
So, the argument about the
distribution of offices and honors
has this teleological character,
but also an honorific dimension.
Because part of the point of politics
is to honor people like Pericles.
It isn't just that Pericles
should have the dominant say
because he has
the best judgment,
and that will lead to
the best outcomes,
to the best consequences
for the citizens.
That's true,
and that's important.
But a further reason
people like Pericles
should have
the greatest measure
of offices, and honors,
and political authority,
and sway in the polis,
is that part of the point of politics
is to single out and honor
those who posses
the relevant virtue,
in this case civic virtue,
civic excellence, practical wisdom,
to the fullest extent.
That's the honorific dimension
bound up with Aristotle's
account of politics.
Here's an example
that shows the link
in a contemporary controversy;
the link to which Aristotle
draws our attention
between arguments about
justice and rights on the one hand
and figuring out the telos or the purpose
of a social practice on the other.
Not only that, the case of
Casey Martin and his golf cart
also brings out
the link between
debates about
what the purpose
of a social practice
or a game
is, on the one hand
and the question of what qualities
should be honored on the other;
the link between teleology
and honor-based
principles of distributive justice.
Who was Casey Martin?
Well, Casey Martin
is a very good golfer.
Able to compete
at the highest levels of golf
but for one thing;
he has a rare
circulatory problem in his leg
that makes it very difficult
for him to walk;
not only difficult but dangerous.
And so he asked the PGA,
which governs the pro tour in golf,
to be able to use a golf cart
when he competed in
professional tournaments.
PGA said no,
and he sued under the
Americans for Disabilities Act;
he sued in a case that went all the way
to the United States Supreme Court.
The question the Supreme Court
had to answer was,
does Casey Martin have a right
that the PGA provide him,
allow him,
to use a golf cart on the tour,
or not?
How many here
think that,
from a moral point of view,
Casey Martin should
have a right to
use a golf cart?
And how many think that he should not
have a right to a golf cart,
in the tournaments?
So the majority are sympathetic
to Casey Martin's right,
though a substantial minority disagree.
Let's first hear from those of you
who would rule against Casey Martin.
Why would you not say that
the PGA must give him a golf cart?
Yes.
Since the inception of golf,
because it has been part of the sport
it is now intrinsically part of golf;
walking the course.
And thus,
because it's intrinsic to golf,
I'd argue that not being able
to walk the course
is just not being able to perform
an aspect of the sport,
which is necessary to performing
at a professional level.
Good.
Stay there for a minute.
What's your name?
Tommy.
Are you a golfer,
by the way, Tom?
Not so much but, yeah,
a little bit.
Are there any golfers
here,
I mean, real golfers?
Thank you, professor,
that was...
No, no.
I'm just taking your word for it.
Is there someone here
on the golf team?
Yes?
Tell us your name,
and tell us what you think.
My name is Michael
and I usually take a cart.
So . . .
I'm probably the wrong
person to ask.
Is that why your hand
went up slowly when I asked?
Yes.
Alright, but Tom is saying,
Tom said a minute ago
that at least at the professional level
walking the course is
essential to the game.
Do you agree?
I would, yes.
You do?
Then why do you take a cart?
And you call yourself
a golfer?
No, no, no.
I'm kidding,
I'm kidding.
What do you say to that?
When I have walked the course
it does add tremendously to the game.
It makes it a lot harder.
It really does.
Yeah?
Alright let's hear,
Michael and Tom stay there,
let's hear from people who
say that he should have
a right to a golf cart.
Why? Who is prepared
to defend that position?
Yes.
Well, I think the PGA
should definitely
be required to give
him a golf cart
because they argue in the decision
that it's not just a matter of,
he's not experiencing fatigue.
For him he's still walking
about a mile,
the cart can't go
everywhere with him,
and in that mile he is still experiencing
more fatigue and pain
than a healthy player would.
So, it's not as if you're
removing the disadvantage.
What's your name?
Riva.
Riva, what do you say
to Tom's point
that walking the course
is essential to the game?
It would be as if
a disabled player could
play in the NBA
but not have to run
up and down the court.
Well, I think there are
two responses to that.
First, I don't think it's
essential to the game,
because most golfers who play,
particularly recreationally,
play with a cart.
-- Like Michael.
And on several of the tours
you can play with a cart;
on the Senior PGA Tour,
on the Nike Tour,
in a lot of the college events.
And those events
are just as competitive
and just as high level
as the PGA Tour.
So, really it's just a matter
of selective reasoning
if you argue it as an
important part of the sport.
But, even if it is he
still does have to walk,
he still plays golf standing up,
it's not as if he's playing golf
from a wheelchair.
Alright.
Who else?
Go ahead.
I think the whole point
of a competition
is that it calls out the best, you know,
from the second best or from the third best.
And when we're talking
about the national level,
we're talking about the
highest of the highest.
I think what they're arguing about here
is the purpose of competition.
And I think in the sake of competition
you can't change the rules.
So, the purpose of the
competition includes walking?
That's an essential,
you agree with Tom.
And what's your name?
David.
The Supreme Court
ruled
that the PGA did have to
accommodate Casey Martin
and they did it on grounds
that Riva mentioned,
that walking isn't really part of,
an essential part of the game.
They cited testimony saying
that walking the court
consumes no more calories
than you get eating a Big Mac.
That's what walking is in golf,
according to the majority.
Scalia was in dissent.
Justice Scalia agreed with David.
He said
there is no purpose,
and it's certainly not your course to try to
figure out the essential purpose of golf.
Golf is like any game,
it's strictly for amusement.
And if there's a group that wants
to have one version of the game
they can have that
version of the game.
And the market can decide
whether people are amused
and like and show up for that
and watch the television broadcasts.
Scalia's dissent was an
anti-Aristotelian dissent,
because notice two things
about the argument;
first we're thrust into a discussion
about what the essential nature,
or purpose,
or telos of golf really is.
Does it include walking?
And, here's something I think is rumbling
beneath the surface of this debate,
whether walking partly determines whether
golf is really an athletic competition.
After all, the ball sits still.
You have to put it in a hole.
Is it more like basketball,
baseball, and football?
Golf, an athletic competition?
Or is it more like billiards?
The ball sits still
there too.
You can be out of shape
and succeed.
It involves skill
but not athletic skill.
Could it be that those
professional golfers,
who excel at golf,
have a stake in golf being honored
and recognized as an athletic event,
not just a game of skill like billiards?
And if that's what's at stake,
then we have a debate about the purpose,
the teleological dimension,
and also a debate about honor.
What virtues,
really,
does the game of golf
honor and recognize?
Two questions to which
Aristotle directs our attention.
We'll continue
on this case next time.
What's strange
and seems paradoxical to me
about Aristotle's view point
is that if you walk like a pirate
and you talk like a pirate
you shouldn't be
an investment banker,
because that's not what
you're inherently supposed to do.
If you have a peg leg
and an eye patch
and a disgruntled disposition,
you know,
you should be on a pirate ship
on the high seas.
So he doesn't . . .
Some would say
that the distinction
between the two vocations
is not as clear as you suggest.
When we ended last time
we were talking about
whether Casey Martin
has a right to ride in a golf cart
in the PGA Tournament.
And it's worth remembering
how we got into this debate
and what's at stake for an
understanding of political philosophy.
Remember, we were looking
at Aristotle's theory of justice
and one way of describing
his approach to justice,
we've called it 'teleological'.
Teleological, because he says
to allocate rights
we first have to figure out
the purpose, or the end,
of the social practice in question.
Another way of describing
Aristotle's account of Justice
is that justice is,
for him, a matter of fit;
it's a matter of fitting persons
with their virtues and excellences
to the appropriate roles.
Now, I want to finish our discussion
about Casey Martin
and his claim for a golf cart,
and then go back to one more
consequential application in Aristotle,
namely, the question of slavery.
What do you think about
Casey Martin's request?
Should there be an
accommodation or not,
given the nature of the game
and of the tournament
and its purposes?
"Isn't it discrimination if he's not provided
the golf cart as an accommodation",
say some.
Others reply, "No, if he got a cart
it would be unfair to the other golfers
because they exert themselves,
become winded, fatigued,
walking the course".
That's where we left it.
What about the fairness argument?
OK, Jenny.
My question was
why doesn't the PGA
just make the option of a cart
available to all golfers?
From our readings I learned that
there are many golf tournaments,
other than the PGA,
where using a cart is not prohibited.
For instance, the Seniors Tournament
it's even allowed and encouraged.
So why doesn't the PGA just do that?
Let everybody use
a cart?
Give everyone
the option of using a cart
and let them pick.
So then the traditionalists
can then still say,
"Well, I still choose
to walk the course
but I do that knowing that I
will be more tired at the end
than the people
who took the cart."
Good.
Alright, so what about Jenny's solution?
For the sake of fairness,
don't give Casey Martin
an advantage,
if indeed there is an
advantage to riding in a cart.
Let everyone who wants to
use a cart.
Is everyone happy
with that solution?
Does it put to rest
this whole dilemma?
Who has an answer for Jenny?
Yes.
As was brought up last time,
if you do that you kind of
ruin some of the spirit of golf
as a lot of people like to see it.
If you let everybody take a cart.
Even though it gives everybody
the same playing field now,
it sort of makes golf less
of an athletic game,
like people pointed out last class.
It's just like if someone decides
to go into another sport
and they want an advantage.
Like, if you have swimming
and then you say,
"OK, he wants flippers
so why don't we just allow everyone
to have flippers when they're swimming?"
And what would that do to the
Olympic Swimming Competition,
if people were free to use,
Jenny, we better
let Jenny reply to this.
Da says it would sort of spoil
the spirit of the athletic competition
as if in Olympic swimming
you let anyone who wanted to
swim with flippers.
Alright, Jenny,
what do you say to Da?
It would spoil the spirit of it.
You're also ruining
the spirit of golf
by not letting people who are
really passionate about the game,
and very good at it,
compete simply because
of an aspect of golf which is not,
the main point of golf is you
use the club to make strokes
and hit it into a hole.
I'm sorry, I'm not a golfer
but that's basically the gist
of the game from what I see it.
And I was reading the
PGA versus Casey Martin decision
that was one of the
sentences that they said
is because walking the course
is not an inherent part of golf,
only swinging the club is.
Good. So, Jenny replies
to Da,
well, it isn't really essential
anyhow to walk the course.
So, we're back to the purpose.
I mean, I'm sure there are,
like wheelchair basketball,
there are certain
different competitions
that can be made for people
who may only be able to use their arms.
Right. Yes.
Michael what do you think?
Jenny just said that there is
stuff like wheelchair basketball
where if you can't play basketball
there is another option.
I think there are other options
in the PGA Tour.
But the PGA Tour is the best,
is the pinnacle,
and you have to have certain
requirements fulfilled to perform.
Alright, Michael, you want
to say to Casey Martin
there is such a thing
as a Special Olympics
for those who are disabled.
Go play in the golfing version
of the Special Olympics.
That's what you would say Michael?
-- Yeah.
I think that walking is part
of the sport of golf.
And Casey Martin, you know
if he can't walk the course
then I don't think he should
be able to play in the PGA.
Alright, well thank you very much
for that exchange.
What comes out
of this exchange
that goes back to Aristotle's
theory of justice?
Well, one thing is the question,
is walking an essential part of golf?
And the very fact that deciding
whether there is a right
for Casey Martin
that the PGA must respect,
seems to depend,
as Aristotle suggests it must,
on debating and
resolving the question,
is walking essential
to the game of golf?
That's one moral of the story.
But there's a second moral
to the story
from an Aristotelian point of view.
What's at stake here,
this is the second Aristotelian
stake in this debate,
is honor.
Casey Martin wants the accommodation
so that he can compete
for the honor
of winning the best tournaments.
Now, why is it
that the professional golfers,
the great golfers,
testified in this case -
Jack Nicklaus, Tom Kite -
in the readings,
against letting him use a cart
and they, I would suspect,
would be equally vehement, Jenny,
in opposing your suggestion
of letting everyone ride in a cart,
and this goes back, in a way,
to Da's point.
How to put this gently?
Professional golfers are sensitive
about whether their
sport is really a sport.
Because if everyone rode
around in a cart, or could,
then it would become clear,
or clearer, depending
on your point of view,
that golf is not really
an athletic competition
but rather a game;
a game of skill
but not a sport.
And so not only the question
of debating the purpose,
the teleological feature,
but also from the standpoint of viewing
debates about the purpose of golf.
What's essential to golf?
Those debates,
Aristotle suggests,
inevitably are also debates
about the allocation of honor.
Because part of
the purpose of golf
is not just to
amuse spectators;
Scalia's wrong about that,
from Aristotle's point of view.
It's not just to
provide entertainment,
it's not just to make people happy.
It's not a mere amusement.
It's honoring,
it's rewarding,
it's recognizing a certain
kind of athletic excellence,
at least those who have
achieved the highest honors
have a powerful stake
in maintaining that view.
Now, some of you took
the position the Scalia position.
"This is an incredibly difficult
and silly question", Scalia said.
"What is the essential nature of golf?"
It's not the kind of thing that
the United States Supreme Court
is equipped to decide,
or should decide.
That's Scalia.
But he only he says that
because he takes a very strong,
and as it happens,
anti-Aristotelian position
on what a game is.
"It is the very nature of a game
to have no object,"
no point,
"except amusement"
says Scalia,
"That is what distinguishes games"
he says, "From productive activity."
You can just imagine what kind
of sports fan Scalia must be.
"And so", he says, "It's impossible to say
that any of the game's arbitrary rules
is essential."
And then he quotes Mark Twain's
disparaging remark
about golf.
He says, "Many consider walking
to be the central feature of golf.
Hence, Mark Twain's
classic criticism of the sport
'a good walk spoiled'."
But Scalia misses
an important feature of games
and the arguments
about rights and fairness
that arise from games,
when he casts games,
sports, athletic competitions,
as solely for the
sake of amusement;
as solely an utilitarian activity.
But an Aristotelian
view of sports says,
no it's not just about amusement,
real sports,
real athletic events,
are also about appreciation,
not just amusement.
And people who follow sports
and care about sports
and play sports
know this.
Which is another way of saying,
there's a difference between
a sport and a mere spectacle.
And the difference is
that a sport is a practice
that calls forth
and honors and prizes
certain excellences,
certain virtues.
And the people who
appreciate those virtues
are the true fans,
the informed fans,
and for them watching the sport
is not mere amusement.
But that means that it's always
possible to make sense
of the debate about
what feature of a sport
is essential to it.
We can make sense
of these arguments.
Never mind the question whether
the court should decide.
The PGA in its own
internal deliberations
can make sense
of that debate,
which is why they
cared very much
about their view,
insisting on their view,
that walking,
an exertion, and fatigue
are essential, not peripheral,
parts of sport.
Well, this is all to illustrate
the teleological and
the honorific feature
of debates about rights,
which Aristotle says
we need to take account of
in thinking about justice.
Now, I want to begin
for us to consider
whether Aristotle's theory of justice
is right or wrong;
whether it's persuasive
or unpersuasive.
I want to get your
thoughts about that.
But I want to anticipate one obvious
and important objection.
If justice is about fit,
fitting persons to roles,
matching virtues
to the appropriate honors
and recognition.
If that's what justice is,
does it leave room for freedom?
And this is one of the
main objections
to Aristotle's teleological
account of justice.
If certain roles,
social roles,
are fitting,
or appropriate, to me
where does that leave my right
to choose my social roles,
my life purposes,
for myself?
What room does teleology
leave for freedom?
And in fact,
you may remember,
Rawls rejects teleological
accounts of justice
because he says that
teleological theories of justice
threaten
the equal basic rights of citizens.
So, let's begin to examine
whether Aristotle is right,
and in particular,
whether his teleological way
of thinking about justice
is at odds with freedom.
Now, one obvious reason to worry
is Aristotle's defense of slavery.
He defends slavery,
which existed as an institution
in the Athens of his day.
Well, what is his defense of slavery?
Two things, two conditions,
have to be met
for slavery to be just.
First, it has to be necessary.
and Aristotle says,
at least in our society,
slavery is necessary.
Why is it necessary?
If there are to be citizens
who are freed from manual
and menial and household chores
to go to the assembly,
to deliberate about politics,
there have to be some who
look after those menial tasks;
the mere necessities of life.
He says, unless you could invent
in some science-fiction
a technological fix
then there are going to be
those who have to do
the hard and difficult
and menial labor
if there are going to be citizens
deliberating about the good
and realizing their nature.
So slavery is necessary
for the life of the polis
for there to be open to citizens.
The life of deliberation,
of argument,
of practical wisdom.
But there's a further condition
that has to be met.
Slavery has not only to be necessary
for the community as a whole to function,
but it also has to be the case,
remember the criterion of fit?
It also has to be the case
that there are some people
for whom being a slave
is the just, or the fitting,
or the appropriate condition.
Now, Aristotle agrees
that by his own standards,
both of those conditions
must be met, must be true,
if slavery is to be just.
And then,
in a deplorable passage,
he says, well, it is true
that there are some people
who are fit by nature
who are cut out to be slaves.
These are people who differ
from ordinary people
in the same way that the
body differs from the soul.
These are people who
are meant to be ruled,
and for them
their nature is best realized
if they're slaves.
They can recognize reason in others
but they can't partake of it,
they can't exercise it.
And somehow we can know this.
Now, Aristotle must have known
that there was something dodgy,
something strained
about this claim,
because he quickly acknowledges
that those who disagree may have a point.
And what those who
disagree point out is
that there are a lot
of people in Athens
who are slaves
not because they
were born to be slaves,
or fit to be slaves,
but because they were captured,
they were losers in a war.
And so, Aristotle admits that
as practiced in ancient Athens,
slavery didn't necessarily line up
with who actually is fit
or born to be a slave,
because some actual slaves
just were slaves by bad luck,
by being captured in a war.
And on Aristotle's own account
even if it's necessary to have slavery
for the sake of citizenship
it's unjust if people
who aren't properly slaves
are cast in that role.
There is a misfit.
Aristotle recognizes that slavery
for those who aren't fit for the task
is a kind of coercion.
The reason slavery is wrong
is not because it's coerced.
Coercion is an indicator
that it's wrong,
because it's not natural.
If you have to coerce
someone into a role
that's a pretty good indication
that they don't belong there,
that that role isn't fitting for them.
And Aristotle recognized this.
So, all of this is to say
the example of slavery,
Aristotle's defense of it,
doesn't show that there isn't
anything wrong in principle
with teleological argument,
with the idea of justice as fit
between persons and roles,
because it's perfectly possible
within Aristotle's own terms,
to explain what's wrong
with this application,
this practical application
that he made of his theory.
I want to turn to the larger challenge
to Aristotle in the name of freedom.
But before I do that
I want to see what people think
of Aristotle's account
of justice as fit,
his teleological way of
reasoning about justice
and the honorific
dimension of rights
and of distributive justice
that immerged in our discussion
of flutes and politics and golf.
Questions of clarification
about Aristotle
or objections to his overall account.
Yes.
My objection to Aristotle
is that he wants to match
a person to a role.
And, you know, if you walk like
a pirate and you talk like a pirate,
you know, you should be a pirate.
And that is what is right.
And so what's strange
and seems paradoxical to me
about Aristotle's view point
is that if you walk like a pirate
and you talk like a pirate
you shouldn't be
an investment banker,
because that's not what you're
inherently supposed to do.
If you have a peg leg
and an eye patch
and a disgruntled disposition,
you know,
you should be on a pirate ship
on the high seas.
So he doesn't...
Some would say
that the distinction
between the two vocations
is not as clear as you suggest.
Alright, but that's
good.
I take your point.
Yes, go ahead.
It just seems to ignore
individual rights.
So, I might be the perfect
janitor in the whole world
and I can do that job
the most efficiently
out of anybody
that exists right now,
but I might not
want to do that.
I might want to do any
other number of pursuits
and it seems to say that
that isn't really a good option for me.
Alright,
and what's your name?
-- Mary-Kate.
-- Good.
Alright, let's take a couple more.
Yes.
I think that the
golf cart exchange
sort of brought up what
I see as my main objection
to this teleological
mode of reasoning.
I mean, Michael,
I think that's your name, right?
Believes that walking is
an inherent part of golf.
Myself, I believe that walking
is not an inherent part of golf.
And I feel that
no matter how long
we debate this particular
point of contention
we're never going
to reach an accord.
The teleological framework of reasoning,
I believe,
doesn't really allow us to come
to any sort of agreement.
Alright,
and what's your name?
-- Patrick.
Alright, let me try to address
this set of objections to Aristotle.
Let me start with Patrick's;
it's an important objection.
We had a debate about whether
walking is essential to golf,
and even in so seemingly trivial,
or at least contained, a case as that,
we couldn't agree.
How can we possibly
hope to agree?
When the stakes are higher
and when we're debating the
fundamental purposes, or ends,
of political community.
And so, if we can't agree
in what the ends or the goods
of our shared public life consist in,
how can we base
justice and rights
on some notion
of what the end,
or the purpose,
or the good consists in?
That's an important objection.
So much so that much modern
political theory takes that worry
about disagreement over the good
as its starting point,
and concludes that justice
and rights and constitutions
should not be based on any
particular conception of the good
or the purposes of political life,
but should, instead,
provide a framework of rights
that leaves people free to choose
their conceptions of the good,
their own conceptions
of the purposes of life.
Now, Mary-Kate said, "What if a person is
very well suited to having a certain role,
like the role of being a janitor,
but wants something else,
wants to reach higher,
wants to choose another way of life?"
So, that goes back to
this question about freedom.
If we take our bearing as persons
from roles that are
said to fit our nature,
shouldn't it at least be up to us
to decide what those roles are?
In fact, shouldn't it be up to us to
define what roles are suitable to us?
And that's going to take us back
to the confrontation between
Aristotle on the one hand
and Kant and Rawls on the other.
Kant and Rawls think
Patrick has a point.
They say precisely
because people disagree
in pluralist societies
about the nature
of the good life,
we shouldn't try to base justice on
any particular answer to that question.
So they reject teleology,
they reject the idea of tying justice
to some conception of the good.
What's at stake in the
debate about teleology,
say Rawlsian and Kantian liberals,
is this;
if you tie justice to a particular
conception of the good,
if you see justice as a matter of fit
between a person and his or her roles,
you don't leave room for freedom,
and to be free is to
be independent of
any particular roles,
or traditions,
or conventions that may be
handed down by my parents
or my society.
So, in order to decide as between
these two broad traditions,
whether Aristotle is right,
or whether Kant and Rawls are right,
we need to investigate whether
the right is prior to the good,
question one,
and we need to investigate what
it means to be a free person,
a free moral agent.
Does freedom require that
I stand for toward my roles,
my ends, and my purposes
as an agent of choice?
Or as someone trying to discover
what my nature really is?
Two big questions
and we'll take them up next time.