Today we turn to Kant's
reply to Aristotle.
Kant thinks that Aristotle
just made a mistake.
It's one thing,
Kant says,
to support a fair
framework of rights
within which people
can pursue their own
conceptions of the good life.
It's something else and something
that runs the risk of coercion
to base law or
principles of justice
on any particular conception
of the good life.
You remember Aristotle says in order
to investigate the ideal constitution
we have first to figure out
the best way to live.
Kant would reject that idea.
He says that constitutions
and laws and rights
rights should not embody
or affirm or promote
any particular way of life.
That's at odds with freedom.
For Aristotle the
whole point of law,
the purpose of polis
is to shape character,
to cultivate the
virtue of citizens,
to inculcate civic excellence,
to make possible a good way of life.
That's what he tells
us in the politics.
For Kant, on the other hand,
the purpose of law, the
point of a constitution
is not to inculcate or
to promote virtue.
It's to set up a fair framework
of rights within which
citizens may be free to pursue their own
conceptions of the good for themselves.
So we see the difference
in their theories of justice.
We see the difference
in their account of
law or the role of a constitution,
the point of politics,
and underlying these
differences are
two different accounts of what
it means to be a free person.
For Aristotle we are free
insofar as we have
the capacity to realize
our potential.
And that leads us to
the question of fit.
Fit between persons and the roles
that are appropriate to them.
Figuring out what I'm cut out for.
That's what it means to lead a free life,
to live up to my potential.
Kant rejects that
idea and instead
substitutes his famously
demanding notion of
freedom as the capacity
to act autonomously.
Freedom means acting according
to a law I give myself.
Freedom is autonomy.
Part of the appeal,
part of the moral force
of the view of Kant
and of Rawls consists in
the conception of the person as
a free and independent self
capable of choosing
his or her own ends.
The image of the self is
free and independent
offers a, if you think about it,
a powerful liberating vision
because what it says is
that as free moral persons
we are not bound by
any ties of history
or of tradition or
of inherited status
that we haven't chosen
for ourselves,
and so we're unbound by any moral
ties prior to our choosing them.
And that means
that we are
free and independent
sovereign selves.
We're the authors of the only
obligations that constrain us.
The communitarian critics of
Kantian and Rawlsian liberalism
acknowledge that there
is something powerful
and inspiring in that
account of freedom,
the free independent
choosing self,
but they argue it
misses something.
It misses a whole dimension of
moral life and even political life.
It can't make sense of our moral
experience because it can't account
for certain moral and
political obligations
that we commonly recognize
and even prize.
And these include obligations
of membership, loyalty,
solidarity, and other moral ties
that may claim us for reasons
that we can't trace to
an act of consent.
Alistair McIntyre
gives an account what he calls a
narrative conception of the self.
It's a different account
of the self.
Human beings are essentially
storytelling creatures, McIntyre argues.
That means I can only
answer the question
'what am I to do?' if I can
answer the prior question
of what story or stories
do I find myself a part?
That's what he means by the
narrative conception of the self.
What does this have to do with the
idea of community and belonging?
McIntyre says this,
Once you accept this narrative
aspect of moral reflection
you will notice that we can
never seek for the good
or exercise of the virtues
only as individuals.
We all approach our circumstance as
bearers of particular social identities.
I am someone's son
or daughter,
a citizen of this or that city,
I belonged to this plan,
that tribe, this nation.
Hence, McIntyre argues,
what is good for me
has to be the good for someone
who inhabits these roles.
I inherit from the past of my family,
my city, my tribe, my nation
a variety of debts, inheritances,
expectations, and obligations.
These constitute the given of my
life, my moral starting point.
This is in part what gives my
life its moral particularity.
That's the narrative
conception of the self.
And it's a conception
that sees the self as
claimed or encumbered,
at least to some extent,
by the history,
the tradition,
the communities,
of which it's a part.
We can't make sense
of our lives,
not only as a psychological matter,
but also as a moral matter
in thinking what we are to do
without attending to
these features about us.
Now, McIntyre recognizes
that this narrative account,
this picture of the
encumbered self,
puts his account at odds with
contemporary liberalism and individualism.
From the standpoint
of individualism
I am what I myself
choose to be.
I may biologically
be my father's son
but I can't be held responsible
for what he did
unless I choose to assume
such responsibility.
I can't be held responsible for what
my country does, or has done,
unless I choose to assume
such responsibility.
But McIntyre says this reflects a
certain kind of moral shallowness
even blindness.
It's a blindness at odds with the full
measure of responsibility which sometimes,
he says, involves collective responsibility
or responsibilities that may flow
from historic memories.
And he gives some examples.
Such individualism is expressed by
those contemporary Americans
who deny any responsibility for the effects
of slavery upon black Americans saying
"I never owned any slaves."
Or the young German
who believes
that having been born
after 1945 means
that what Nazis did to Jews
has no moral relevance
to his relationship to his
Jewish contemporaries.
McIntyre says all of these
attitudes of historical amnesia
amount to a kind of
moral abdication.
Once you see that
who we are
and what it means to sort
out our obligations
can't be separated,
shouldn't be separated
from the life histories
that define us.
The contrast, he says, with
a narrative account, is clear,
For the story of my life is always
embedded in the story
of those communities from
which I derived my identity.
I am born with the past and to try
to cut myself off from that past
is to deform my present
relationships.
So there you have in McIntyre,
a strong statement of the idea
that the self can't be detached,
shouldn't be detached,
from its particular ties
of membership history,
story narrative.
Now, I want to get
your reactions
to the communitarian critique
of the individualist
or the voluntarist,
the unencumbered self.
But let's make it concrete
so that you can react
to more than just the
theory of it by looking at
the two different accounts of moral
and political obligation that arise
depending on which of these conceptions
of the person one accepts.
On the liberal conception,
moral and political obligations
arise in one of two ways.
There are natural duties that we
owe human beings as such.
duties of respect for
persons qua persons.
These obligations are universal.
Then, as Rawls points out,
there are also voluntary
obligations.
Obligations that we owe
to particular others
insofar as we have agreed
whether through a promise
or a deal or a contract.
Now, the issue between the liberal and
communitarian accounts of the self,
is there another category
of obligation or not?
The communitarian says there is.
There is a third category
that might be called
obligations of solidarity or
loyalty or membership.
The communitarian argues that
construing all obligations
as either natural duties
or voluntary obligations
fails to capture obligations
of membership or solidarity.
Loyalties whose moral force
consists partly in the fact
that living by them
is inseparable from
understanding ourselves as
the particular persons we are.
What would be some examples?
And then I want to see how
you would react to them.
Examples of obligations
of membership
that are particular but don't
necessarily flow from consent
but rather from membership narrative
community, one situation.
The most common examples are
ones to do with the family.
The relation between parents
and children, for example.
Suppose there were two
children drowning.
You could save only
one of them.
One was your child, the other
was a stranger's child.
Would you have an
obligation to flip a coin
or would there be
something morally obtuse
if you didn't rush
to save your child?
Now, you may say, well,
parents have agreed
to have their children.
So take the other case,
the case of children's
obligation for their parents.
Now, we don't choose
our parents.
We don't even choose
to have parents.
There is that asymmetry.
And yet consider two aging
parents, one of them yours,
the other a stranger's.
Doesn't it make moral sense to think
that you have a greater obligation
to look after your aged parent than to
flip a coin or to help the stranger's?
Now, is this traceable to consent?
Not likely
Or take a couple of
political examples.
During World War II,
French resistance pilots
flew bombing raids over
occupied France.
One day, one of the pilots
received his target
and noticed that the village
he was being asked to bomb
was his home village.
He refused, not disputing that it was as
necessary as the target he bombed yesterday.
He refused on the ground that
he couldn't bring himself.
It would be a special moral crime
for him to bomb his people
even in a cause that he supported,
the cause of liberating France.
Now, do we admire that?
If we do, the communitarian argues,
it's because we do recognize
obligations of solidarity.
Take another example.
Some years ago there was
a famine in Ethiopia.
Hundreds of thousands
of people were starving.
The Israeli government organized an
airlift to rescue Ethiopian Jews.
They didn't have the capacity to
rescue everyone in Ethiopia.
They rescued several
hundred Ethiopian Jews.
Now, what's your moral
assessment?
Is that a kind of morally troubling
partiality, a kind of prejudice?
Or as the Israeli government thought,
is there a special obligation of solidarity
that this airlift properly
responded to?
Well, that takes us to the
broader question of patriotism.
What, morally speaking, is
to be said for patriotism?
There are two towns
named Franklin.
One is Franklin, Texas,
and the other is just across the
Rio Grande River, Franklin, Mexico.
What is the moral significance
of national boundaries?
Why is it, or is it the case
that we as Americans have
a greater responsibility
for the health and the education
and the welfare and public provision
for people who live
in Franklin, Texas,
than equally needy people
just across the river,
living in Franklin, Mexico?
According to the communitarian
account, membership does matter.
And the reason patriotism is
at least potentially a virtue
is that it is an expression of
the obligations of citizenship.
How many are sympathetic to the idea that
there is this third category of obligation?
The obligations of solidarity
or membership.
How many are sympathetic
to that idea?
And how many are
critical of that idea?
How many think all obligations
can be accounted for
in the first two ways?
All right, let's hear from the critics
of the communitarian idea first.
Yes.
My biggest concern with the
idea of having obligations
because you're a member of
something or because of solidarity
is that it seems that if you accept
those obligations as being
sort of morally binding, then there is a
greater occurrence of overlapping obligations
a greater occurrence
of good versus good.
And I don't know if
this sort of framework
allows us to choose
between them.
Good, and what's your name?
- Patrick.
So you worry that if we recognize
obligations of membership or solidarity,
since we inhabit different communities,
their claims might conflict,
and what would we do if we
have competing obligations?
Yes.
Well, one solution is that we
could view ourselves as
ultimately, members of
the human community
and that then within that we have
all these smaller spheres, of that,
you know, I am American or
I am a student at Harvard.
and so the most important
community to be obligated to
is the community
of human beings.
And then from there you
can sort of, evaluate,
which other ones are
most important to you.
So the most, and what's your name?
- Nichola.
So, Nichola, you say the
most universal community
we inhabit, the community
of human kind,
always takes precedence?
- Yes.
Patrick, are you satisfied?
No.
- Why not?
It seems rather arbitrary that
we should choose the
universal obligation over the
more specific obligation.
I might also say that I should be obligated
first to the most specific of my obligations.
For instance, take my family
as a small unit of solidarity.
Perhaps I should be first
obligated to that unit
and then perhaps to
the unit of my town,
and then my country, and
then the human race.
Good, thank you.
I want to hear from another critic
of the communitarian view.
We have the objection, well,
what if goods collide?
Who objects to the
whole idea of it?
Who sees patriotism as just
the kind of prejudice
that ideally we should overcome?
Yes.
Patriotism reflects a
community membership.
That's a, like, a given.
I think the problem is that where some
memberships are natural narratives,
the narrative of citizenship
is a constructed one.
And I think a false one because, as
the river is just a historical accident,
it makes no sense that because
the lottery of birth threw me into
the United States as
opposed to Mexico that
that's the membership that
I should be a part of.
Good. And what's your name?
- Elizabeth.
Elizabeth.
Who has a reply?
Yes.
I think in general, we have to ask where
do our moral obligations arise from anyway.
And I think, basically, there'd be two
places from which they could arise.
One would be kin and the other
one would be reciprocity.
And isn't the closer you are
associated to other people,
there's a natural reciprocity
there in terms of
having interactions
with those people.
You interact with the
neighbors on your street,
with the other people in your country
through economic arrangements-
But I don't know and you don't know
those people in Franklin, Texas,
any more than you know the people
in Franklin, Mexico, do you?
Presumably you're naturally more
connected with the people
in your own country in terms
of interaction and trade
than you are with people
in other countries.
Good. Who else?
Go ahead.
Yeah, I think that a lot of
the basis for patriotism
can be compared to like school spirit
or even house spirit that we see here
where freshmen are sorted into houses
and then within a day they have developed
some sort of attachment or a
pride associated with that house.
And so I think that we can
probably draw a distinction between
a moral obligation for
communitarian beliefs
and sort of just a sentimental,
emotional attachment.
Good. Wait, stay there.
What's your name?
Rina.
What about... Go back to my
example about the obligation
of the child to the parent.
Would you say the
same thing there?
It just may or may not be a sentimental
type and it has no moral weight?
Well, I mean, I'm not entirely certain
that accident, in the initial stages,
something that will preclude
moral obligations later.
Just because we are randomly
sorted into a house or just because
we don't choose who our parents
are or what country we're born into
doesn't necessarily mean that we won't
develop an obligation based on
some type of benefit,
I guess, to sort of...
So your obligation to
your aged parent
that's greater than to aged
parents around the world,
is only because and insofar
as you're repaying a benefit
that your parent gave you
when you were growing up?
Yeah, I mean, I would say that if
you look at cases of adoption where,
you have a biological parent somewhere
else that you don't interact with,
and then you have a parent
who adopted you,
most people would say that if
you had to pick between them
in the case of aging parents,
that your obligation would lie
more with the person who raised you and
who had exchanges with you meaningfully.
May I ask you one more
question about the parent?
Sure.
Do you think that a person with
a bad parent owes them less?
I don't know because I've
never had a bad parent.
I think that's a good place to end.
- Thank you.
We'll continue with this
next time. Thank you.
If I were working on an [economics]
problem set, for example,
and I saw that my
roommate was cheating,
that might be a bad thing for him
to do but I wouldn't turn him in.
You would not turn him in.
I wouldn't turn him in and I think that
I would argue that's the right thing to do
because of my obligation to him.
You don't have a duty
to tell the truth,
to report someone
who cheated?
Today I'd like to take,
I'd like to consider
the strongest objections
to the idea that there are
obligations of solidarity
or membership.
Then I want to see if those objections
can be met successfully.
One objection emerged in
the discussion last time.
Patrick said,
if obligations flow from community
membership and identity,
we inhabit multiple
communities,
doesn't that mean that our
obligations will sometimes conflict?
So that's one possible objection.
And then Rina said these examples
meant to bring out the moral force
of solidarity and membership,
examples about parents and children,
about the French resistant fighter
asked to bomb his own village
and withdrawing back.
About the airlift by Israel
of the Ethiopian Jews.
These examples, they maybe
intuitively evocative, Rina said.
But really they're pointing to matters
of emotion, matters of sentiment.
Not true moral obligations.
And then there were a
number of objections,
not necessarily to
patriotism as such.
But to patriotism understood as an
obligation of solidarity and membership
beyond consent.
This objection allowed that there can be
obligations to the communities we inhabit
including obligations
to patriotism.
But this objection argued that all
of the obligations of patriotism,
or of community
or membership,
are actually based on liberal ideas
and perfectly compatible with them.
Consent, either implicit
or explicit or reciprocity.
Julia Ratthel for example
on the web site
said that liberalism can endorse patriotism
as a voluntary moral obligation.
Patriotism and familial love
both fall into this category
because after all,
Julia points out,
the Kantian framework allows people
free reign to choose to express
virtues such as these
if they want to.
So you don't need the idea of a
non-voluntary particular moral obligation
to capture the moral force
of community values.
Where is Julia?
Okay, so did I summarize
that fairly?
Julia actually is in line with what
Rawls says about this very topic.
You weren't aware of that?
You came up it within your own.
That's pretty good.
Rawls says, when he's discussing
political obligation,
he says it's one thing if
someone runs for office
or enlists in the military,
they are making a
voluntary choice.
But Rawls says there is, I believe, no
political obligations, strictly speaking,
for a citizens generally.
Because it's not clear what is
the requisite binding action
and who has performed it.
So Rawls acknowledges
that for ordinary citizens
there is no political obligation
except in so far as
some particular citizen willingly,
through an act of consent,
undertakes or chooses
such an obligation.
That's in line with Julia's point.
It's related to another objection
that people have raised which is
it's perfectly possible to recognize
particular obligations
to ones family or to
ones country, provided
honoring those obligations
doesn't require you
to violate any of the natural
duties or requirements
of the universal respect for
persons-qua-persons.
So that's consistent with the idea
that we can choose if we want to,
to express our loyalty to our country
or to our people or to our family
provided we don't
do any injustice
within the framework acknowledging the
priority that is of the universal duties.
The one objection that
I didn't mention is
the view of those who say
that obligations of membership really
are kind of collective selfishness,
why should we honor them?
Isn't it just the kind of prejudice?
So what I'd like to do,
perhaps of those of you
who have agreed, who wrote
and who have agreed
to press these objections,
perhaps if you could gather
down all together,
we'll form a team as
we did once before.
And we'll see if you can respond to
those who want to defend patriotism
conceived as a communal
obligation.
Now there were a
number of people
who argued in defense
of patriotism
as the communitarian
view conceives it.
So let me go down now
and join the critics,
the critics of communitarianism.
If there's a microphone that
we could use somewhere.
Okay, thanks Kate.
Who as the critics of patriotism,
communal patriotism
gather their forces here?
Patrick if you want to you
can join as well or Rina.
Others who have spoken or
addressed this question
are free to join in.
But I would like to hear
now, from those you who
defend patriotism
and defend it as
a moral obligation that can't
be translated back into
purely consent based terms.
Can't be translated
into the liberal terms.
Where is AJ Kumar?
AJ, everybody seems
to know you.
All right, let's hear from AJ.
You said, in the same way I feel I owe more
to my family than to the general community,
I owe more to my country
than to humanity in general.
Because my country holds a
great stake in my identity.
It is not prejudice for
me to love my country
unless it is prejudice for
me to love my parents
more than somebody else's.
So AJ what would you
say to this group?
Stand up.
I think that there is some
fundamental, a moral obligation
that comes from a
communitarian responsibility
to people in groups that
form their identity.
I mean even, like I'll give
the example that,
there are a lot of things about
our government, right now,
that I'm not in favor of
but part of my identity is
that America values a free
society where we can
object to certain things
and I think that's an
expression of patriotism as well.
And, I go back to the parent
example, even at Harvard,
I think, I owe more to my roommates
because they make up my identity,
than I do it to the Harvard
community as a whole.
And I think that applies to our country
because there's certain things
that growing up here,
yes, we can't choose it,
we can't choose our
parents, things like that.
But it makes up part
of our identity.
Okay, who would like
to take that on? Mike?
Yeah about the obligation to the others
simply by virtue of being in their,
being influenced by them.
I'm a German citizen and if
I've been born 80 years earlier
then I would have been a
citizen of Nazi Germany.
And for some reason I just don't think
that I would have to feel obligated
towards Germany because I had
benefited from actions of Nazis.
I mean I guess my response
to that would be
you have hundreds of thousands of
protesters in the United States right now
who hold up signs that
say, "Peace is patriotic."
And I'm sure there are people in this
room who don't agree with that.
I personally do and
I would say that
they are strongly objecting to basically
everything the Bush administration is
doing right now but they
still consider themselves
loving their country because
they're furthering the cause of
what they see is best
for the country.
And I tend to agree with that
as a patriotic movement.
Well but how's that then, how
do you still favor your country?
How's that still patriotic?
I mean isn't that more
sentimental attachment?
Where is the obligation there?
Rina?
Yeah not to bring this
back to John Locke, but
I would like to bring this
back to John Locke.
So, I mean in his conception
of, when people join society,
there's still some outlet.
If you're not satisfied
with your society,
you do have a means
of exit even though
we had a lot of concerns
about how you're born
and it's not very feasible,
he still provides that option.
If we want to say that your
obligation to society is a moral one,
that means that prior to knowing exactly
what that society is going to be like
or what your position is
going to be in that society,
that means that you have a binding
obligation to a complete unknown body
that could be, completely foreign
to all of your personal beliefs
Or what you would
hold to be correct.
Do you think that that kind of
communal obligation or patriotism
means writing the community
a blank moral check?
Basically, yeah.
I think it's reasonable to say that
as you grow and as you develop
within the community that you acquire
some type of obligation based on reciprocity
but to say that you have a moral obligation
I think requires a stronger justification.
Who else?
Anyone else who would
like to address that?
I guess we could say you could argue
that you are morally obliged to society
by the fact that there
is that reciprocity.
I think it's the idea that, you know, we
participate in society, we pay our taxes,
we vote, this is why we could say
that we owe something to society.
But beyond that I don't think
there's anything inherent in the fact
that we are members of the society
itself that we owe at anything.
I think it's in so far as we, as
the society give us something,
gives us protection,
safety, security,
then we owe the society something but
nothing beyond what we give the society.
Who want to take that on?
Raul?
I don't think we give the community
a blank moral check in that sense.
I think we only give it a blank moral
check when we abdicate our sense of
civic responsibility and
when we say that
the debate does matter
because patriotism is a vice.
I think that patriotism is important
because it gives us a sense of community,
a sense of common civic virtue
that we can engage in the issues.
Even if you don't agree with the
way the government is acting,
you can still love your country
and hate the way it's acting.
And I think because out
of that love of county,
you can debate with other people
and have respect for their views
but still engage
them in debate.
If you just say that, patriotism is a
vice, you drop out of that debate
and you cede the ground to people
who are more fundamentalist,
who have a stronger view and
who may coerce the community.
Instead we should engage the
other members of the community
on that same moral ground.
Now this, what we hear from AJ and Raul
that's very pluralistic argumentative
critically minded patriotism.
Whereas what we hear from, Ike
and the critics of patriotism here
is the worry that to take patriotic
obligation in a communal way, seriously,
involves the kind of loyalty that doesn't
let us just pick and choose among the beliefs
or actions or practices
of our country.
what's left of loyalty if
we're all talking about,
AJ and Raul,
if all we're talking about is
loyalty to principles of justice
that may happen to be
embodied in our community
or not as the case may be.
And if not then we
can reject its course.
I don't know, I sort
of given a reply.
I got carried away. I'm sorry.
Who would like...?
Go ahead Julia.
Yeah I think that patriotism you
need to define what that is.
It sounds like, you would normally think
that we are given a more weak definition
here of patriotism amongst
us but almost sounds like
your definition is merely to have some
sort civic involvement in debating
within your society.
and I think that that kind of undermines
maybe some of the moral worth of patriotism
as a virtue as well.
I think if you can consent to a stronger
form of patriotism if you want
that's a stronger, I guess, moral obligation
than even what you're suggesting.
What we really need to sharpen the
issue is an example from the defenders
of communitarianism of a case where
loyalty can actually compete with
and possibly outway universal
principles of justice.
That's the test they really
need to meet isn't it?
All right. So that's the
test you need to meet.
Or, any among you who would like to defend
obligations of membership or solidarity
independent of ones that happened
to embody just principles.
Who has an example
of a kind of loyalty
that can and should
compete with
universal moral claim
respect for persons?
Go ahead.
Yeah, if I were working on an
[economics] problem set, for example
and I saw that my roommate was cheating,
that might be a bad thing for him to do
I wouldn't turn him in.
- You would not turn him in?
I wouldn't turn him in and I think that
I would argue that's the right thing to do
because of my obligation to him.
It may be wrong but
that's what I would do
and, I think that's what most
people would do as well.
All right, that's...
Now there's a fair test.
He's not slipping out by saying he's
invoking, in the name of community,
some universal principles of justice.
What's your name?
Stay there.
It's Dan.
Dan. So what do people
think about Dan's case?
That's a harder case for the
ethic of loyalty, isn't it?
But a truer test.
How many agree with Dan?
So loyalty... Dan loyalty
has its part, if that's it.
How many disagree with Dan?
Peggy.
Oh well I agree with Dan but I agree
that it's a choice that we make
but it's not necessarily
right or wrong.
I'm agreeing that I'm going
to make the wrong choice
because I'm going to
choose my roommate.
But I also recognize that
that choice isn't morally right.
So you're still translating,
even Dan's loyalty,
you're saying well that's
a matter of choice,
but what's the right thing to do?
Most people put up
their hands saying
Dan would be right to stand by his
roommate and not turn him in.
Yes, go ahead.
Also I think as a roommate you
have insider information
and that might not be
something you want to use.
That might be something
unfair to hold against.
You're spending that much
time with the roommate,
obviously you're going to
learn things about him
and I don't think it's fair to reveal
that to a greater community.
But it's loyalty, Vojtech.
You agree with Dan that loyalty
is the ethic at stake here?
Absolutely.
You don't have a duty to tell the truth,
to report someone who cheated?
Not if you've been advantage into
getting that kind of information.
Before our critics of
patriotism leave,
I want to give you another version,
a more public example of what,
I guess we should call
it Dan's dilemma.
Dan's dilemma of loyalty and I want
to get the reaction of people to this.
This came up a few years
ago in Massachusetts.
Does anyone know
who this man is?
Billy Bulger that's right.
Who is Billy Bulger?
He was president of the Massachusetts
State Senate for many years.
One of the most powerful
politicians in Massachusetts
and then he became president of
the Univeristy of Massachusetts.
Now Billy Bulger, did you hear the story
about him that bears on Dan's dilemma?
Billy Bulger has a brother
named Whitey Bulger
and this is Whitey Bulger.
His brother Whitey is on the
FBI's most wanted list
alleged to be a notorious
gang leader in Boston,
responsible for many murders
and now a fugitive from justice.
But when the US attorney...
They called Billy Bulger,
then the president of the
Univeristy of Massachusetts,
before the grand jury
and wanted information
on the whereabouts of his
brother, this fugitive,
and he refused to give it.
US attorney said,
"Just to be clear Mr. Bulger,
you feel more loyalty to your
brother than to the people
of the commonwealth
of Massachusetts?"
And here's what
Billy Bulger said,
"I never thought
of it that way
but I do have a loyalty to my
brother, I care about him.
I hope that I'm never helpful
to anyone against him.
I don't have an obligation to
help anyone catch my brother."
Dan you would agree.
How many would agree with
the position of Billy Bulger?
Let me give one other example and
then we'll let the critics reply,
the critics of loyalty
as we'll describe it.
Here's an even more fateful example
from a figure in American history,
Robert E. Lee.
Now Robert E. Lee on the
eve of the civil war,
was an officer of
the Union Army.
He opposed secession, in fact,
regarded as treason.
When war loomed,
Lincoln offered Lee
to be the commanding
general of the Union Army,
and Lee refused.
And he described in a letter
to his sons why he refused.
With all my devotion to
the Union, he wrote,
I have not been able
to make up my mind
to raise my hand against my
relatives, my children, my home.
By which he meant Virginia.
If the union is dissolved I shall
return to my native state
and share the miseries
of my people.
Save in her defense, I will
draw my sword no more.
Now here's a
real test, Dan,
for your principle of loyalty.
Because here is the cause
of the war against,
not only to save the union
but against slavery.
And Lee is going to fight for Virginia
even though he doesn't share
the desire of the southern
states to secede.
Now the communitarian would say
there is something admirable in that.
Whether or not the decision
was ultimately right,
there's something admirable.
And the communitarian would say
we can't even make sense, Rina,
we can't make sense
of Lee's dilemma
as a moral dilemma
unless we acknowledge
that the claim of loyalty
arising from his sense of
narrative of who he is
is a moral, not just
sentimental, emotional tug.
All right, who would like to
respond to Dan's loyalty,
to Billy Bulger's loyalty or to
Robert E. Lee's loyalty to Virginia?
What do you say Julia?
Okay, well I think that these
are some classic examples
of multiple spheres of influence.
And that you have conflicting communities
that your family and your country.
I think that's one reason why the idea
of choice in your obligation is so important
because how else can
you resolve this?
If you're morally obligated and
there's no way out of this
need for loyalty to the
both communities,
you're trapped, there's
nothing you can do.
You have to make a choice.
And I think that being able to choose
based on other characteristics,
than merely the arbitrary fact that you're
a member of this community is important,
otherwise it's left to,
I guess, randomness.
Well, Julia, the issue isn't whether
Dan makes a choice,
or Billy Bulger or Robert E. Lee,
of course they make a choice.
The question is on what grounds, on
what principle should they choose?
The communitarian doesn't deny
that there is choice to be made.
The question is which choice,
on what grounds
and should loyalty,
as such, weigh.
Andre now you want to, all right,
go ahead. What do you say?
Well one of the things we've noticed
in the three examples is that
the people of all chosen the most immediate
community of which they're a part.
The more local one.
And I think there's something
to be said for that.
It's not just random.
I mean, there doesn't
seem to be a conflict
because they know which
one is more important.
And it's their family
over the Ec10 Class.
Their state over
their country,
and their family over the
Commonwealth on Massachusetts.
So I think that's the answer
to which is more important.
Do you think that the local,
the more particular,
is always the weightier
morally, Andre?
Well I mean there's seems to be
a trend in the three cases.
I would agree with that.
And I think most of us would agree that
your family takes precedence over
the United States perhaps.
Which is why you go with Dan?
Loyalty to the roommate
over Ec10 and the truth?
Yeah, exactly.
I would because it...
I mean truth telling,
not the truth of Ec10.
Yes.
- Alright, so we understand.
But on the same example
in terms of family,
you had cases in the civil war where
brother was pitted against brother
on both sides of the war, where they
chose country instead of family.
So I think the exact same, more
shows, that different people
have different means of
making these choices
and that there is no one set of
values, or one set of morality
that communitarians
can stick to.
And personally, I think that's the
biggest problem with communitarians,
that we don't have one set
of standard moral obligations.
And tell me your name.
- Samantha.
So Samantha, you
agree with Patrick.
Patrick's point the other day
that there may be...
If we allow obligations
to be defined by community,
identification or membership,
they may conflict, they may
overlap, they may compete.
And there is no clear principle.
Andre says here's a clear principle,
the most particular.
The other day, Nichola who was
sitting over here, where's Nichola?
Said that most universal.
You're saying, Samantha,
the scale of the community as such
can't be the decisive moral factor.
So there has to be some
other moral judgment.
All right, let's first...
Let's let our defe...
our critics of communal
patriotism,
let's express our appreciation
and thank them
for their having stood up and
responded to these arguments.
Let's turn to the
implications for justice
of the positions that we've
heard discussed here.
One of the worries underlying
these multiple objections
to the idea of loyalty or membership
as having independent moral weight
is that it seems to argue
that there is no way
of finding principles of justice
that are detached from
conceptions of the good life
as they may be lived in any
particular community.
Supposed the communitarian
argument is right.
Suppose the priority of the right
over the good can't be sustained.
Suppose instead, that justice
and rights unavoidably
are bound up with
conceptions of the good.
Does that mean that
justice is simply
a creature of convention,
of the values that happen to prevail in any
given community at any given time?
One of the writings we have
among the communitarian critics
is by Michael Walzer.
He draws the implications
of justice this way.
Justice is relative to
social meanings.
A given society is just if its substantive
life is lived in a certain way,
in a way that is faithful to the shared
understandings of the members.
So Walzer's account
seems to bear out
the worry that if we can't find
independent principles of justice,
independent that is, from conceptions of the
good that prevail in any given community,
that we're simply left with justice being
a matter of fidelity or faithfulness
to the shared understandings
or values or conventions
that prevail in any given
society at any given time.
But is that an adequate way
of thinking about justice?
Well, let's take a
look at a short clip
from the documentary
"Eyes on the Prize."
It goes back in the
1950s in the south.
Here are some situated
American Southerners
who believed in the tradition and the
shared understandings of segregation.
Listen to the arguments they
make about loyalty and tradition
And see if they don't
make you uneasy
about tying arguments about justice to
the shared understandings or traditions
that prevail in any given society
at the moment. Let's run the clip.
'This land is composed of two
different appearances.
A white culture and
a colored culture.
And I've lived close
to them all my life.
But I'm told now that
we've mistreated them
and that we must change.
And these changes are coming
faster than I expected.
And I'm required
to make decisions
on the basis of a new way
of thinking and it's difficult.
It's difficult for me, it's
difficult for all southerners.'
Well there you have it, narrative selves,
situated selves invoking tradition.
Doesn't that show us that
justice can't be tied
to the shared understandings of goods
that prevail in any given community
at any given time?
Or is there a way of rescuing
that claim from this example?
Think about that question and
we'll return to it next time.