Captions proofread by @xiaolai, www.lixiaolai.com
When we ended last time,
we were discussing
Locke's idea of government
by consent and the question arose,
"What are the limits on government
that even the agreement
of the majority can't override?"
That was the question we ended with.
We saw in the case of property rights
that on Locke's view
a democratically elected government
has the right to tax people.
It has to be taxation
with consent
because it does involve the taking
of people's property
for the common good
but it doesn't require the consent
of each individual
at the time the tax is enacted or collected.
What it does require
is a prior act of consent
to join the society,
to take on the political obligation
but once you take on that obligation,
you agree to be bound by the majority.
So much for taxation.
But what you may ask,
about the right to life?
Can the government conscript people
and send them into battle?
And what about the idea
that we own ourselves?
Isn't the idea of self-possession
violated if the government can,
through coercive legislation
and enforcement powers, say
"You must go risk your life to fight in Iraq."
What would Locke say?
Does the government
have the right to do that?
Yes. In fact he says in 139,
he says,
"What matters is that the
political authority or the military authority
not be arbitrary, that's what matters."
And he gives a wonderful example.
He says "A sergeant, even a sergeant,
let alone a general,
a sergeant can command a soldier
to go right up to a face of a cannon
where he is almost sure to die,
that the sergeant can do.
The general can condemn the soldier
to death for deserting his post
or for not obeying even a desperate order.
But with all their power over life and death,
what these officers can't do
is take a penny of that soldier's money
because that has nothing to do
with the rightful authority,
that would be arbitrary
and it would be corrupt."
So consent winds up being
very powerful in Locke,
not consent of the individual
to the particular tax or military order,
but consent to join the government
and to be bound
by the majority in the first place.
That's the consent that matters
and it matters so powerfully
that even the limited government
created by the fact
that we have an unalienable right
to life, liberty, and property,
even that limited government
is only limited in the sense
that it has to govern by
generally applicable laws,
the rule of law, it can't be arbitrary.
That's Locke.
Well this raises a question about consent.
Why is consent such a
powerful moral instrument
in creating political authority
and the obligation to obey?
Today we begin to investigate
the question of consent
by looking at a concrete case,
the case of military conscription.
Now some people say
if we have a fundamental right
that arises from the idea
that we own ourselves,
it's a violation of that right
for government to conscript citizens
to go fight in wars.
Others disagree.
Others say that's a
legitimate power of government,
of democratically elected governments,
anyhow,
and that we have an obligation to obey.
Let's take the case
of the United States fighting a war in Iraq.
News accounts tells us
that the military is having great difficulty
meeting its recruitment targets.
Consider three policies
that the U.S. government
might undertake to deal
with the fact
that it's not achieving
its recruiting targets.
Solution number one:
increase the pay and benefits
to attract a sufficient number of soldiers.
Option number two:
shift to a system of military conscription,
have a lottery,
and whose ever numbers are drawn,
go to fight in Iraq.
System number three:
outsource, hire what traditionally
have been called mercenaries,
people around the world
who are qualified,
able to do the work,
able to fight well,
and who are willing to do it
for the existing wage.
So let's take a quick poll here.
How many favor increasing the pay?
A huge majority.
How many favor going to conscription?
Maybe a dozen people
in the room favor conscription.
What about the outsourcing solution?
Okay, so there may be two,
three dozen.
During the Civil War,
the Union used a combination
of conscription and the market system
to fill the ranks of the military
to fight in the Civil War.
It was a system
that began with conscription
but if you were drafted
and didn't want to serve,
you could hire a substitute
to take your place
and many people did.
You could pay whatever
the market required
in order to find a substitute,
people ran ads in newspapers,
in the classified ads offering
500 dollars, sometimes 1000 dollars,
for a substitute who would
go fight the Civil War
in their place.
In fact, it's reported
that Andrew Carnegie
was drafted and hired a substitute
to take his place
for an amount
that was a little less
than the amount he spent
in the year on fancy cigars.
Now I want to get your views
about this Civil War system,
call it the hybrid system,
conscription but with a buyout provision.
How many think it was a just system?
How many would defend
the Civil War system?
Anybody?
Anybody else?
How many think it was unjust?
Most of you
don't like the Civil War system,
you think it's unjust.
Let's hear an objection.
Why don't you like it?
What's wrong with it? Yes.
Well by paying $300
to be exempt one time around,
you're really putting a price
on valuing human life
and we established earlier,
that's really hard to do
so they're trying to accomplish
something that really isn't feasible.
Good. So paying someone
$300 or $500 or $1,000 每
You're basically saying
that's what their life is worth to you.
That's what their life is worth,
it's putting a dollar value on life.
That's good. What's your name?
-Liz.
Liz.
Well, who has an answer for Liz.
You defended the Civil War system,
what do you say?
If you don't like the price
then you have the freedom
to not be sold or hired
so it's completely up to you.
I don't think it's necessarily
putting a specific price
on you and if it's done by himself,
I don't think there's anything
that's really morally wrong with that.
So the person who takes the $500,
let's say, he's putting his own price
on his life
or on the risk of his life
and he should have the freedom
to choose to do that.
Exactly.
What's your name?
- Jason.
Jason. Thank you.
Now we need to hear
from another critic
of the civil war system. Yes.
It's a kind or coercion almost,
people who have lower incomes,
for Carnegie he can totally ignore the draft,
$300 is an irrelevant
in terms of his income
but someone of a lower income,
they're essentially being coerced to draft,
to be drafted,
it's probably they're not able
to find a replacement.
Tell me your name.
Sam.
Sam. All right so you say,
Sam, that when a poor laborer
accepts $300 to fight in the Civil War,
he is in effect being coerced
by that money
given his economic circumstances
whereas Carnegie can go off,
pay the money, and not serve.
Alright. I want to hear someone
who has a reply to Sam's argument,
that what looks like a free exchange
is actually coercive.
Who has an answer to Sam?
Go ahead.
I'd actually agree with him in saying that 每
You agree with Sam.
I agree with him in saying that it is coercion in the sense that it robs individual of his ability to reason.
Okay, and what's your name?
Raul.
All right. So Raul and Sam
agree that what looks
like a free exchange,
free choice, voluntary act
actually involves coercion.
It's profound coercion
of the worst kind
because it falls so disproportionately
upon one segment of the society.
Good. Alright. So Raul and Sam
have made a powerful point.
Who would like to reply?
Who has an answer for Sam and Raul?
Go ahead.
I don't think that these
drafting systems
are really terribly different
from all volunteer army
sort of recruiting strategies.
The whole idea of having benefits
and pay for joining the army
is sort of a coercive strategy
to get people to join.
It is true that military volunteers
come from disproportionately
lower economic status
and also from certain regions of the country
where you can use like patriotism
to try and coerce people
to feel like it's the right thing to do
to volunteer and go over to Iraq.
And tell me your name.
Emily.
Alright, Emily says, and Raul
you're going to have to
reply to this so get ready.
Emily says fair enough,
there is a coercive element
to the Civil War system
when a laborer takes the place
of Andrew Carnegie for $500.
Emily concedes that but she says
if that troubles you about
the Civil War system
shouldn't that also trouble
you about the volunteer army today?
Before you answer,
how did you vote in the first poll?
Did you defend the volunteer army?
I didn't vote.
You didn't vote.
By the way,
you didn't vote
but did you sell your vote
to the person sitting next to you?
No. Alright.
So what would you say to that argument.
I think that the circumstances
are different in that
there was conscription in the Civil War.
There is no draft today
and I think that volunteers
for the army today have a
more profound sense of patriotism
that is of an individual choice
than those who were forced
into the military in the Civil War.
Somehow less coerced?
Less coerced.
Even though there is still inequality
in American Society?
Even though, as Emily points out,
the makeup of the American military
is not reflective of the population
as a whole?
Let's just do an experiment here.
How many here have either served
in the military or have a family member
who has served in the military
in this generation, not parents?
Family members. In this generation.
And how many have neither served
nor have any brothers or sisters who have served?
Does that bear out your point Emily?
Yes.
Alright. Now we need to hear from 每
most of you defended the idea
of the all volunteer military
overwhelmingly and yet overwhelmingly,
people considered the
Civil War system unjust.
Sam and Raul articulated reasons
for objecting to the Civil War system,
it took place against a background
of inequality
and therefore the choices people made
to buy their way in to military service
were not truly free
but at least partly coerced.
Then Emily extends that argument
in the form of a challenge.
Alright, everyone here
who voted in favor
of the all volunteer army should be able 每
should have to explain
what's the difference in principle.
Doesn't the all volunteer army
simply universalize the feature
that almost everyone found objectionable
in the Civil War buyout provision?
Did I state the challenge fairly Emily?
Yes.
Okay. So we need to hear
from a defender
of the all volunteer military
who can address Emily's challenge.
Who can do that?
Go ahead.
The difference between the Civil War system
and the all volunteer army system
is that in the Civil War,
you're being hired not by the government,
but by an individual and as a result,
different people who get hired
by different individuals
get paid different amounts.
In the case of the all volunteer army,
everyone who gets hired
is hired by the government
and gets paid the same amount.
It's precisely the universalization of
essentially paying your way
to the army that makes
the all volunteer army just.
Emily?
I guess I'd frame the principle
slightly differently.
On the all volunteer army,
it's possible for somebody
to just step aside
and not really think
about the war at all.
It's possible to say,
"I don't need the money,
I don't need to have an opinion about this,
I don't need to feel obligated
to take my part and defend my country.
With the coercive system, or sorry,
with an explicit draft
then there's the threat
at least that every individual
will have to make
some sort of decision
regarding military conscription
and perhaps in that way,
it's more equitable.
It's true that Andrew Carnegie
might not serve in any case but in one,
he can completely step aside from it,
and the other there's some level of responsibility.
While you're there, Emily,
so what system do you favor, conscription?
I would be hard pressed to say
but I think so
because it makes the whole country
feel a sense of responsibility
for the conflict instead
of having a war
that's maybe ideologically supported
by a few but only if there's no real responsibility.
Good. Who wants to reply?
Go ahead.
So I was going to say
that the fundamental difference
between the all volunteer army
and then the army in the Civil War
is that in the all volunteer army,
if you want to volunteer
that comes first
and then the pay
comes after
whereas in the Civil War system,
the people who are accepting
the pay
aren't necessarily doing it
because they want to,
they're just doing it
for the money first.
What motivation beyond the pay
do you think is operating
in the case of the all volunteer army?
Like patriotism for the country.
Patriotism. Well what about 每
And a desire to defend the country.
There is some motivation in pay
but the fact that it's first and foremost
an all volunteer army will
motivate first I think, personally.
Do you think it's better?
And tell me your name.
Jackie.
Jackie do you think it's better
if people serve in the military
out of a sense of patriotism
than just for the money?
Yes, definitely because the people who 每
that was one of the main problems
in the Civil War
is that the people
that you're getting to go in it
to go to war
aren't necessarily people
who want to fight
and so they won't be as
good soldiers as they will be
had they been there because they wanted to be.
Alright, what about
Jackie's having raised the question of patriotism,
that patriotism is a better
or a higher motivation
than money for military service.
Who would like to address that question?
Go ahead.
Patriotism absolutely is not necessary
in order to be a good soldier
because mercenaries can do
just as good of a job
as anyone who waves the American flag
around and wants to defend
what the government believes
that we should do.
Did you favor the outsourcing solution?
Yes sir.
Alright, so let Jackie respond.
What's your name?
Philip.
What about that Jackie?
So much for patriotism.
If you've got someone
whose heart is in it
more than another person,
they're going to do a better job.
When it comes down to the wire
and there's like a situation
in which someone has to put
their life on the line,
someone who's doing it
because they love this country
will be more willing
to go into danger
than someone who's just getting paid,
they don't care,
they've got the technical skills
but they don't care what happens
because they really have 每
they have nothing
like nothing invested in this country.
There's another aspect though
once we get on to the issue of patriotism.
If you believe patriotism,
as Jackie does,
should be the foremost consideration
and not money,
does that argue for or against
the paid army we have now?
We call it the volunteer army
though if you think about it,
that's a kind of misnomer.
A volunteer army as we use the term,
is a paid army.
So what about the suggestion
that patriotism should be
the primary motivation
for military service not money?
Does that argue in favor
of the paid military
that we have
or does it argue for conscription?
And just to sharpen that point
building on Phil's case for outsourcing,
if you think that the all volunteer army,
the paid army,
is best because it lets the market
allocate positions
according to people's preferences
and willingness to serve
for a certain wage,
doesn't the logic that takes you
from a system of conscription
to the hybrid Civil War system
to the all volunteer army,
doesn't the idea of expanding
freedom of choice in the market,
doesn't that lead you
all the way if you followed that principle
consistently to a mercenary army?
And then if you say no,
Jackie says no,
patriotism should count for something,
doesn't that argue
for going back to conscription
if by patriotism,
you mean a sense of civic obligation?
Let's see if we can step back
from the discussion
that we've had and see
what we've learned
about consent as it applies
to market exchange.
We've really heard two arguments,
two arguments against the use of markets
and exchange in the allocation
of military service.
One was the argument
raised by Sam and Raul,
the argument about coercion,
the objection that letting the market
allocate military service
may be unfair
and may not even be free
if there's severe inequality
in the society so that people
who buy their way into military service
are doing so not because they really want to
but because they have so few
economic opportunities
that that's their best choice
and Sam and Raul say
there's an element of coercion in that,
that's one argument.
Then there is a second objection
to using the market
to allocate military service,
that's the idea that military service
shouldn't be treated
as just another job for pay
because it's bound up
with patriotism and civic obligation.
This is a different argument
from the argument about
unfairness and inequality
and coercion,
it's an argument
that suggests that maybe
where civic obligations are concerned,
we shouldn't allocate
duties and rights by the market.
Now we've identified
two broad objections.
What do we need to know
to assess those objections?
To assess the first,
the argument from
coercion, inequality, and unfairness,
Sam, we need to ask
what inequalities in the background
conditions of society undermine
the freedom of choices
people make to buy and sell their labor,
question number one.
Question number two:
to assess the civic obligation patriotism.
Argument: we have to ask
what are the obligations of citizenship?
Is military service one of them or not?
What obligates us as citizens?
What is the source of political obligation?
Is it consent
or are there some civic obligations
we have, even without consent,
for living and sharing in a certain kind of society?
We haven't answered
either of those questions
but our debate today
about the Civil War system
and the all volunteer army
has at least raised them
and those are questions
we're going to return to in the coming weeks.
Today I'd like to turn our attention
and get your views about an argument
over the role of markets in the
realm of human reproduction and procreation.
Now with infertility clinics,
people advertise for egg donors
and from time to time,
in the Harvard Crimson
ads appear for egg donors.
Have you seen them?
There was one that ran
a few years ago
that wasn't looking for just any egg donor,
it was an ad that offered
a large financial incentive
for an egg donor
from a woman who was intelligent,
athletic, at least 5'10",
and with at least 1400
or above on her SATs.
How much do you think
the person looking for this egg donor
was willing to pay for an egg
from a woman of that description?
What would you guess?
A thousand dollars?
Fifteen thousand? Ten?
I'll show you the ad.
Fifty thousand dollars for an egg
but only a premium egg.
What do you think about that?
Well there are also sometimes
ads in the Harvard Crimson
and the other college newspapers
for sperm donors.
So the market in reproductive
capacities is an equal opportunity market.
Well not exactly equal opportunity,
they're not offering $50,000 for sperm
but there is a company,
a large commercial sperm bank
that markets sperm,
it's called California Cryobank,
it's a for-profit company,
it imposes exacting standards
on the sperm it recruits,
and it has offices in Cambridge,
between Harvard and MIT,
and in Palo Alto near Stanford.
Cryobank's marketing materials
play up the prestigious source of its sperm.
Here is, from the website of Cryobank,
the information.
Here they talk about
the compensation
although compensation
should not be the only reason
for becoming a sperm donor,
we are aware of the considerable time
and expense involved in being a donor.
So do you know what they offer?
Donors will be reimbursed $75 per specimen,
up to $900 a month if you donate
three times a week,
and then they add
"We periodically offer incentives
such as movie tickets or gift certificates
for the extra time and effort
expended by participating donors."
It's not easy to be a sperm donor.
They accept fewer than five
percent of the donors who apply.
Their admission criteria
are more demanding than Harvard's.
The head of the sperm bank
said the ideal sperm donor
is 6 feet tall, with a college degree,
brown eyes, blond hair,
and dimples for the simple reason
that these are the traits
that the market has shown
that customers want.
Quoting the head of the sperm bank,
"If our customers wanted high school dropouts,
we would give them high school dropouts."
So here are two instances,
the market in eggs for donation
and the market in sperm,
that raise a question,
a question about whether
eggs and sperm
should or should not be bought
and sold for money.
As you ponder that,
I want you to consider
another case involving market
and in fact a contract
in the human reproductive capacity
and this is the case
of commercial surrogate motherhood,
and it's a case that wound up
in court some years ago.
It's the story of Baby M.
It began with William and Elizabeth Stern,
a professional couple wanting a baby
but they couldn't have one
on their own,
at least not without medical risk
to Mrs. Stern.
They went to an infertility clinic
where they met Mary Beth Whitehead,
a 29-year-old mother of two,
the wife of a sanitation worker.
She had replied to an ad that The
Standard had placed seeking the service
of a surrogate mother.
They made a deal.
They signed a contract
in which William Stern
agreed to pay Mary Beth Whitehead
a $10,000 fee
plus all expenses in exchange
for which Mary Beth Whitehead
agreed to be artificially inseminated
with William Stern's sperm,
to bear the child,
and then to give the baby to the Sterns.
Well, you probably know
how the story unfolded.
Mary Beth gave birth
and changed her mind,
she decided she wanted to keep the baby.
The case wound up in
court in New Jersey.
So let's take,
put aside any legal questions,
and focus on this issue
as a moral question.
How many believe
that the right thing to do in the Baby M case,
would have been to uphold the contract,
to enforce the contract?
And how many think
the right thing to do
would have been not to
enforce that contract?
The majority say enforce
so let's now hear the reasons
that people had,
either for enforcing or refusing
to enforce this contract.
First I want to hear from someone
in the majority.
Why do you uphold the contract?
Why do you enforce it?
Who can offer a reason?
Yes. Stand up.
It's a binding contract,
all the parties involved
knew the terms of the contract
before any action was taken,
it's a voluntary agreement,
the mother knew what she was getting into,
all four intelligent adults,
regardless of formal education, whatever.
So it makes sense that if you know
that you're getting into beforehand
and you make a promise,
you should uphold that promise in the end.
Okay, a deal is a deal in other words.
Exactly.
- And what's your name?
Patrick.
Is Patrick's reason the reason
that most of you in the majority
favored upholding the contract?
Yes. Alright, let's hear now someone
who would not enforce the contract.
What do you say to Patrick?
Why not? Yes.
Well, I mean, I agree,
I think contracts should be upheld
when all the parties know all the information
but in this case,
I don't think there's a way a mother,
before the child exists,
could actually know
how she's going to feel about that child
so I don't think the mother actually
had all the information.
She didn't know the person
that was going to be born
and didn't know how much she would
love that person so that's my argument.
So you would not,
and what's your name?
Evan Wilson.
Evan says he would not uphold the
contract because when it was entered into
the surrogate mother couldn't be expected
to know in advance
how she would feel
so she didn't really have the relevant information
when she made that contract.
Who else?
Who else would not uphold the contract? Yes.
I also think that a contract should
generally be upheld
but I think that the child
has an inalienable right to its actual mother
and I think that if that mother
wants it then that child
should have the right to that mother.
You mean the biological mother not the adoptive mother?
Right.
And why is that?
First of all, tell me your name.
Anna.
Anna. Why is that Anna?
Because I think that that bond
is created by nature
is stronger than any bond
that is created by a contract.
Good. Thank you.
Who else? Yes.
I disagree. I don't think that a child
has an inalienable right
to her biological mother.
I think that adoption and surrogacy
are both legitimate tradeoffs
and I agree with the point made
that it's a voluntary agreement,
the individual who made it,
it's a voluntary agreement
and you can't apply
coercion to this argument.
You can't apply the objection
from coercion to this argument?
Correct.
What's your name?
- Kathleen.
Kathleen, what do you say to
Evan that though there may not have been 每
Evan claimed that the consent
was tainted not by coercion
but by lack of adequate information.
She couldn't have known
the relevant information
namely how she would feel about the child.
What do you say to that?
I don't think the emotional content
of her feelings plays into this.
I think in a case of law,
in the justice of this scenario,
her change of feelings are not relevant.
If I give up my child for adoption
and then I decide later on
that I really want that child back,
too bad, it's a tradeoff,
it's a tradeoff that the mother has made.
So a deal is a deal,
you agree with Patrick?
I agree with Patrick,
a deal's a deal.
A deal is a deal.
Yes.
- Good. Yes.
I would say that though
I'm not really sure if I agree
with the idea that the child
has a right to their mother.
I think the mother definitely
has a right to her child
and I also think that there's
some areas where market forces
shouldn't necessarily penetrate.
I think that the whole
surrogate mother area
smacks a little bit of dealing
in human beings seems dehumanizing.
It doesn't really seem right
so that's my main reason.
And what is 每 could you tell us your name.
I'm Andrew.
Andrew, what is dehumanizing about buying and
selling the right to a child, for money,
what is dehumanizing about it?
Well because you're buying
someone's biological right.
I mean you can't 每 in the law as it stated,
you can't sell your own child
were you to have a child,
I'd believe that the law
prohibits you selling it to another person or 每
So this like baby selling?
Right. To a certain extent.
Though there's a contract
with another person,
you've made agreements and what not,
there is an undeniable emotional bond
that takes place between the mother
and the child and it's wrong
to simply ignore this because
you've written out something contractually.
Right. You want to reply to Andrew?
Stay there.
You point out there's an
undeniable emotional bond,
I feel like in this situation,
we're not necessarily arguing
against adoption or surrogacy in itself,
we're just sort of
pointing out the emotional differences.
But wait, I mean,
it's easy to break everything down
to numbers and say
"Oh, we have contracts,"
like you're buying or selling a car
but there are underlying emotions,
I mean, you're dealing with people,
these are not objects to be bought and sold.
Alright. What about Andrew's claim
that this is like baby selling.
I believe that adoption and surrogacy
should be permitted,
whether or not I actually will partake in it
is not really relevant
but I think that the government should,
the government should
give its citizens the rights
to allow for adoption and surrogacy.
But adoption is not 每 according to 每
Is adoption baby selling?
Well, do you think you should
be able to bid for a baby that's up for adoption?
That's Andrew's challenge.
Do I think I should be
able to bid for a baby?
I'm not - sure! It's a market,
I feel the extent to which it's been applied
and I'm not sure if the government
should be able to permit it
and I have to think about it more but 每
Alright. Fair enough.
Are you satisfied Andrew?
Well, yeah, I mean,
I think surrogacy should be permitted.
I think that people can do it
but I don't think that it should be
forced upon people that
once a contract is signed,
it's absolutely the end all.
I think that it's unenforceable.
So people should be free
Andrew to enter into these contracts
but it should not be
enforceable in the court.
Not in the court, no.
Who would like to turn on
one side or the other? Yes.
I think I have an interesting perspective
on this because my brother
was actually one of the people
who donated to a sperm bank
and he was paid a very large amount of money,
he was six feet tall but not blond,
he had dimples though.
So he actually has, I'm an aunt now,
he has a daughter,
he donated his sperm to a lesbian couple
in Oklahoma and he has been
contacted by them and he has seen pictures
of his daughter but he still
does not feel an emotional bond
to his daughter,
he just has a sense of curiosity
about what she looks like
and what she's doing
and how she is.
He doesn't feel love for his child
so from this experience,
I think the bond between a mother
and a child cannot be compared
to the bond between
the father and the child.
That's really interesting.
What's your name?
Vivian.
Vivian. So we've got the case
of surrogacy, commercial surrogacy,
and it's been compared to baby selling
and we've been exploring
whether that analogy
is apt and it can also be compared,
as you point out, to sperm selling.
But you're saying that sperm
selling and baby selling
or even surrogacy are very different because 每
Yes, they're unequal services.
They're unequal services
and that's because Vivian,
you say that the tie, the bond 每
Yes, and also the time investment
that's given by a mother,
nine months, cannot be compared
to a man going into a sperm bank,
looking at pornography,
depositing into a cup.
I don't think those are equal.
Good. Alright.
Because that's what happens in a sperm bank.
Alright. So this is really interesting,
we have 每 notice the arguments
that have come out so far.
The objections to surrogacy,
the objections to enforcing
that contract are of at least two kinds.
There was the objection
about tainted consent,
this time not because of coercion
or implicit coercion
but because of imperfect
or flawed information.
So tainted or flawed consent
can arise either because of coercion
or because of a lack
of relevant information,
at least according
to one argument that we've heard
and then a second objection
to enforcing the surrogacy contract
was that it was somehow dehumanizing.
Now when this case
was decided by the courts,
what did they say about these arguments?
The lower court ruled
that the contract was enforceable,
neither party had a
superior bargaining position.
A price for the service
was struck and a bargain was reached.
One side didn't force the other
neither had disproportionate bargaining power.
Then it went to the New Jersey Supreme Court.
And what did they do?
They said this contract is not enforceable.
They did grant custody to Mr. Stern
as the father
because they thought that would be
in the best interest of the child
but they restored the rights of Mary Beth Whitehead
and left it to lower courts to decide
exactly what the visitation rights should be.
They invoked two different kinds of reasons,
along the lines that Andrew proposed.
First, there was not sufficiently
informed consent, the court argued.
"Under the contract the natural
mother is irrevocably committed
before she knows the strength of her bond
with her child,
she never makes a truly voluntary informed
decision for any decision
prior to the baby's birth
is in the most important sense,
uninformed," that was the court.
Then the court also made a
version of the second argument
against commodification in this kind
of case "this is the sale of a child,"
the court said, "or at the very least,
the sale of a mother's right to her child.
Whatever idealism may motivate the
participants, the profit motive predominates
permeates, and ultimately
governs the transaction."
And so regardless,
the court said,
regardless of any argument
about consent or flawed consent
or full information,
there are some things in a civilized society
that money can't buy,
that's what the court said
in voiding this contract.
Well, what about these two arguments
against the extension of markets
to procreation and to reproduction?
How persuasive are they?
There was 每 it's true, a voluntary agreement,
a contract struck between
William Stern and Mary Beth Whitehead.
But there are at least two ways
that consent can be other than truly free.
First, if people are pressured
or coerced to give their agreement
and second, if their consent
is not truly informed
and in the case of surrogacy,
the court said a mother can't know,
even one who already
has kids of her own,
what it would be like to bear a child
and give it up for pay.
So in order to assess criticism,
objection number one,
we have to figure out
just how free does a voluntary exchange
have to be with respect
to the bargaining power and equal information
Question number one:
how do we assess the second objection?
The second objection
is more elusive, it's more difficult.
Andrew acknowledged this, right?
What does it mean to say
there is something dehumanizing
to make childbearing a market transaction?
Well, one of the philosophers
we read on this subject, Elizabeth Anderson,
tries to brings some philosophical clarity
to the unease that Andrew articulated.
She said "by requiring the surrogate mother
to repress whatever parental love
she feels for the child,
surrogacy contracts
convert women's labor
into a form of alienated labor.
The surrogate's labor is alienated
because she must divert it
from the end which the social practices
of pregnancy rightly promote,
namely an emotional bond with her child."
So what Anderson is suggesting
is that certain goods should not be treated
as open to use or to profit.
Certain goods are properly valued
in ways other than use.
What are other ways of valuing
and treating goods
that should not be open to use?
Anderson says there are many:
respect, appreciation,
love, honor, awe, sanctity.
There are many modes of valuation
beyond use and certain goods
are not properly valued
if they're treated simply as objects of use.
How do we go about evaluating
that argument of Anderson?
In a way, it takes us back
to the debate we had with utilitarianism.
Is utility 每 is use the only
proper way of treating goods,
including life, military service,
procreation, childbearing?
And if not,
how do we figure out?
How can we determine
what modes of valuation
are fitting or appropriate
to those goods?
Several years ago
there was a scandal surrounding a doctor,
an infertility specialist
in Virginia named Cecil Jacobson.
He didn't have a donor catalogue
because unknown to his patients,
all of the sperm he used to inseminate
his patients came from one donor,
Dr. Jacobson himself.
At least one woman who testified in court
was unnerved at how much
her newborn daughter
looked just like him.
Now it's possible to condemn
Dr. Jacobson for failing
to inform the women in advance
that would be the argument about consent.
The columnist, Ellen Goodman,
described the bizarre scenario as follows,
"Dr. Jacobson," she wrote
"gave his infertility business
the personal touch
but now the rest of us,"
she wrote "are in for a round
of second thoughts about sperm donation."
Goodman concluded that fatherhood
should be something you do,
not something you donate.
And I think what she was doing
and what the philosopher
Elizabeth Anderson is doing
and what Andrew was suggesting
with his argument about dehumanization
is pondering whether
there are certain goods
that money shouldn't buy,
not just because of tainted consent
but also perhaps because
certain goods are properly valued
in a way higher than mere use.
Those at least are the questions
we're going to pursue
with the help of some
philosophers in the weeks to come.