Captions proofread by @xiaolai, www.lixiaolai.com
Today, we turn
to the question of
distributive justice.
How should income
in wealth and power
and opportunities
be distributed?
According to what principles?
John Rawls offers a detailed
answer to that question.
And we're going to examine
and assess his answer
to that question, today.
We put ourselves in a
position to do so last time.
By trying to make sense
of why he thinks
that principles of justice
are best derived from a
hypothetical contract.
And what matters is that
the hypothetical contract
be carried out in an original
position of equality,
behind, what Rawls calls,
the veil of ignorance.
So that much is clear?
Alright, then let's turn
to the principles
that Rawls says
would be chosen
behind the veil of ignorance.
First, he considered some of
the major alternatives.
What about utilitarianism?
Would the people in
the original position
choose to govern
their collective lives
utilitarian principles, the greatest
good for the greatest number?
No, they wouldn't, Rawls says.
And the reason is,
that behind the veil of ignorance,
everyone knows
that once the veil goes up,
and real life begins,
we will each want to be
respected with dignity.
Even if we turn out to be
a member of a minority.
We don't want to be oppressed.
And so we would agree
to reject utilitarianism,
and instead to adopt
as our first principle,
equal basic liberties.
Fundamental rights to
freedom of speech,
freedom of assembly,
religious liberty,
freedom of conscience
and the like.
We wouldn't want to
take the chance
that we would wind up
as members of an oppressed
or a despised minority
with the majority
tyrannizing over us.
And so Rawls says utilitarianism
would be rejected.
"Utilitarianism makes the
mistake", Rawls writes,
"of forgetting, or at least
not taking seriously,
the distinction between persons."
And in the original position
behind the veil of ignorance,
we would recognize that
and reject utilitarianism.
We wouldn't trade off our
fundamental rights and liberties
for any economic advantages.
That's the first principle.
Second principle has to do with
social and economic inequalities.
What would we agree to?
Remember, we don't know
whether we're going to
wind up rich or poor.
Healthy or unhealthy.
We don't know what kind of family
we're going to come from.
Whether we're going
to inherit millions
or whether we will come from
an impoverished family.
So we might, at
first thought,
say, "Well let's require an equal
distribution of income and wealth."
Just to be on the safe side.
But then we would realize,
that we could do
better than that.
Even if we're unlucky and
wind up at the bottom.
We could do better if we agree to
a qualified principle of equality.
Rawls calls it
"the Difference Principle".
A principle that says, only
those social and economic
inequalities will be permitted
that work to the benefit
of the least well off.
So we wouldn't reject all
inequality of income and wealth.
We would allow some.
But the test would be,
do they work to the benefit of
everyone including those,
or as he specifies, the principle,
especially those at the bottom.
Only those inequalities would be
accepted behind the veil of ignorance.
And so Rawls argues, only those
inequalities that work to the benefit
of the least well off, are just.
We talked about
the examples of
Michael Jordan making
31 million dollars a year.
Of Bill Gates having a fortune
in the tens of billions.
Would those inequalities be permitted
under the difference principle?
Only if they were part of a system,
those wage differentials,
that actually work to the
advantage of least well off.
Well, what would
that system be?
Maybe it turns out that
as a practical matter
you have to provide incentives
to attract the right
people to certain jobs.
And when you do, having
those people in those jobs
will actually help those
at the bottom.
Strictly speaking, Rawls's argument
for the difference principle
is that it would be chosen
behind the veil of ignorance.
Let me hear what
you think about
Rawls's claim that these two
principles would be chosen
behind the veil of ignorance.
Is there anyone who disagrees
that they would be chosen?
Alright, let's start up in the
balcony, if that's alright.
Go ahead.
OK, your argument depends
upon us believing that
we would argue in said policy,
or justice from a bottom.
For the disadvantaged.
And I just don't see from
a proof standpoint,
where we've proven that.
Why not the top?
Right, and what's your name?
- Mike.
Mike, alright, good question.
Put yourself behind
the veil of ignorance.
Enter into the thought experiment.
What principles would you choose?
How would you think it through?
Well, I would say things like,
even Harvard's existence
is an example of preaching
toward the top.
Because Harvard takes
the top academics.
And I didn't know when I was
born how smart I would be.
But I worked my life to get
to a place of this caliber.
Now, if you had said Harvard's going
to randomly take 1600 people
of absolutely no qualification,
we'd all be saying,
"There's not much to work for."
And so what principle
would you choose?
In that situation I would
say a merit based one.
One where I don't necessarily know, but
I would rather have a system that
rewards me based
on my efforts.
So you, Mike, behind
the veil of ignorance,
would choose a
merit-based system,
where people are rewarded
according to their efforts?
Alright, fair enough.
What would you say?
Go ahead.
My question is, if the merit-based
argument is based on
when everyone is at
a level of equality?
Where from that position, you're
rewarded to where you get,
or is it regardless of what
advantages you may have
when you began your education
to get where you are here?
I think what the question
you're asking is saying that
if we want to look at,
whatever, utilitarianism, policy,
do you want to maximize
world wealth.
And I think a system
that rewards merit
is the one that we've pretty
much all established,
is what is best for all of us.
Despite the fact that some of us
may be in the second percentile
and some may be in
the 98th percentile.
At the end of the day it lifts
that lowest based level,
a community that rewards effort
as opposed to an differences.
But, I don't understand how you're
rewards someone's efforts
who clearly has had, not
you, but maybe myself,
advantages throughout,
to get where I am here.
I mean, I can't say
that somebody else
who maybe worked
as hard as I did
would have had the same
opportunity to come
to a school like this.
Alright, let's look at that point.
What's your name?
Kate. -Kate, you suspect
that the ability
to get into top schools
may largely depend
on coming from
an affluent family.
Having a favorable
family background,
social, cultural, economic
advantages and so on?
I mean, economic, but
yes, social, cultural.
All of those advantages,
for sure.
Someone did a study,
of the 146 selective
colleges and universities
in the United States.
And they looked at the students
in those colleges and universities
to try to find out what their background
was, their economic background.
What percentage do you think,
come from the bottom quarter
of the income scale?
You know what the figure is?
Only three percent of students, at the
most selective colleges and universities
come from poor backgrounds.
Over 70 percent come
from affluent families.
Let's go one step further then,
and try to address Mike's challenge.
Rawls actually has two
arguments, not one,
in favor of his principles of justice.
And in particular, of
the difference principle.
One argument is the
official argument,
what would be chosen behind
the veil of ignorance.
Some people challenge
that argument, saying,
"Maybe people would want
to take their chances.
Maybe people would be gamblers
behind the veil of ignorance.
Hoping that they would
wind up on top."
That's one challenge that
has been put to Rawls.
But backing up the argument
from the original position
is the second argument.
And that is the straightforwardly
moral argument.
And it goes like this,
it says,
the distribution of income and
wealth and opportunities
should not be based on factors
for which people can
claim no credit.
It shouldn't be based on factors that are
arbitrary from a moral point of view.
Rawls illustrates this by considering
several rival theories of justice.
He begins with the
theory of justice
that most everyone
these days would reject.
A feudal aristocracy.
What's wrong with the allocation of
life prospects in a feudal aristocracy?
Rawls says, well the thing that's
obviously wrong about it is
that people's life prospects
are determined
by the accident of birth.
Are you born to a noble family or
to a family of peasants and serfs?
And that's it.
You can't rise.
It's not your doing
where you wind up
or what opportunities
you have.
But that's arbitrary from
a moral point of view.
And so that objection
to feudal aristocracy
leads, and historically has
lead, people to say,
careers should be
open to talents.
There should be formal
equality of opportunity
regardless of the accident
of birth.
Every person should be free
to strive, to work,
to apply for any job
in the society.
And then, if you open up jobs,
and you allow people to apply,
and to work as hard as they can,
then the results are just.
So it's more or less the libertarian
system that we've discussed
in earlier weeks.
What does Rawls think
about this?
He says it's an improvement.
It's an improvement because
it doesn't take as fixed
the accident of birth.
But even with formal
equality of opportunity
the libertarian conception
doesn't extend that,
doesn't extend its
insight far enough.
Because if you let
everybody run the race,
everybody can enter the race,
but some people start
at different starting points,
that race isn't going to be fair.
Intuitively, he says, the most
obvious injustice of this system
is that it permits distributive shares
to be improperly influenced
by factors arbitrary from
a moral point of view.
Such as, whether you got
a good education or not.
Whether you grew up in
a family that support you
and developed in
you a work ethic
and gave you the
opportunities.
So that suggests moving
to a system of fair
equality of opportunity.
And that's really the system that
Mike was advocating earlier on.
What we might call
a merit-based system.
A meritocratic system.
In a fair meritocracy the society
sets up institutions
to bring everyone to the
same starting point
before the race begins.
Equal educational opportunities.
Head start programs,
for example.
Support for schools in
impoverished neighborhoods.
So that everyone, regardless
of their family background,
has a genuinely fair opportunity.
Everyone starts from the
same starting line.
Well, what does Rawls think
about the meritocratic system?
Even that, he says,
doesn't go far enough
in remedying,
or addressing,
the moral arbitrariness
of the natural lottery.
Because if you bring everyone
to the same starting point
and begin the race,
who's going to win the race?
Who would win?
To use the runners example.
The fastest runners would win.
But is it their doing
that they happen to be blessed
with athletic prowess to run fast?
So Rawls says, "Even the
principle of meritocracy,
where you bring everyone
to the same starting point,
may eliminate the influence of social
contingencies and upbringing,
...but it still permits the distribution of
wealth and income to be determined
by the natural distribution
of abilities and talents."
And so he thinks that the
principle of eliminating
morally arbitrary influences in the
distribution of income and wealth
requires going beyond
what Mike favors,
the meritocratic system.
Now, how do you go beyond?
Do you bring everyone to
the same starting point
and you're still bothered
by the fact that
some are fast runners and
some are not fast runners,
what can you do?
Well, some critics of a more
egalitarian conception
say the only thing you can do
is handicap the fast runners.
Make them wear lead shoes.
But who wants to do that?
That would defeat the whole
point of running the race.
But Rawls says, you
don't have to have
a kind of leveling equality,
if you want to go
beyond a meritocratic conception.
You permit, you
even encourage,
those who may be gifted,
to exercise their talents.
But what you do,
is you change the terms
on which people are
entitled to the fruits of
the exercise of those talents.
And that really is what
the difference principle is.
You establish a
principle that says,
people may benefit from
their good fortune,
from their luck in
the genetic lottery,
but only on terms that work to the
advantage of the least well off.
And so, for example,
Michael Jordan can make
31 million dollars but,
only under a system that
taxes away a chunk of that
to help those who lack the basketball
skills that he's blessed with.
Likewise, Bill Gates.
He can make his billions.
But he can't think that he
somehow morally deserves
those billions.
"Those who have been
favored by nature,
may gain from their good fortune
but only on terms that improve
the situation of those
who have lost out."
That's the difference principle.
And it's an argument from
moral arbitrarianists.
Rawls claims, that if you're bothered
by basing distributive shares
on factors arbitrary from
a moral point of view,
you don't just reject a feudal
aristocracy for a free market.
You don't even rest content
with a meritocratic system
that brings everyone to
the same starting point.
You set up a system, where everyone,
including those at the bottom,
benefit from the exercise of
the talents held by those
who happen to be lucky.
What do you think?
Is that persuasive?
Who finds that argument
unpersuasive?
The argument for
moral arbitrarianists.
Yes.
I think that in the
egalitarian proposition
the more talented people,
I think it's very optimistic
to think that they
would still work really hard,
even if they knew that
part of what they made
would be given away.
So I think that the only way for
the more talented people to
exercise their talents to
the best of their ability
is in the meritocracy.
And in a meritocracy,
what's your name?
Kate.
Kate, does it bother you, and
Mike, does it bother you,
that in a meritocratic system, that even
with fair equality of opportunity,
people get ahead, people get
rewards that they don't deserve
simply because they happen
to be naturally gifted.
What about that?
I think that it is arbitrary.
Obviously it's arbitrary.
But I think that correcting for
it would be detrimental.
Because it would reduce
incentives, is that why?
It would reduce incentives, yeah.
Mike, what do you say?
We're all sitting in this room
and we have undeserved,
we have undeserved
glory of some sort.
So you should not be satisfied
with the process of your life.
Because you have not
created any of this.
And I think, from a standpoint of,
not just this room, us being upset,
but from a societal standpoint
we should have some kind of
a gut reaction to that feeling.
The guy who runs the
race, he doesn't...
He actually harms us as opposed
to maybe makes me run that last
ten yards faster.
And that makes the guy behind
me run ten yards faster
and the guy behind
him ten yards faster.
Alright, so Mike,
let me ask you.
You talked about effort before.
Effort.
Do you think when people work
hard to get ahead, and succeed,
that they deserve the rewards
that go with effort?
Isn't that the idea behind
your defense?
I mean, of course, bring
Michael Jordan here,
I'm sure you can get him,
and have him come
and defend himself about
he makes 31 million dollars.
And I think what you're
going to realize is
his life was a very, very tough
one to get to the top.
And that we are basically being the majority
oppressing the minority in a different light.
It's very easy to pick on him.
Very easy.
Alright, effort.
You've got...
I've got a few. I've got a few.
But that's about it.
Effort, you know what
Rawls's answer to that is?
Even the effort that
some people expend,
conscientious driving,
the work ethic,
even effort depends a lot on
fortunate family circumstances.
For which you, we,
can claim no credit.
Let's do the test.
Let's do a test here.
Never mind economic class, those
differences are very significant.
Put those aside.
Psychologists say that birth
order makes a lot of difference
in work ethic, striving,
effort.
How many here,
raise your hand,
those of you here,
who are first in birth order.
I am too by the way.
Mike, I noticed you
raised your hand.
If the case for the
meritocratic conception
is that effort should
be rewarded,
doesn't Rawls have a
point that even effort
striving, work ethic is largely
shaped even by birth order?
Is it your doing?
Mike, is it your doing that you
were first in birth order?
Then why, Rawls says,
of course not.
So why should income and wealth
and opportunities in life
be based on factors arbitrary
from a moral point of view?
That's the challenge that he puts
to market societies,
but also
to those of us at
places like this.
A question to think
about for next time.
A justice of the United States
Supreme Court,
what do they make?
It's just under $200,000.
But there's another judge who makes
a lot more than Sandra Day O'Connor.
Do you know who it is?
- Judge Judy?
Judge Judy.
How did you know that?
Judge Judy, you know
how much she makes?
$25 million.
Now, is that just?
Is it fair?
We ended last time with that
remarkable poll, do you remember?
The poll about birth order.
What percentage of people
in this room raised
their hands,
was it, to say that they
were the first born?
75, 80 percent?
And what was the
significance of that?
If you're thinking about these
theories of distributive justice.
Remember, we were discussing
three different theories
of distributive justice.
Three different ways of
answering the question,
"How should income and wealth
and opportunities
and the good things in
life, be distributed?"
And so far we've looked
at the libertarian answer.
That says, the just
system of distribution
is a system of free exchange,
a free market economy.
Against a background
of formal equality.
Which simply means, that jobs and
careers are open to anyone.
Rawls says that this represents
an improvement
over aristocratic and caste systems,
because everyone can
compete for every job.
Careers open to talents.
And beyond that, the just
distribution is the one
that results from free exchange.
Voluntary transactions.
No more, no less.
Then Rawls argues, if all you
have is formal equality,
jobs open to everyone,
the result is not
going to be fair.
It will be biased in favor of
those who happen to be born
to affluent families,
who happen to have the benefit of
good educational opportunities.
And that accident of birth
is not a just basis for
distributing life chances.
And so, many people who
notice this unfairness,
Rawls argues, are lead to embrace a
system of fair equality of opportunity.
That leads to the
meritocratic system.
Fair equality of opportunity.
But Rawls says, even if
you bring everyone
to the same starting
point in the race,
what's going to happen?
Who's going to win?
The fastest runners.
So once you're troubled by
basing distributive shares
on morally arbitrary contingencies,
you should, if you
reason it through,
be carried all the way to what Rawls
calls, "the democratic conception".
A more egalitarian conception
of distributive justice
that he defines by
the difference principle.
Now, he doesn't say that
the only way to remedy
or to compensate for differences
in natural talents and abilities
is to have a kind of,
leveling equality.
A guaranteed equality
of outcome.
But he does say
there's another way to deal
with these contingencies.
People may gain, may benefit
from their good fortune,
but only on terms that work to the
advantage of the least well off.
And so, we can test how
this theory actually works
by thinking about some
paid differentials that arise
in our society.
What does the average
school teacher make
in the United States,
do you suppose?
Roughly.
-$35,000.
It's a little more, 40, $42,000.
What about David Letterman?
How much do you think
David Letterman makes?
More than a school teacher?
$31 million.
David Letterman.
Is that fair?
That David Letterman makes that
much more than a school teacher?
Well, Rawls's answer would be,
it depends whether the basic structure
of society is designed in such a way
that Letterman's $31 million
is subject to taxation
so that some of those
earnings are taken
to work for the advantage
of the least well off.
One other example of
a paid differential.
A justice of the United States
Supreme Court.
What do they make?
It's just under $200,000.
Here's Sandra Day O'Connor,
for example. There she is.
But there's another judge
who makes a lot more
than Sandra Day O'Connor.
Do you know who it is?
- Judge Judy.
Judge Judy.
How did you know that?
You watch?
You're right.
Judge Judy, you know
how much she makes?
There she is.
$25 million.
Now, is that just?
Is it fair?
Well, the answer is,
it depends on whether
this is against
a background system
in line with
the difference principle.
Where those who come
out on top, in terms of
income and wealth are
taxed in a way
that benefits the least
well off members of society.
Now, we're going to come back
to these wage differentials,
pay differentials,
between a real judge
and a TV judge.
The one Marcus watches
all the time.
What I want to do now,
is return to these theories
and to examine the objections to
Rawls's more egalitarian theory.
The difference principle.
There are at least
three objections
to Rawls's difference principle.
One of them came up last
time in the discussion
and a number of you
raised this worry.
What about incentives?
Isn't there the risk, if taxes reach
70, 80, 90 percent marginal rate
that Michael Jordan
won't play basketball?
That David Letterman won't
do late night comedy?
Or that CEOs will go into
some other line of work?
Now, who among those who
are defenders of Rawls
who has an answer to
this objection about
the need for incentives?
Yes. Go ahead, stand up.
Rawls's idea is that there should
only be so much difference
that it helps the least
well off the most.
So if there's too much equality,
then the least well off
might not be able to
watch late night TV,
or might not have a job because
their CEO doesn't want to work.
So you need to find the
correct balance where
taxation still leaves enough incentive
to least well off to benefit
from the talents.
- Good.
And what's your name?
- Tim.
Tim. Alright, so Tim is
saying, in effect,
that Rawls is taking
count of incentives.
And could allow for pay
differentials and
for some adjustment
in the tax rate
to take account of incentives.
But, Tim points out,
the standpoint from which the question
of incentives needs to be considered
is not the effect on the total
size of the economic pie.
But instead from the
standpoint of the effect
of incentives, or disincentives,
on the well-being of
those on the bottom.
Right?
Good. Thank you.
I think that is what
Rawls would say.
In fact, if you look
in section 17,
where he describes
the difference principle,
he allows for incentives.
"The naturally advantaged
are not gain
merely because they
are more gifted,
but only to cover the costs
of training and education
and for using their endowments in
ways that help less fortunate as well."
So you can have incentives.
You can adjust the tax rate.
If taking too much from
David Letterman
or from Michael Jordan,
or from Bill Gates,
winds up actually hurting
those at the bottom.
That's the test.
So incentives, that's not a
decisive objections against
Rawls's difference principle.
But there are two weightier,
more difficult objections.
One of them
comes from defenders of
a meritocratic conception.
The argument that says,
what about effort?
What about people
working hard
having a right
to what they earn
because they've deserved it.
They've worked hard for it.
That's the objection from
effort and moral desert.
Then there's another objection.
That comes from libertarians.
And this objection has to do
with reasserting the idea
of self-ownership.
Doesn't the difference principle,
by treating
our natural talents and
endowments as common assets,
doesn't that violate the idea
that we own ourselves?
Now, let me deal first,
with the objection that comes
from the libertarian direction.
Milton Friedman writes,
in his book, "Free to Choose,"
"Life is not fair.
And it's tempting to believe
that government can rectify
what nature has spawned."
But his answer is,
"The only way to try to
rectify that is to have
a leveling equality
of outcome."
Everyone finishing the
race at the same point.
And that would be a disaster.
This is an easy argument
to answer.
And Rawls addresses it.
In one of the most powerful
passages, I think,
of the theory of justice.
It's in Section 17.
"The natural distribution",
and here he's talking about
the natural distribution
talents and endowments.
"...is neither just nor unjust.
"Nor is it unjust that persons are born
into society at some particular position.
These are simply natural facts.
What is just and unjust is
the way that institutions
deal with these facts."
That's his answer to libertarian
laissez faire economists
like Milton Friedman who say,
"Life is unfair but get over it."
Get over it and let's see
if we can, at least,
maximize the benefits
that flow from it.
But the more powerful
libertarian objection to Rawls
is not libertarian from the libertarian
economists like Milton Friedman.
It's from the argument
about self-ownership.
Developed as we saw,
in Nozick.
And from that point of view,
yes, it might be a good thing,
to create head start programs
and public schools
so that everyone can
go to a decent school
and start the race at the
same starting line.
That might be good.
But if you tax people to
create public schools,
if you tax people
against their will,
you coerce them.
It's a form of theft.
If you take some of
Letterman's $31 million,
tax it away to support public
schools, against his will,
the state is really doing
no better than stealing from him.
It's coercion.
And the reason is,
we have to think of ourselves
as owning our talents
and endowments.
Because otherwise we're back to just
using people and coercing people.
That's the libertarian reply.
What's Rawls's answer
to that objection?
He doesn't address the idea
of self-ownership directly.
But the effect, the moral
weight of his argument
for the difference principle is,
maybe we don't own ourselves in
that thoroughgoing sense after all.
Now, he says, this doesn't
mean that the state
is an owner in me, in the
sense that it can simply
commandeer my life.
Because remember,
the first principle
we would agree to behind
the veil of ignorance,
is the principle of
equal basic liberties.
Freedom of speech,
religious liberty,
freedom of conscience
and the like.
So the only respect
in which the idea of
self-ownership must give way,
comes when we're thinking
about whether
I own myself in the sense that
I have a privileged claim
on the benefits that come from
the exercise of my talents
in a market economy.
And Rawls says, on
reflection, we don't.
We can defend rights.
We can respect the individual.
We can uphold human dignity.
Without embracing the
idea of self-possession.
That, in effect, is his reply
to the libertarian.
I want to turn now,
to his reply to
the defender of a
meritocratic conception.
Who invokes effort as the
basis of moral desert.
People who work hard
to develop their talents
deserve the benefits that come
from the exercise of their talents.
Well, we've already seen the
beginning of Rawls's answer
to that question.
And it goes back to that poll
we took about birth order.
His first answer is
even the work ethic, even the
willingness to strive conscientiously,
depends on all sorts of
family circumstances and
social and cultural contingencies
for which we can claim no credit.
You can't claim credit for
the fact that you,
most of you, most of us, happen
to be first in birth order.
And that for some complex
psychological and social reasons
that seems to be
associated with striving,
with achieving,
with effort.
That's one answer.
There's a second answer.
Those of you who
invoke effort,
you don't really believe that moral
desert attaches to effort.
Take two construction workers.
One is strong and can raise
four walls in an hour
without even breaking
a sweat.
And another construction
worker is small and scrawny.
And has to spend three days
to do the same
amount of work.
No defender of meritocracy
is going to look at the effort
of that weak an scrawny
construction worker and say
"Therefore he deserves
to make more".
So it isn't really effort.
This is the second reply
to the meritocratic claim.
It isn't really effort
that the defender of meritocracy
believes is the moral basis
of distributive shares.
It's contribution.
How much do you
contribute?
But contribution
takes us right back to
our natural talents and abilities.
Not just effort.
And it's not our doing, how
we came into the possession
of those talents in
the first place.
Alright, suppose you
accepted these arguments,
that effort isn't everything,
that contribution matters,
from the standpoint of the
meritocratic conception.
That effort, even,
isn't our own doing.
Does that mean,
the objection continues,
does that mean that
according to Rawls,
moral desert has nothing to
do with distributive justice?
Well, yes.
Distributive justice is not
about moral desert.
Now, here, Rawls
introduces an important
and a tricky distinction.
It's between moral desert,
on the one hand,
and entitlements to legitimate
expectations, on the other.
What is the difference between
moral deserts and entitlements?
Consider two different games.
A game of chance and
a game of skill.
Take a game of pure chance.
Say, I play the Massachusetts
state lottery.
And my number comes up.
I'm entitled to my winnings.
But even though I'm
entitled to my winnings,
there's no sense in which,
because it's just a game of luck,
no sense in which, I morally
deserve to win in the first place.
That's an entitlement.
Now contrast the lottery with
a different kind of game.
A game of skill.
Now, imagine the Boston Red Sox
winning the World Series.
When they win, they're
entitled to the trophy.
But it can be always
asked of a game of skill
did they deserve to win?
It's always possible,
in principle,
to distinguish what
someone's entitled to,
under the rules,
and whether they deserve
to win in the first place.
That's an antecedent standard.
Moral desert.
Now, Rawls says distributive
justice is not a matter of
moral desert though
it is a matter of
entitlements to
legitimate expectations.
Here's where he explains it.
"A just scheme answers to
what men are entitles to.
It satisfies their legitimate
expectations as founded upon
social institutions.
But what they are entitled
to is not proportional to
nor dependent upon
their intrinsic worth."
"The principles of justice that
regulate the basic structure
do not mention moral desert
and there is no tendency
for distributive shares
to correspond to it."
Why does Rawls make
this distinction?
What, morally, is at stake?
One thing morally at stake is
the whole question of effort
that we've already discussed.
But there's a second contingency,
a second source of
moral arbitrariness
that goes beyond
the question of whether
it's to my credit
that I have the talents that
enable me to get ahead.
And that has to do
with the contingency
that I live in an society
that happens to prize
my talents.
The fact that David Letterman
lives in a society that
puts a great premium,
puts a great value, on a
certain type of smirky joke,
that's not his doing.
He's lucky that he happens
to live in such a society.
But this is a second contingency.
This isn't something that
we can claim credit for.
Even if I had sole,
unproblematic, claim
to my talents and
to my effort.
It would still be the case,
that the benefits I get
from exercising those talents,
depend on factors that are arbitrary
from a moral point of view.
What my talents will reap
in a market economy.
What does that depend on?
What other people happen to
want or like in this society.
It depends on the law
of supply and demand.
That's not my doing.
It's certainly not the basis
for moral desert.
What counts as contributing
depends on the qualities that this
or that society happens to prize.
Most of us are fortunate
to possess, in large measure,
for whatever reason,
the qualities that our
society happens to prize.
The qualities that
enable us to provide
what society wants.
In a capitalist society it helps
to have entrepreneurial drive.
In bureaucratic society it helps
to get on easily and smoothly
with superiors.
In a mass democratic society
it helps to look good
on television
and to speak in short,
superficial sound bites.
In a litigious society,
it helps to go to law school and have
the talents to do well on LSATs.
But none of this is our doing.
Suppose that we,
with our talents,
inhabited not our society,
technologically advanced,
highly litigious,
but a hunting society,
or a warrior society.
What would become
of our talents then?
They wouldn't get us very far.
No doubt some of us
would develop others.
But would we be less worthy?
Would we be less virtuous?
Would we be less meritorious if
we lived in that kind of society
rather than in ours.
Rawls's answer is, no.
We might make less money
and properly so.
But while we would
be entitled to less,
we would be no less worthy.
No less deserving
than we are now.
And here's the point.
The same could be said
of those in our society
who happen to hold less
prestigious positions,
who happen to have fewer of
the talents that our society
happens to reward.
So here's the moral import
of the distinction between
moral desert and entitlements
to legitimate expectations.
We are entitled to
the benefits
that the rules of
the game promise
for the exercise of our talents.
But it's a mistake and
a conceit to suppose
that we deserve,
in the first place,
a society that values the qualities
we happen to have in abundance.
Now we've been talking here
about income and wealth,
what about opportunities
and honors?
What about the distribution of access
of seats in elite colleges and universities?
It's true,
all of you
most of you first born,
worked hard, strived,
developed your talents,
to get here.
But Rawls asks,
in effect,
what is the moral
status of your claim
to the benefits that attach
to the opportunities
that you have?
Are seats in colleges
and universities
a matter, a kind of
reward, an honor
for those who deserve them,
because they've
worked so hard?
Or, are those seats, those
opportunities and honors
entitlements to
legitimate expectations
that depend for
their justification
on those of us
who enjoy them
doing so in a way that
works to the benefit
of those at the bottom
of society?
That's the question that Rawls's
difference principle poses.
It's a question that
can be asked
of the earnings of Michael Jordan
and David Letterman
and Judge Judy.
But it's also a question
that can be asked
of opportunities to go to
the top colleges and universities.
And that's a debate
that comes out
when we turn to the question
of affirmative action next time.