Captions proofread by @xiaolai, www.lixiaolai.com
Now we turn
Now we turn to the hardest philosopher
we're going to read in this course.
Today we turn to Immanuel Kant
who offers a
different account
of why we have a
categorical duty
to respect the
dignity of persons
and not to use people
as means merely
even for good ends.
Kant excelled at the
University of Konigsberg
at the age of 16.
At age of 31, he got his first job
as an unsalaried lecturer
paid on commission based on
the number of students
who showed up at his lectures.
This is a sensible system that
Harvard would do well to consider.
Luckily for Kant,
he was a popular lecturer
and also an industrious one
and so he eked out a meager living.
It wasn't until he was 57
that he published his first major work.
But, it was worth the wait,
the book was the
"Critique of Pure Reason"
perhaps the most important work
in all of modern philosophy.
And a few years later, Kant wrote the
groundwork for "Metaphysics of Morals"
which we read in this course.
I want to acknowledge
even before we start
that Kant is a difficult thinker
but it's important to try
to figure what he's saying
because what this book is about
is what the supreme principle
of morality is,
number one,
and it also gives us an account 每
one of the most powerful
accounts we have 每
of what freedom really is.
So, let me start today,
Kant rejects utilitarianism.
He thinks that
the individual person,
all human beings,
have a certain dignity
that commands our respect.
The reason the individual is sacred
or the bearer of rights,
according to Kant,
doesn't stem from the idea
that we own ourselves
but instead from the idea
that we are all rational beings.
We're all rational beings,
which simply means
that we are beings
who are capable of reason.
We are also autonomous beings,
which is to say that we are beings
capable of acting and choosing freely.
Now, this capacity
for reason and freedom
isn't the only capacity we have.
We also have the capacity
for pain and pleasure,
for suffering and satisfaction.
Kant admits the utilitarians
were half right.
Of course,
we seek to avoid pain
and we like pleasure,
Kant doesn't deny this.
What he does deny
is Bentham's claim
that pain and pleasure
are our sovereign masters.
He thinks that's wrong.
Kant thinks that it's
our rational capacity
that makes us distinctive,
that makes us special,
that sets us apart from and above
mere animal existence.
It makes us something more than
just physical creatures with appetites.
We often think of freedom as
simply consisting in doing what we want
or in the absence of obstacles
to getting what we want,
that's one way of
thinking about freedom.
But this isn't Kant's idea of freedom.
Kant has a more stringent
demanding notion
of what it means
to be free.
And though it's stringent
and demanding,
if you think it through,
it's actually pretty persuasive.
Kant reasons as follows:
when we,
like animals,
seek after pleasure
or the satisfaction of our desires
or the avoidance of pain,
when we do that
we aren't really acting freely.
Why not?
We're really acting as the slaves
of those appetites and impulses.
I didn't choose this particular hunger
or that particular appetite
and so when I act to satisfy it,
I'm just acting according
to natural necessity.
And for Kant,
freedom is the opposite of necessity.
There was an advertising slogan for
the soft drink Sprite a few years ago.
The slogan was,
"Obey your thirst."
There's a Kantian insight buried in
that Sprite advertising slogan
that in a way is Kant's point.
When you go for Sprite or Pepsi,
you're really 每
you might think that
you're choosing freely,
Sprite versus Pepsi,
but you're actually
obeying something,
a thirst or maybe a desire manufactured
or massaged by advertising,
you're obeying a prompting that you
yourself haven't chosen or created.
And here it is worth noticing Kant's
specially demanding idea of freedom.
What way of acting 每
how can my will be determined
if not by the promptings of nature
or my hunger or my appetite
or my desires?
Kant's answer?
To act freely is to act autonomously,
and to act autonomously
is to act according to a law
that I give myself
not according to the
physical laws of nature
or the laws of cause and effect
which include my desire
to eat or to drink
or to choose this
food in a restaurant
over that.
Now, what is the opposite
of autonomy for Kant?
He invents a special term
to describe the
opposite of autonomy.
Heteronomy is the
When I act heteronomously,
I'm acting according to an inclination,
or a desire,
that I haven't chosen for myself.
So, freedom as autonomy is an especially
stringent idea that Kant insists on.
Now, why is autonomy the opposite
of acting heteronomously
or according to
the dictates of nature?
Kant's point is that
nature is governed by laws,
laws of cause and effect for example.
Suppose you drop
a billiard ball,
it falls to the ground;
we wouldn't say the billiard ball
is acting freely.
Why not?
It's acting according
to the law of nature,
according to the laws
of cause of effect,
the law of gravity.
And just as he has an unusually
demanding and stringent
conception of freedom,
freedom as autonomy,
he also has a demanding
conception of morality.
To act freely is not to choose
the best means to a given end;
it's to choose the end itself
for its own sake.
And that's something
that human beings can do
and that billiard balls can't.
In so far as we act on inclination
or pursue pleasure,
we act as means to the realization
of ends given outside us.
We are instruments rather than authors
of the purposes we pursue,
that's the heteronymous
determination of the will.
On the other hand,
in so far as we act autonomously,
according to a law
we give ourselves,
we do something for its own sake
as an end in itself.
When we act autonomously,
we seize to be instruments
to purposes given outside us,
we become,
or we can come to think of ourselves
as ends in ourselves.
This capacity to act freely,
Kant tells us,
is what gives human life
its special dignity.
Respecting human dignity
means regarding persons
not just as means
but also as ends in themselves.
And this is why it's wrong
to use people
for the sake of other peoples'
well-being or happiness.
This is the real reason,
Kant says,
that utilitarianism goes wrong.
This is the reason it's important
to respect the dignity of persons
and to uphold their rights.
So, even if there are cases,
remember John Stewart Mill said,
"Well, in the long run,
if we uphold justice
and respect the
dignity of persons,
we will maximize
human happiness."
What would Kant's
answer be to that?
What would his answer be?
Even if that were true,
even if the calculus
worked out that way,
even if you shouldn't throw
the Christian's to the lions
because in the long run
fear will spread,
the overall utility will decline.
The utilitarian would be
upholding justice and right
and respect for persons
for the wrong reason,
for a purely a contingent reason,
for an instrumental reason.
It would still be using people,
even where the calculus works out
for the best in the long run,
it would still be using
people as means
rather than respecting them
as ends in themselves.
So, that's Kant's idea
of freedom as autonomy
and you can begin to see how it's
connected to his idea of morality.
But we still have to answer
one more question,
what gives an act its moral worth
in the first place?
If it can't be directed,
that utility or satisfying
wants and desires,
what gives an action
its moral worth?
This leads us from Kant's
demanding idea of freedom
to his demanding idea
of morality.
What does Kant say?
What makes an action
morally worthy
consists not in the consequences
or in the results that flow from it,
what makes an action morally worthy
has to do with the motive,
with the quality of the will,
with the intention for
which the act is done.
What matters is the motive
and the motive must be
of a certain kind.
So, the moral worth
of an action
depends on the motive
for which it's done
and the important thing
is that the person
do the right thing
for the right reason.
"A good will isn't good because of
what it affects or accomplishes,"
Kant writes,
"it's good in itself.
Even if by its utmost effort,
the goodwill accomplishes nothing,
it would still shine like a jewel
for its own sake
as something which has
its full value in itself."
And so, for any action
to be morally good,
it's not enough that it should conform
to the moral law,
it must also be done
for the sake of the moral law.
The idea is that the motive
confers the moral worth on an action
and the only kind of motive that can
confer moral worth on an action
is the motive of duty.
Well, what's the opposite of doing
something out of a sense of duty
because it's right?
Well for Kant,
the opposite would be
all of those motives
having to do
with our inclinations.
And inclinations refer
to all of our desires,
all of our contingently given wants,
preferences, impulses,
and the like.
Only actions done for the sake
of the moral law,
for the sake of duty,
only these actions
have moral worth.
Now, I want to see what you think
about this idea
but first let's consider
a few examples.
Kant begins with an example
of a shopkeeper.
He wants to bring out
the intuition
and make plausible the idea
that what confers
moral worth on an action
is that it be done
because it's right.
He says suppose there's a shopkeeper
and an inexperienced customer comes in.
The shopkeeper knows that he could
give the customer the wrong change,
could shortchange the customer
and get away with it;
at least that customer wouldn't know.
But the shopkeeper nonetheless says,
"Well, if I shortchange this customer,
word may get out,
my reputation would be damaged,
and I would lose business,
so I won't shortchange this customer."
The shopkeeper does nothing wrong,
he gives the correct change,
but does his action
have moral worth?
Kant says no,
it doesn't have moral worth
because the shopkeeper only did
the right thing for the wrong reason,
out of self-interest.
That's a pretty
straightforward case.
Then he takes another case,
the case of suicide.
He says we have a duty
to preserve ourselves.
Now, for most people
who love life,
we have multiple reasons
for not taking our own lives.
So, the only way
we can really tell,
the only way we can isolate
the operative motive
for someone who
doesn't take his or her life
is to think 每
to imagine someone who's miserable
and who despite having an
absolutely miserable life
nonetheless recognizes the duty
to preserve one's self
and so does not commit suicide.
The force of the example is to
bring out the motive that matters
and the motive that matters
for morality
is doing the right thing
for the sake of duty.
Let me just give you
a couple of other examples.
The Better Business Bureau,
what's their slogan?
The slogan of the
Better Business Bureau:
"Honesty is the best policy.
It's also the most profitable."
This is the Better Business Bureau's
full page ad in the New York Times,
"Honesty, it's as important
as any other asset
because a business that deals in truth,
openness, and fair value
cannot help but do well.
Come join us and profit from it."
What would Kant say
about the moral worth
of the honest dealings of members
of the Better Business Bureau?
What would he say?
That here's a perfect example
that if this is the reason
that these companies deal honestly
with their customers,
their action lacks moral worth,
this is Kant's point.
A couple of years ago,
at the University of Maryland,
there was a problem with cheating
and so they initiated
an honor system
and they created a program
with local merchants
that if you signed the honor pledge,
a pledge not to cheat,
you would get discounts of
10% to 25% at local shops.
Well what would you think of someone
motivated to uphold an honor code
with the hope of discounts?
It's the same as Kant's shopkeeper.
The point is, what matters
is the quality of the will,
the character of the motive
and the relative motive to morality
can only be the motive of duty,
not the motive of inclination.
And when I act out of duty,
when I resist as my motive
for acting inclinations
or self-interest,
even sympathy and altruism,
only then am I acting freely,
only then am I acting autonomously,
only then is my will not
determined or governed
by external considerations,
that's the link between Kant's
idea of freedom and of morality.
Now, I want to pause here
to see if all of this is clear
or if you have some
questions or puzzles.
They can be questions
of clarification
or they can be challenges.
If you want to challenge this idea
that only the motive of duty
confers moral worth
on the action.
What do you think?
Yes.
Yeah, I actually have two
questions of clarification.
The first is, there seems
to be an aspect of this
that makes it sort of
self-defeating
in that once you're conscious
of what morality is
you can sort of alter your motive
to achieve that end of morality.
Give me an example of
what you have in mind.
The shopkeeper example.
If he decides that he wants to
give the person the money
to do the right thing
and he decides that
it's his motive to do so
because he wants to be moral
then isn't that sort of
defeating trying to 每
isn't that sort of defeating
the purity of his action
if morality is determined
by his motive?
His motive is then
to act morally.
I see.
So, you're imagining a case
not of the purely selfish
calculating shopkeeper
but of one who says,
well, he may consider
shortchanging the customer.
But then he says, "Not,
or my reputation might suffer
if word gets out."
But instead he says,
"Actually, I would like to be
the kind of honest person
who gives the right change
to customers
simply because it's
the right thing to do."
Or simply, "Because
I want to be moral."
"Because I want to be moral,
I want to be a good person,
and so I'm going to conform
all of my actions
to what morality requires."
It's a subtle point,
it's a good question.
Kant does acknowledge,
you're pressing Kant
on an important point here,
Kant does say there
has to be some incentive
to obey the moral law,
it can't be a self-interested incentive
that would defeat it by definition.
So, he speaks of a different kind
of incentive from that inclination,
he speaks of reverence
for the moral law.
So, if that shopkeeper says,
"I want to develop
a reverence for the moral law
and so I'm going to do
the right thing"
then I think he's there,
he's there as far as
Kant's concerned
because he's formed his motive,
his will is conforming
to the moral law
once he sees the
importance of it.
So, it would count,
it would count.
All right, then, secondly,
very quickly,
what stops morality from becoming
completely objective in this point?
What stops morality
from becoming subjective?
Yeah, like how can 每 if morality
is completely determined by your morals
then how can you apply this
or how can it be enforced?
All right,
that's also a great question.
-- What's your name?
-- My name is Amady.
-- Amady?
-- Yes.
All right,
if acting morally
means acting according
to a moral law out of duty
and if it's also to act freely
in the sense of autonomously,
it must mean that I'm acting according
to a law that I give myself,
that's what it means
to act autonomously,
Amady is right about that,
but that does raise a
really interesting question.
If acting autonomously means acting
according to a law I give myself,
that's how I escape the chain of cause
and effect and the laws of nature.
What's the guarantee
that the law I give myself
when I'm acting out of duty
is the same as the law
that Amady is giving himself
and that each of you gives yourselves?
Well, here's the question,
how many moral laws,
from Kant's point of view,
are there in this room?
Are there a thousand or is there one?
He thinks there's one, which in a way
does go back to this question:
all right, what is the moral law?
What does it tell us?
So, what guarantees 每
it sounds like to act autonomously
is to act according
to one's conscience,
according to a law
one gives oneself,
but what guarantees
that we 每
if we all exercise our reason,
we will come up with
one and the same moral law?
That's what Amady wants to know.
Here's Kant's answer:
the reason that leads us
to the law we give ourselves
as autonomous beings is a reason,
it's a kind of practical reason
that we share as human beings.
It's not idiosyncratic.
The reason we need to
respect the dignity of persons
is that we're all rational beings,
we all have the capacity for reason
and it's the exercise of
that capacity for reason
which exists undifferentiated
in all of us
that makes us worthy of dignity,
all of us,
and since it's the same
capacity for reason,
unqualified by particular
autobiographies and life circumstance,
it's the same universal
capacity for reason
that delivers the moral law,
it turns out that to act autonomously
is to act according to a law we give
ourselves exercising our reason,
but it's the reason we share
with everyone as rational beings,
not the particular reasons we have
given our upbringings,
our particular values,
our particular interests.
It's pure practical reason,
in Kant's terms,
which legislates a priori regardless
of any particular contingent
or empirical ends.
Well, what moral law would
that kind of reason deliver?
What is its content?
To answer that question,
you have to read the groundwork
and we'll continue with
that question next time.
For Kant, morally speaking,
suicide is on a par with murder.
It's on a par with murder
because what we violate
when we take a life,
when we take someone's life,
ours or somebody else's,
we use that person,
we use a rational being,
be use humanity as a means
and so we fail to
respect humanity as an end.
Today we turn back to Kant.
Before we do,
remember this is the week
by the end of which all of you
will basically get Kant,
figure out what he's up to.
You're laughing.
No, it will happen.
Kant's groundwork is
about two big questions.
First, what is the supreme
principle of morality?
Second, how is freedom possible?
Two big questions.
Now, one way of making your way
through this dense philosophical book
is to bear in mind
a set of oppositions
or contrasts
or dualisms
that are related.
Today I'd like to talk about them.
Today we're going to
answer the question,
what, according to Kant,
is the supreme principle of morality?
And in answering that question,
in working our way up to Kant's answer
to that question
it will help
to bear in mind
three contrasts,
or dualisms,
that Kant sets out.
The first,
you'll remember,
had to do with the motive
according to which we act.
And according to Kant,
only one kind of motive
is consistent with morality,
the motive of duty,
doing the right thing
for the right reason.
What other kind of motives are there?
Kant sums them up in
the category of inclination.
Every time the motive for what we do
is to satisfy a desire or a preference
that we may have,
to pursue some interest,
we're acting out of inclination.
Now, let me pause to see
if in thinking about the question
of the motive of duty,
the goodwill,
see if any of you has a question
about that much of Kant's claim.
Or is everybody happy
with this distinction?
What do you think?
Go ahead.
When you make that distinction
between duty and inclination
is there ever any moral action ever?
I mean you could always, kind of,
probably find some selfish motive, can't you?
Maybe, very often people do have
self-interested motives when they act.
Kant wouldn't dispute that
but what Kant is saying is
that in so far as we act morally,
that is in so far as our actions
have moral worth,
what confers moral worth
is precisely our capacity
to rise above self-interest
and prudence and inclination
and to act out of duty.
Some years ago I read
about a spelling bee
and there was a young man
who was declared the winner
of the spelling bee,
a kid named Andrew,
13 years old.
The winning word,
the word that he was able to spell,
was "echolalia."
Does anyone know what echolalia is?
What?
Some type of flower?
It's not some type of flower.
No.
It means the tendency
to repeat as in echo,
to repeat what you've heard.
Anyhow, he misspelled it actually
but the judges misheard him,
they thought he had
spelled it correctly
and awarded him the championship
of the National Spelling Bee
and he went to the judges
afterward and said,
"Actually, I misspelled it,
I don't deserve the prize."
And he was regarded as a moral hero
and he was written up
in the New York Times,
"Misspeller is Spelling Bee Hero."
There's Andrew with his proud mother
and when he was interviewed afterwards,
listen to this,
when he was interviewed afterwards,
he said,
"The judges said
I had a lot of integrity,"
but then he added
that part of his motive was,
"I didn't want to feel like a slime."
All right.
What would Kant say?
Go ahead.
I guess it would depend
on whether or not
that was a marginal reason
or the predominant reason
and whether or not 每
and why he decided to confess
that he didn't actually
spell the word correctly.
Good.
And what's your name?
Bosco.
That's very interesting.
Is there anyone else who
has a view about this?
Does this show that Kant's principle
is too stringent, too demanding?
What would Kant say about this?
Yes.
I think that Kant actually says
that it is the pure motivation
that comes out of duty
which gives the action moral worth.
So, it's like,
for example in this case,
he might have more than one motive,
he might have the motive
of not feeling like a slime
and he might have the motive of doing
the right thing itself out of duty
and so, while there's more
than one motivation going on there
doesn't mean that the action
is devoid of moral worth
just because he has one other motive
because the motive which involves duty
is what gives it the moral worth.
Good.
And what's your name:
Judith.
Well Judith, I think that your account
actually is true to Kant.
It's fine to have
sentiments and feelings
that support doing the right thing
provided they don't provide
the reason for acting.
So, I think Judith actually has
mounted a pretty good defense of Kant
on this question of the
motive of duty.
Thank you.
Now, let's go back to
the three contrasts.
It's clear at least what
Kant means when he says
that for an action to have moral worth,
it must be done for the sake of duty,
not out of inclination.
But as we began to see last time,
there's a connection between
Kant's stringent notion of morality
and his specially demanding
understanding of freedom.
And that leads us to
the second contrast,
the link between
morality and freedom
The second contrast describes
two different ways
that my will can be determined;
autonomously
and heteronomously.
According to Kant, I'm only free
when my will is determined autonomously.
Which means what?
According to a law
that I give myself.
We must be capable, if we're
capable of freedom as autonomy,
we must be capable of acting
according not to a law
that's given or imposed on us
but according to a law
we give ourselves.
But where could such a law
come from?
A law that we give ourselves.
Reason.
If reason determines my will
then the will becomes a power to choose
independent of the dictates of nature
or inclination or circumstance.
So, connected with Kant's demanding
notions of morality and freedom
is a specially demanding
notion of reason.
Well, how can reason
determine the will?
There are two ways and this leads
to the third contrast.
Kant says there are two
different commands of reason
and a command of reason
Kant calls an imperative
an imperative is simply an ought.
One kind of imperative,
perhaps the most familiar kind,
is a hypothetical imperative.
Hypothetical imperatives
use instrumental reason.
If you want x then do y.
It's means-ends reasoning.
If you want a good business reputation
then don't shortchange your customers,
word may get out.
That's a hypothetical imperative.
"If the action would be good
solely as a means to something else,"
Kant writes,
"the imperative is hypothetical.
If the action is represented
as good in itself
and therefore is necessary for a will
which of itself accords with reason,
then the imperative is categorical."
That's the difference between
a categorical imperative
and a hypothetical one.
A categorical imperative
commands categorically,
which just means without reference to
or dependence on any further purpose
and so you see
the connection
among these three
parallel contrasts.
To be free,
in the sense of autonomous,
requires that I act not out of
a hypothetical imperative
but out of a categorical imperative.
And so you see by these three
contrasts Kant reasons his way,
brings us up to his derivation
of the categorical imperative.
Well, this leaves us
one big question:
what is the categorical imperative?
What is the supreme
principle of morality?
What does it command of us?
Kant gives three versions,
three formulations,
of the categorical imperative.
I want to mention two
and then see what you think of them.
The first version,
the first formula,
he calls the
formula of the universal law;
"Act only on that maxim whereby
you can at the same time will
that it should become
a universal law."
And by maxim,
what does Kant mean?
He means a rule that explains the
reason for what you're doing,
a principle.
For example,
promise keeping.
Suppose I need money,
I need $100 desperately
and I know I can't pay it back
anytime soon.
I come to you
and make you a promise,
a false promise,
one I know I can't keep,
"Please give me $100 today,
lend me the money,
I will repay you next week."
Is that consistent with
the categorical imperative,
that false promise?
Kant says no.
And the test,
the way we can determine
that the false promise is at odds
with the categorical imperative
is try to universalize it,
universalize the maxim upon
which you're about to act.
If everybody made false promises
when they needed money
then nobody would believe
those promises,
there would be no such thing
as a promise,
and so there would be
a contradiction.
The maxim universalized
would undermine itself.
That's the test.
That's how we can know
that the false promise is wrong.
Well what about the
formula of the universal law?
You find it persuasive?
What do you think?
Go ahead.
I have a question about
the difference between categoricalism
and a hypothesis
that if you're going to act . . .
Between categorical and hypothetical.
Hypothetical, yeah.
Imperatives.
Right. If you're going to act
with a categorical imperative
so that the maxim doesn't
undermine itself,
it sounds like I am going to
do x because I want y,
I'm going to not lie in dire need
because I want the world to function
in such a way that promises are kept.
I don't want to liquidate
the practice of promises.
Right, it sounds like
justifying a means by an ends.
It seems like an instance of
consequentialist reasoning,
you're saying.
-- Right.
-- And what's your name?
-- Tim.
Well Tim, John Stewart Mill
agreed with you.
He made this criticism of Kant.
He said, "If I universalize the maxim
and find that the whole practice
of promise keeping would be
destroyed if universalized,
I must be appealing somehow
to consequences
if that's the reason not to tell
a false promise."
So, John Stewart Mill agreed
with that criticism against Kant
but John Stewart Mill was wrong.
You're in good company though.
You're in good company, Tim.
Kant has often read,
as Tim just read him,
as appealing to consequences.
The world would be worse off
if everybody lied
because then no one could rely
on anybody else's word
therefore you shouldn't lie.
That's not what Kant
is saying exactly.
Although, it's easy to
interpret him as saying that.
I think what he's saying is
that this is the test,
this is the test of whether
the maxim corresponds
with the categorical imperative.
It isn't exactly the reason,
it's not the reason,
the reason you should universalize
to test your maxim
is to see whether you are privileging
your particular needs and desires
over everybody else's.
It's a way of pointing
to this feature,
this demand of the
categorical imperative
that the reasons for your action
shouldn't depend
for their justification
on your interests, your needs,
your special circumstances being
more important than somebody else's.
That, I think, is the moral intuition
lying behind the universalization test.
So, let me spell out the second,
Kant's second version of
the categorical imperative,
perhaps in a way that's more
intuitively accessible
than the formula of universal law.
It's the formula of humanity as an end.
Kant introduces the second version
of the categorical imperative
with the following line of argument:
"We can't base the
categorical imperative
on any particular interests,
purposes, or ends
because then it would be only relative
to the person whose ends they were.
But suppose, however, there was
something whose existence has in itself
an absolute value . . .
an end in itself . . .
then in it,
and in it alone,
would there be the ground of a
possible categorical imperative."
Well, what is there
that we can think of
as having its end in itself?
Kant's answer is this,
"I say that man,
and in general every rational being,
exists as and end in himself,
not merely as a means for arbitrary use
by this or that will."
And here Kant distinguishes between
persons on the one hand
and things on the other.
Rational beings are persons,
they don't just have a
relative value for us
but if anything has they
have an absolute value,
an intrinsic value,
that is rational beings have dignity.
They're worthy of
reverence or respect.
This line of reasoning leads Kant
to the second formulation
of the categorical imperative
which is this:
"Act in such a way that
you always treat humanity,
whether in your own person
or in the person of any other,
never simply as a means,
but always at the same time,
as an end."
So, that's the
formula of humanity as an end,
the idea that human beings as
rational beings are ends in themselves,
not open to use
merely as a means.
When I make a
false promise to you,
I'm using you
as a means to my ends,
to my desire for the $100,
and so I'm failing to respect you,
I'm failing to respect your dignity,
I'm manipulating you.
Now, consider the example
of the duty against suicide.
Murder and suicide are at odds
with the categorical imperative.
Why?
If I murder someone,
I'm taking their life for some purpose,
either because I'm a hired killer
or I'm in the throes of
some great anger passion,
I have some interest,
some purpose,
that's particular for the sake
which I'm using them as a means.
Murder violates the
categorical imperative.
For Kant, morally speaking,
suicide is on a par with murder.
It's on a par with murder because
what we violate when we take a life,
when we take someone's life,
ours or somebody else's,
we use that person,
we use a rational being,
we use humanity
as a means
and so we fail to respect
humanity as an end.
And that capacity for reason,
that humanity that commands respect,
that is the ground of dignity,
that humanity,
that capacity for reason
resides undifferentiated in all of us
and so I violate that dignity in my
own person, if I commit suicide,
and in murder
if I take somebody else's life.
From a moral point of view
they're the same
and the reason they're the same
has to do with the universal character
and ground of the moral law.
The reason that we have to respect
the dignity of other people
has not to do with anything
in particular about them
and so respect, Kantian respect,
unlike love in this way.
It's unlike sympathy.
It's unlike solidarity
or fellow feeling or altruism
because love and those
other particular virtues or reasons
for caring about other people have to
do with who they are in particular.
But respect,
for Kant,
respect is respect for humanity
which is universal,
for a rational capacity
and that's why violating it,
in my own case,
is as objectionable as violating it
in the case of any other.
Questions or objections?
Go ahead.
I guess I'm somewhat worried
about Kant's statement
that you cannot
use a person as a means
because every person
is an end of themselves,
because it seems that everyday,
in order to get something
accomplished for that day,
I must use myself
as a means to some end
and I must use the people around me
as a means to some end as well.
For instance, suppose that
I want to do well in a class
and I have to write a paper.
I have to use myself
as a means to write the paper.
Suppose I want to buy something,
food,
I must go to the store and use
the person working behind the counter
as a means for me to purchase my food.
Right.
That's true, you do.
What's your name?
Patrick.
Patrick, you're not
doing anything wrong.
You're not violating
the categorical imperative
when you use other people as means,
that's not objectionable
provided when we deal
with other people
for the sake of advancing
our projects and purposes and interests,
which we all do,
provided we treat them
in a way that is consistent
with respect for their dignity
and what it means
to respect them
is given by the
categorical imperative.
Are you persuaded?
Do you think that Kant
has given a compelling account,
a persuasive account,
of the supreme principle of morality?
Reread the groundwork and we'll
try to answer that question next time.